<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The rockes of Christian shipwracke, discouered by the holy Church of Christ to her beloued children, that they may keepe aloofe from them. Written in Italian by the most reuerend father, Marc Ant. de Dominis, Archb. of Spalato, and thereout translated into English</title>
            <title>Scogli del christiano naufragio, quali va scoprendo la santa chiesa di Christo. English</title>
            <author>De Dominis, Marco Antonio, 1560-1624.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 236 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 96 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20606</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7005</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117489</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852702</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852702</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18039</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20606)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18039)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1234:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The rockes of Christian shipwracke, discouered by the holy Church of Christ to her beloued children, that they may keepe aloofe from them. Written in Italian by the most reuerend father, Marc Ant. de Dominis, Archb. of Spalato, and thereout translated into English</title>
                  <title>Scogli del christiano naufragio, quali va scoprendo la santa chiesa di Christo. English</title>
                  <author>De Dominis, Marco Antonio, 1560-1624.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 171, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Bill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M. DC. XVIII. [1618]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of his: Scogli del christiano naufragio, quali va scoprendo la santa chiesa di Christo.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18039:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ROCKES, OF CHRISTIAN SHIPWRACKE, Diſcouered by the holy Church of CHRIST to her beloued Children, that they may keepe aloofe from them. WRITTEN IN ITALIAN BY THE MOST REVEREND FATHER, <hi>MARC ANT. DE DOMINIS,</hi> Archb. of Spalato, <hi>And thereout tranſlated into Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of a fleet of ships sinking on rocks, and a fleet of ships afloat sailing towards a haloed female figure in the clouds</figDesc>
               <head>
                  <q>CITO: LONGE: NVNQVAM.</q>
               </head>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by IOHN BILL. M.DC.XVIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18039:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18039:2"/>
            <head>THE CHVRCH OF CHRIST TO HER MOST deare children wiſheth ſauing health, and peace.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y beloued children, If the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Wracke of Christian ſoules could in the approach be ſenſibly diſcerned, it might of it ſelfe ſerue for a warning-marke, and all both eminent Rocks and vnder-water ſhelfs would be diſcried, and ſo ſhunned. But ſo much the more dangerous, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious is that woefull ſhipwrack, which ſwalloweth vp an infinite number of you, my deare children, in that thoſe, that vndergoe it, neither know, nor once all their life long heed this their owne ruine. Can I then your
<pb facs="tcp:18039:3"/>dolorous Mother, can I brooke this miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable loſse? can I ſuffer ſo many of my chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to bee cast away? Noe, I cannot. Needs muſt I impart the trueth vnto you; I am reſolued to hide nothing from you.</p>
            <p>When in my yong &amp; first teeming daies I felt the wounds, and torments of Heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh perſecutions, very bitter, alas, was the anguiſh of my ſoule, to behold on all ſides ſtreaming riuers of the blood of my tender children ſo impiouſly ſhed by moſt cruel Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, &amp; perſecutors of the faith of <hi>IESVS CHRIST</hi> my Spouſe, and Lord. No ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ceaſed theſe tyrannous perſecutions, but I was beſet with other more dangerous af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions of Hereſies, whereby the bitternes of my ſoule was more encreaſed: In aſmuch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as that first kinde of perſecution was onely outward, ſlaying the bodies of my children, but not hurting their ſoules, nay rather much benefiting them. But this latter pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb facs="tcp:18039:3"/>inward, destroying the ſoules of many, and wounded my very heart, euen the faith of my Spouſe. At length the ſtorme of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies was huſhed; and ſo I ſate me downe in peace, enioying a faire and goodly calme, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>behold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 38.17.</note> 
               <hi>my griefe was moſt bitter in peace.</hi> Peace brought vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me a greater bitternes then any of my former. The per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions of the Heathen, and the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinies of the Heretiques were indeed a bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſeruice to mee; but yet they both had their ſweetning. For, by the former I was made a more fruitfull mother,
<note place="margin">Tertul. Apol. aduerſ. gent.</note> 
               <hi>The blood of the Martyrs being the ſeed where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out more Chriſtians grew;</hi> and by oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of the latter my Officers, and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters became the more watchfull, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed themſelues with more ſtore of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ſound doctrine, and pure faith, and alſo fed my children with ſo much the more exact ſpirituall nouriſhment. But the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes,
<pb facs="tcp:18039:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>which mine owne Officers and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants haue, by reaſon of peace, through their owne idlenes, brought vpon me, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come diuers ages ſince, but in theſe dayes more then euer, distastfull to me.</p>
            <p>From theſe my Miniſters comes this your ſhipwrack; they haue ſet in your way all theſe Rocks, &amp; Shelfes, &amp; Quick-ſands, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſo many of you are caſt away. Peace, and idleneſse haue beene my bane. As stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding-water in wells, ditches, and puddles through want of motion quickly corrupteth, and breedeth wormes, toades, ſnakes, and other ſuch vermine: ſo peace, and idleneſse hath bin to my chiefe Miniſters, Biſhops, &amp; Prelates the cauſe of putrefaction. And ſo they following the crooked bent of corrupt nature, and running a madding after their owne concupiſcences, haue first giuen ouer themſelues in prey to <hi>Auarice.</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ery large haue bin of old the almes, and oblations of
<pb facs="tcp:18039:4"/>faithfull, and very deuout people, for the maintayning of their ſpirituall fathers Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theſe followed the bounty of Emperours, and other Chriſtian Princes, and benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors; they, in their vnaduiſed deuotion hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping vpon me more and more riches, haue, I may ſay to you, brought my Ministers to a good paſſe. For my part, I was at my high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, and in best esteeme, whilest I went in a thinne coate, ſuch as I was cladde withall when my Spouſe <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> betroathed himſelfe to me. My moſt proper orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, my trueſt greatneſſe conſiſteth, not in outward pompe, nor ſuperfluous worldly commodities, but in ſpirituall, and inward vertues. My beloued <hi>Dauid</hi> wrote con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning me,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 45.13.</note> that <hi>the king's daughter is all-glorious within.</hi> And my worthy ſonne St. <hi>Hierome</hi> hath noted concerning me, that,
<note place="margin">Hiero. de vita Malchi.</note> 
               <hi>after that I was entertained by Chriſtian Princes, I grew greater in
<pb facs="tcp:18039:5"/>ſtate, and wealth, but abated much in vertue.</hi> In thus ſaying, (alas the while) hee came too neere the truth. Yet this was none of my fault: It was mine owne Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, that haue brought this ſcar vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me: eſpecially in that they, without my allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, or weeting, haue diuided among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues that ſtocke of temporal goods, which, by my appointment, for diuers ages remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in common, and whereout, by the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique diſpenſers, or stewards, dayly, or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethly portions were wont to bee allotted to euery of thoſe my Ministers for their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsary maintena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce; but afterward by their <hi>Auarice</hi> properly was brought in. And I would to God they had there stayed, and contented themſelues with their parts ſo aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to them: then had that bene tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and now perhaps were neceſsary. But (as the guiſe of the couetous man is neuer to ſay hee hath enough) they haue gone on,
<pb facs="tcp:18039:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>inuenting new deuiſes of purchaſe, though with the apparant danger of their owne, &amp; their peoples, my childrens, ſoules, and to the no ſmall hinderance of all kind of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall gaine.</p>
            <p>Hauing afforded ſome, but neuer full, content to <hi>Auarice,</hi> they, by the ſway of naturall corruption, caſt themſelues farther in prey to <hi>Ambition.</hi> They ſaw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues esteemed, and exalted by me, like fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers reſpected, reuerenced, and honored by my children: whereupon, forgetting that they were no other then my Ministers, and ſeruants, and that their office, and charge was to ſerue my children, rather then to command, (euen as they were taught by the example, and precept of my Spouſe, their and my Lord and Maſter, who <hi>came not to be miniſtred vnto,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 20.28.</note> 
               <hi>but to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi>) they began to think ſo highly of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and to ſwell ſo bigge with the conceit
<pb facs="tcp:18039:6"/>of their office, that they pretended them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be Lords ouer my houſe, and very Princes, and ſo caried very ſmall reſpect to me, whoſe miniſters, and ſeruants they are. After that this Infernall ſpirit of <hi>Ambition</hi> had entred into them, they now, not deigning any lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger to employ their ioynt paines in digging my vineyard, (which is the very office allotted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by my <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi>) ſet themſelues to contend with one another about Primacy, &amp; Ancestry, and one to domineere ouer the other, and to play the commander, as is well obſerued, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by my <hi>Euſebius.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. hiſtor. lib. 8. cap. 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe bee the two horrible wilde beaſts, theſe the two monſters, namely <hi>Auarice</hi> and <hi>Ambition,</hi> which haue cast my Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers headlong into very important errors, ſo that, putting away a good conſcience, they haue alſo made ſome ſhipwrack concerning the faith: And, that which is worſe, to
<pb facs="tcp:18039:6"/>boulſter out their <hi>Couetouſneſſe,</hi> and <hi>Ambition,</hi> they of their owne head, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out my foreknowledge, or conſent, nay to my great griefe, &amp; notwithſtanding my ceaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe reclaimes, and continuall protests a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, euen to the ſtopping of my mouth, by downe-right violence, they haue thruſt vpon the world their owne inuentions, and eſtabliſhed their owne ordinances, not drawne out of that Teſtament, which my Spouſe left to me, and them, namely the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures; but craftily hammered out of their owne capricious proiects, and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the preiudice, downefall, and ruine of your poore ſoules, my deare children. Theſe their fancyfull deuices, and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous inuentions, brought in after thoſe many ages of my purity and ſingleneſſe, were paſt, theſe being founded vpon <hi>Aua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice,</hi> and <hi>Ambition,</hi> and cunningly cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vnder the water, yet ſo that they ſtand
<pb facs="tcp:18039:7"/>neere the toppe of it, are the Rockes, and Shelfes, and Quick-ſands, vpon which full many a wracke is made in the chiefeſt parts of my Dominions.</p>
            <p>Now therefore, my beloued children, eſpecially you, that finde your ſelues, though to my diſhonour and great preiudice, vnder the yoake of my daughter of <hi>Rome,</hi> I will diſcouer to you all theſe Rockes, as I haue formerly diſcouered them to diuerſe other my daughters, whereby they haue beene much ſecured from danger. Afford mee attention with diligence, for your part. I, for mine, proteſt in the preſence of my Spouſe, your Lord, and mine, and forwarne you, that from henceforth the ſhipwrackes, which you ſhall ſuffer, ſhall bee your owne fault, and not mine, if vpon vaine ſcruples, or feares ſuggeſted by the diuell, and cheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by thoſe, who in name and profeſsion beare themſelues as my ſeruants, but are
<pb facs="tcp:18039:7"/>indeede my most deadly enemies, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells against me, you ſhall forbeare to open your eyes, and to bee aduertiſed of thoſe dreadful Rocks, which for your euerlaſting good I heere compendiouſly, as in a Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mappe, decipher out before your eyes, to the end that you, eſcaping out of them, or rather keeping farre and wide from them, may euery of you guide the veſſell of his ſoule with all ſafetie to the hauen of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſaluation. Giue eare therefore to me. And although <hi>Couetiſe</hi> hath riſen before <hi>Ambition,</hi> and giuen the firſt blow to my Miniſters; yet, foraſmuchas <hi>Ambition</hi> hath been the firſt of the two that hath built to your coſt, I will therefore beginne with the Rockes, which <hi>Ambition</hi> hath layd, and afterward will paſſe to thoſe which grew out of <hi>Auarice.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:18039:8"/>
            <list>
               <head>THE FIRST PART hath theſe Rocks.</head>
               <item>1 THE <hi>Papacie. Fol.</hi> 1.</item>
               <item>2 <hi>Temporall power.</hi> 30.</item>
               <item>3 <hi>Infolded faith.</hi> 38.</item>
               <item>4 <hi>Exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication.</hi> 45.</item>
               <item>5 <hi>The Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements of the Church.</hi> 56.</item>
               <item>6 <hi>Falſe vnion.</hi> 69.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>THE SECOND PART hath theſe Rocks.</head>
               <item>1 THE <hi>Maſſe. Fol.</hi> 73</item>
               <item>2 <hi>Auricular, Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> 97.</item>
               <item>3 <hi>Purgatory, together with Satisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and Indulgences.</hi> 117.</item>
               <item>4 <hi>Inuocation of Saincts.</hi> 142.</item>
               <item>5 <hi>Images and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques.</hi> 148.</item>
               <item>6 <hi>Merits.</hi> 158.</item>
            </list>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>PROVERB. 1.20.</bibl>
                  <p>Wiſedome crieth without; ſhe vttereth her voice in the ſtreets. She crieth in the chiefe place of concourſe, in the opening of the gates, in the citie ſhe vttereth her words, ſaying, How long, yee ſimple ones, will yee loue ſimplicitie, and the ſcorners delight in ſcorning, and fooles hate knowledge? Turne you at my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe; behold, I will powre out my Spirit vnto you, I will make knowen my words vnto you.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18039:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE FIRST PART. ¶ <hi>The rockes, which are founded on Ambition.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="rock">
               <head>
                  <hi>The firſt Rocke:</hi> The Papacie.</head>
               <p>CHRIST my Lord, and Spouſe, <hi>the Sauiour of my body,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5. c 3.</note> mine one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true, and liuing Head, as hee hath promiſed to <hi>be with me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 28.20.</note> 
                  <hi>euen vnto the ende of the world;</hi> ſo he neuer would like, that I ſhould ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge any other ſpouſe, or Lord, or Head, then himſelfe. Indeed once he died, and that was to waſh me with his owne blood, to make for me a vitall bath, and lauer of ſaluation; but he quickly roſe againe, and <hi>dieth no more,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 6.9.</note> 
                  <hi>death hath no more dominion ouer him:</hi> and howſoeuer in his moſt ſacred manhood hee remaineth in heauen, farre diſtant from me in regard of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily preſence; yet notwithſtanding by his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit hee is here vpon earth continually preſent with me; and ſo by way of Headſhip, or Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18039:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>he hath no need of any Succeſſor, or Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant, in that himſelfe, being mine owne, and onely Head, doeth infuſe into me all vigor, all motion, and all direction, which I, being his Body, receiue from him, being ſuch an Head, as is not dead, but liuing, not ſeuered from mee, but ſtill growing to me. What need then haue I of a viſible Head? Whatſoeuer an head vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally doeth, or can do to its owne body materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, all that is ſpiritually wrought in me by my Chriſt, and that with abundant ſufficiencie. I am indeed a body, but rather an inuiſible and ſpirituall one, then viſible, and materiall: in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard whereof my imployments are for the moſt part ſpirituall, and inuiſible. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I haue need of ſuch an Head, as, by his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall and inuiſible influence, may keepe mee in life, and gouerne mee, and furniſh mee with ſtrength for my performances. In this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe a viſible head can ſtead me iuſt nothing. And as for that ſmall deale of viſibilitie, and outwardneſſe, which concerneth me in this world, I haue no need, in that behalfe, of any head for influence, but of a Miniſtery onely for execution, which is very ſufficient for mee. So haue I need of viſible hands and feet, but
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18039:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>not of a viſible head; inaſmuch as that, which is to be wrought viſibly, and outwardly in me, is fully, and completely performed by the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Miniſtery of my members, without any proper office of an Head.</p>
               <p>Hence was it that my Chriſt, as ſoone as he eſpouſed me, did appoint me diuers Miniſters, who in my viſible employments ſhould all of them ſerue my turne, but as members onely, and not as an Head. Of this the firſt were the twelue Apoſtles, who were no other then meere Miniſters both vnto Chriſt, and to me alſo, not maſters, nor Heads properly ſo called. Neither was it his pleaſure, that any of them ſhould be ſet ouer me, as a proper Head, or as a Lord, or Maſter in any wiſe: but his appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was, that, vnder himſelfe my onely King, Lord, Maſter, and huſband, I ſhould be left, as Lady and Miſtreſſe ouer all his, and my Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, or ſeruants: which is acknowledged by <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſtiling himſelfe <hi>my Miniſter.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Col. 1.25.</note> As indeed were likewiſe all the other Apoſtles, euen <hi>S. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> himſelfe; who auoucheth as much,
<note place="margin">Actes 1.17.</note> whileſt hee calleth his Apoſtleſhip <hi>a Miniſtery.</hi> And ſurely he neuer had, nor profeſſed himſelfe to haue any ſuch Headſhip, or Lordſhip ouer me,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18039:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>but was enterteined in my ſeruice only, as were the reſt alſo. Neither can it euer be found, that Chriſt committed to S. Peter any greater, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther charge, dignitie, iuriſdiction or authority, then to the other Apoſtles, who all, and euery of them were, by the inſtitution of Chriſt himſelfe, abſolutely equall in all charge and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, which they bare in reſpect of me. Nay, my Spouſe was ſo farre from affoording to any of them a pretended title of greatneſſe aboue the reſt of his fellowes, that, when as they diuers times caſt out words among themſelues, and diſputed concerning Soueraigntie, he alwayes checked them,
<note place="margin">Luke 22.26.</note> and would haue them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine as brethren, and ioyntly to attend his ſeruice, and mine, and to keep themſelues from affecting dominion, either ouer me, or among themſelues. And when he tooke his leaue of them at his departure vp into heauen, they ſtill dreaming on this idle fantaſie, and asking him whether he would then <hi>reſtore the Kingdome to Iſrael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Actes 1.6.</note> (namely, that hereby they might know which of them ſhould bee exalted aboue the reſt) they had the repulſe of him in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, with intimation that they ſhould attend, and that ioyntly with equall charge and office,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18039:10"/>no other thing, then to be <hi>throughout the world witneſſes vnto him of his reſurrection.</hi> Certes, if euer there were a time for him to ſpeake plaine, and to declare, that hee left in his roome his Lieutenant Peter, or ſome other, to bee their, and mine Head, then moſt of all it behooued, when in regard of his bodily preſence he gaue them his farewell: and yet he then recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded me, his Spouſe, to them all together ioynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and equally, that they might employ their attendance on me:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hane ſponſam ſuis amicis ſponſus abiens commendauit.</hi> Aug. cont. 2. Gaud. epiſt. lib. 2. cap. 12.</note> Which is well obſerued by my holy doctor <hi>S Auguſtine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There was no reaſon for it, nor decencie in it, that I, beeing his Spouſe, and an vniuerſall Mother, ſhould bee domineered ouer, and lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by any one of mine owne members, mine owne ſonnes, nay mine owne ſeruants. As for my <hi>Peter,</hi> certainly he neither exerciſed, nor e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer chalenged any ſuch ſoueraignety ouer me, or ouer his Collegues, and fellowes; neither did he pretend to be an vniuerſall Pope, or on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Vicar-generall of Chriſt. One of the firſt actions of employment about me, after the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent of my Spouſe into heauen, was the orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Deacons, which ſhould take care of the widowes, and poore. And this action was
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18039:11"/>neither performed, nor gouerned by Saint Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but by all the twelue Apoſtles ioyntly. This being my perpetuall ordinance,
<note place="margin">Actes 6.2.</note> as I haue receiued it from my Spouſe, that my Miniſters, and Officers all together ioyntly ſhould treat concerning the externall good guidance of my family: So likewiſe, when there were ſome to bee ſent into <hi>Samaria,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Actes 8.14.</note> to finiſh the good worke of their conuerſion, Saint Peter was ſo farre from taking vpon him to ſend whom hee pleaſed, that hee himſelfe was by the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Apoſtles choſen and ſent thither, as one of the many. When the firſt controuerſie, brake out in <hi>Antioch</hi> concerning the obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ancient Iudaicall Ceremonies, to whom did <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> thinke they ought to haue recourſe, for certaine reſolution in that point? Surely if Chriſt had left Saint Peter his Vicar, they ought to haue addreſſed themſelues to him principally; yet did they ſay among themſelues, and reſolue, that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooued them to goe vp to Ieruſalem, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult <hi>about this queſtion with the Apoſtles,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Actes 15.2.</note> 
                  <hi>and Elders</hi> of that City. Which accordingly was done: and there was gathered a Councel, and that ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned, and ordered, not by <hi>Peter</hi> alone, but
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18039:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Apoſtles, of themſelues, ioyntly met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with the Elders alſo. And howſoeuer Saint <hi>Peter</hi> (as the moſt ſtept in age, and the moſt ancient Apoſtle, and much reſpected by the reſt of the Apoſtles) was the firſt that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered his opinion; yet Saint <hi>Iames</hi> proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſame, did further adde of his owne, &amp; did ſtrike vp the matter. And the publique letters, diſpatched in that behalfe, were not ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the name of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> but of all the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and Elders in common. Neither was it a ſleight checke, or reproofe, wherewith St. Paul openly tooke vp Saint Peter,
<note place="margin">Galat. 2.11.</note> for halting in the inſtruction of the faithfull: which hee might doe; beeing the Apoſtles were, in their office, and care of my affaires, all of them e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall, and euen brothers among themſelues.</p>
               <p>And howſoeuer yee read in the Goſpell, that Chriſt ſaid to Peter, <hi>Thou art Peter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 16.18.</note> 
                  <hi>and vpon this rocke will I build my Church,</hi> yet are ye not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to deeme, that Peter had hereby com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto him any dominion, or command ouer mee, or that hee was entruſted with a lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger cure, then the reſt of the Apoſtles. For, theſe words (according to the interpretation of them communicated to me by the ſpirit of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18039:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>my Spouſe, and declared by my moſt ſincere, pure, and holy Doctors) import, that that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, made by Saint Peter, ſaying, <hi>Thou art Chriſt the Sonne of the liuing God,</hi> muſt bee that Rocke, whereon was to bee grounded that faith, which is indeed my foundation and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porter. By this Rocke is alſo vnderſtood he, whom Peter confeſſed, euen <hi>Christ,</hi> who is my true foundation, whereon, and not on Peter, I was built: for, if Peter had bene my founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, certes more then once ſhould I haue fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len by his falls.
<note place="margin">Matth. 26.70.</note> But if any man will preſſe yet further,
<note place="margin">Galat. 2.12.</note> that <hi>Christ</hi> doth in theſe words promiſe that I ſhould bee built vpon Peter, let him vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand withall, that to build my houſe is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but to get and prouide <hi>petras,</hi> ſtones, and to reare them vp in my walles; that is to ſay, to preach the Goſpell, to conuert the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleeuers, and to bring them home to mee. And foraſmuch as Peter was to bee, of all the twelue (or rather by the default of <hi>Iudas,</hi> eleuen) Apoſtles, the moſt feruent, and moſt diligent in conuerting a many of ſoules, therefore to him, as to a principall Miniſter, and Builder, there was a prediction made of the worke, which hee was to performe, and that I was to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18039:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>be built vpon him; namely that <hi>Chriſt</hi> had eſpeciall confidence in his care, for the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of my houſe, as being more zealous then the other ten Apoſtles. But it followeth not thence, that hee was the onely builder, or that hee was choſen for the onely <hi>Architect,</hi> or Chiefe-builder: for, the other Apoſtles alſo were Maſteres of this Art, and laid to their hands for the rearing vp of my Fabrique, and in ſpeciall, Saint <hi>Paul laboured more abundantly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.10.</note> 
                  <hi>then they all,</hi> and ſo ſurpaſſed, euen Saint <hi>Peter</hi> himſelfe, in edifying me, and hath acquit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for a <hi>ſkifull Maſter-builder.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.10.</note>
               </p>
               <p>In like maner, when ye heare it ſaid to Saint <hi>Peter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 16.19.</note> 
                  <hi>I will giue thee the keyes of the kingdome of heauen, and whatſoeuer thou ſhalt bind vpon earth, ſhall bee bound in heauen, and whatſoeuer thou ſhalt looſe on earth, ſhall bee looſed in heauen;</hi> yee are to remember, that the ſame was alſo ſpoken to all the reſt of the Apoſtles. So likewiſe, though the keyes were promiſed to <hi>Peter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 18.18.</note> yet it was neuer ſaid to him, I will giue the keyes to thee onely. And when this promiſe was perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, it was accompliſhed, not in <hi>Peter</hi> onely, but in all the Apoſtles ioyntly, when <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſayd to them, <hi>Goe, and teach all nations.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 28.19. Ioh. 20.21.</note> 
                  <hi>As my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18039:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſent me, ſo ſend I you:</hi> namely with the ſame authority, and power, but yet miniſteriall in you, which is principall in me. What power therefore had <hi>Peter,</hi> other then that, which all the reſt had, to whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> imparted his owne power? Moreouer, <hi>Chriſt</hi> gaue the keyes to them all, as alſo the power of binding, and looſing, when he ſaid ioyntly to all, <hi>Whoſoeuers ſinnes yee remit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 21.23.</note> 
                  <hi>they are remitted vnto them: and whoſoeuer ſins yee retaine, they are retained.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Saint <hi>Peter</hi> had no other part in my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, nor other power, then the reſt of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles had.</p>
               <p>Laſtly,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 21.15.</note> if it was ſaid to <hi>Peter, Feed my ſheepe and my lambes:</hi> know yee likewiſe, that feeding is principally preaching, inſtructing, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtering the Sacraments. All which was committed to all the Apoſtles, <hi>Goe and teach all nations, baptizing them &amp;c. As my Father ſent me, ſo ſend I you.</hi> Nor did <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſay to <hi>Peter;</hi> Bee thou the only ſheepeheard of my ſheepe: But he, by a ſpeciall application, thus beſpake him, to feed his ſheepe, that hee might comfort, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage, and reuiue him, whom hee ſaw then caſt downe with griefe, for hauing ſo lately ſhewed himſelfe a Renegate, whereupon hee
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18039:13"/>might with good reaſon miſdoubt himſelfe, to haue lapſed from his Apoſtleſhip. But <hi>Christ</hi> recomforteth him by this his ſpeach, as ſaying to him, I reſtore thee to thy Apoſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and, in recompence of thy crime in baſe deniall of mee, I now enioyne thee the more zeale, and charity in feeding, and attending my poore flock; and therefore, in lieu of thy thrice denying mee, I will, that thou thrice confeſſe thy loue to mee: and ſo I recommend this of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to thee in a more ſpeciall manner, euen by way of penance, which in general I haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted alſo to the reſt ioyntly: but to them I do not redouble my charge, becauſe they haue not as thou, denied me. And euen this he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of him, when hee foretold his fall, and ſaid to him, <hi>I haue prayed for thee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 22 32.</note> 
                  <hi>that thy faith faile not: therefore, when thou art conuerted, ſtrengthen thy brethren.</hi> That is to ſay, if thou ſhalt ſee the faithfull, which hereafter ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in me, to fall ſometimes by weakeneſſe and infirmity, it is your part to animate, and ſtrengthen them by your owne example, whom beeing fallen I haue rayſed vp againe: and with this care of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firming thy brethren, I burthen thee in ſpecial more then the reſt; for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18039:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>that thou by thine enſample canſt doe this, whereas others are like to doe that office by their exhortations onely, and not by ſo liuely an example of their owne.</p>
               <p>And if any doubt ariſe in your mindes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Chriſt's</hi> ſpeaking onely to <hi>Peter</hi> in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the reſt of the Apoſtles, and of ſuch things, as were to bee imparted vnto all, and if thereupon yee ſhould ſurmiſe, that he did this to intimate heereby to the reſt <hi>Peter's</hi> Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignety ouer them, as if hee were to bee the <hi>Cheife,</hi> and ordinary Paſtor, and all the reſt as his adiutors, and aſſiſtants, you muſt awake out of this error. Verely <hi>Chriſt</hi> neuer had any ſuch purpoſe, or intention, nor (as I haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) can he now ſuffer any ſuch conſtruction: neither did euer any ſuch interpretation come into my head. But well may yee know, that, in this action, not any ſuch Primacy of <hi>Peter,</hi> but other myſteries are included, which bee theſe:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Christ</hi> giuing charge concerning that, which was to bee committed equally to them all,
<note place="margin">Cypr. de vnit. Eccleſ.</note> yet directeth his ſpeech onely to one, that it might hence be gathered, that I, his Spouſe, was to be but one, and that they ſhould not imagine that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18039:14"/>euery of them might make a ſeuerall foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their owne, by ſchiſmes, and diuiſions, but that their ioynt labours ſhould bring forth one, and the ſame worke, namely mee, beeing one, and the ſame Church. And this is Saint <hi>Cyprian's</hi> interpretation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi> in ſpeaking onely with <hi>Peter,</hi> doth appoint him, as the Head in order, and the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident of the Apoſtolique Colledge, which is a dignitie, and preheminence, not of authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, nor iuriſdiction, but onely of ranke, and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; that thereby the Apoſtolicall Company might attaine to a perfect collectiue vnity, ſuch as is in a Collegiate-Chapter with their Deane, or in a Senate with their Preſident; and that heereby the Apoſtles might gather, how well vnity did pleaſe their Maſter, in that, hee ſpeaking to <hi>Peter</hi> onely,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hieron. l.</hi> 1. <hi>aduerſ. Iouin.</hi>
                  </note> as to the Head in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and Foreman of that Society, they ſhould in no wiſe fall aſunder in diuiſions, but keepe themſelues in perfect vnion, and ſo, holding all together, they might the better ſet themſelues to tend me, who am but one. And thus Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> expoundeth it.</p>
               <p>Onely <hi>Peter</hi> was ſpoken to, as beeing my type, and repreſenting mee. <hi>Chriſt</hi> did then
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:18039:15"/>treat with him, as with my Proctor, or Atur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney: and ſo when <hi>Chriſt</hi> deliuered him the keyes, he tooke ſey ſin of them, not to his owne priuate vſe, but to mine, and in the name of the publique. For, there were then included, and repreſented in <hi>Peter,</hi> all my Prelates preſent, or ſucceeding: and ſo in the name of them al, and to the vſe of them all he both receiued the keies,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. de Agon. Chriſt. c.</hi> 30. <hi>&amp; in pſalm.</hi> 108. <hi>&amp; in Io. tract.</hi> 124. <hi>&amp;c. Ambr. de dig. Sacerd. c.</hi> 2.</note> and the charge of feeding my flocke, and buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding my houſe. Not that he had liberty to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow thoſe keyes at his pleaſure, or to appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate them to any one, whom he would make his ſucceſſor: but that I, in his perſon, did then take them to the vſe of my Prelates. Like as an Atturney taking Liuery and ſeiſin for an incorporation, doth not receiue it as an owner, or diſpoſer, nor hath thereby authority to doe his pleaſure with it, but by this Attornement the right, and property inureth to the Body or Society repreſented. And, as for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Peter,</hi> he receiued indeede the keyes for himſelfe alſo, inaſmuch as himſelfe was one of them, in whoſe name he tooke them: And this is Saint <hi>Augustine's</hi> iudgement.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Chriſt maketh this conference with <hi>Peter</hi> onely, that all Prelates, caſting their eye
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18039:15"/>on Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> might from him take a iuſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell and patterne of gentleneſſe,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Leo. Serm.</hi> 3. <hi>de ſu. Aſſump.</hi>
                  </note> and other E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopall vertues: Which is the expoſition of Saint <hi>Leo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe, and other like myſteries haue I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes vnderſtood concerning this action of <hi>Chriſt</hi> with <hi>Peter:</hi> but that therein ſhould be compriſed any Soueraignety, or Papacy, or commiſſion for the only ordinary Paſtorſhip, there hath not bin in all my houſe, for the firſt fiue hundreth yeeres, any one found ſo idle, as to dreame of ſuch an inuention.</p>
               <p>And though I ſhould bee ſo prodigall, as to grant, that which I haue ſhewed to bee moſt falſe, namely that Saint <hi>Peter</hi> was ordained by Chriſt an vniuerſall Pope ouer mee, yet what hath the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> to doe with St. <hi>Peter?</hi> The holy Scriptures giue-in no euidence at all, that euer <hi>Peter</hi> was at Rome. Onely humane hiſtories report it. And as for diuine Records, they plainely ſhew, that he departed not from the coaſts of Iudea till the fiftieth yeere of our Lord. Thereafter wee finde in the Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtique hiſtories, that before his going into the Weſt,
<note place="margin">Hieron. in Pet.</note> hee preached the Goſpell in the Eaſterne parts, in Pontus, Cappadocia, Aſia, Bythinia,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18039:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>&amp;c. for the ſpace of diuers yeeres; and that hee ſuffered martyrdome in <hi>Rome,</hi> about the ſixty eight yeere of our Lord. It is not poſſible there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that he could haue bene Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> ſo long as fifteene yeeres, much leſſe twenty fiue: Which ſpace of time is very vnaduiſedly aſſigned him by ſome paſſable ancient writers.</p>
               <p>But, to omit theſe arguments from compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, ſuerely neither Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> nor any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Apoſtle was euer made Biſhop of any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular City, whereto his ſeat might be entay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by a perpetuity. This is repugnant to the very office of Apoſtleſhip, which was by <hi>Chriſt</hi> their Chiefe Lord inſtituted an order of profeſſed <hi>errants</hi> throughout the whole world, when he gaue them their commiſſion,
<note place="margin">Matth 28.19. Mar. 16.15.</note> to <hi>Goe and teach all Nations,</hi> and <hi>to preach the Goſpell to euery creature,</hi> that is to ſay, to all men whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer throughout the world. They had no po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer therefore to fix themſelues on any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar place, nor to binde themſelues to it, but their duty was to attend the enlargement of my tents,
<note place="margin">Act. 1.8.</note> 
                  <hi>beginning from Ieruſalem, to the vtmoſt parts of the earth:</hi> and when they had founded any particular Church, and vnited it to me the vniuerſall Mother, they were then to paſſe on
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18039:16"/>for new plantations. Who therefore is ſo har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as to coope vp Saint <hi>Peter</hi> at Rome, and to binde him to a particular Biſhopricke there till the day of his death? And if hee finiſhed his courſe at Rome, certainely hee died not with the title of Biſhop of Rome, but of an vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Apoſtle. For, neither that, nor any other <hi>See</hi> could be choſen by him, as proper to him, beeing by his function, and calling to paſſe to and fro through the world. But if hee ended his life in any heatheniſh place, where, as then, there was no Church planted, who then was to be his ſucceſſor in the Papacie? It is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a groundleſſe, and idle aſſertion, to name perſonall ſucceſſors to any of the Apoſtles; whenas none of them all was a locall Biſhop, (for, as for Iames Biſhop of Ieruſalem,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Conſtit. Apoſt. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>c</hi> 14. <hi>&amp; Doroth. in ſynopſi &amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> hee was none of the twelue Apoſtles, but a Diſciple be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide that number) and therfore all Biſhops ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed all the Apoſtles <hi>in Solidum,</hi> that is to ſay, euery particular Biſhop, whatſoeuer hee bee, holdeth the place, and office of the Apoſtles, who by Chriſt's inſtitution committed their charge, and office to the Biſhops, and thoſe to other Biſhops, and ſo to others by continuall ſucceſſion till the end of the world; and that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18039:17"/>by vertue euen of thoſe words of <hi>Christ</hi> to the Apoſtles.
<note place="margin">Io. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>As the Father hath ſent me, ſo I ſend you.</hi> That is to ſay, As the Father hath giuen mee power to ſend you, ſoe I giue power to you to ſend others, and to giue them likewiſe the ſame miſſiue power, which I giue you, and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath giuen me. And hereupon it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that euery Biſhop, in reſpect of the diuine inſtitution, hath the very Apoſtolicall power, that is, <hi>vniuerſall</hi> in habite, or generall qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, which he is enabled to exerciſe actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in any part of the world. But, in regard of my reſtreining precept, for the auoyding of diſorder, and confuſion, there are long ſince limitations ſet downe, and particular diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of euery ones Dioceſſe. Now therefore, when as there is no perſonall ſucceſſion vnto any of the Apoſtles, who can fetch his claime from <hi>Peter?</hi> who from Iohn? who from any other of the Apoſtles? Nay, if ſuch plea were good, there could not bee aboue 12. or at the moſt 13. Biſhops in the world. And to afford perſonall ſucceſſion to <hi>Peter</hi> onely, with deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of it to all the reſt, is to beate the aire with idle words, and to goe againſt the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>Certeinely for a thouſand yeeres and more,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18039:17"/>I neuer heard in all my family from the mouth, or penne of any pious and holy Author, that the Biſhop of Rome was acknowledged for an Vniuerſall Pope. Indeed the Biſhops of Rome themſelues haue endeuoured to make me an vnderling, and to put me vnder their feete, and to make themſelues my Head, and Lord, and Maſter, with great wrong to my true, and one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Head, Lord, and Spouſe CHRIST IESVS: but they haue long attempted it in vaine. For they haue met with ſtout oppoſitions. St. <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> a moſt holy Biſhop of Aſia did ſtrongly oppoſe <hi>S. Victor B. of Rome. S. Irenaeus</hi> B. of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons did the like; and this befell neere the times of the Apoſtles.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cypr. l.</hi> 1. <hi>ep.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp; l.</hi> 3. <hi>op.</hi> 13. <hi>Apud. Cypr. ep.</hi> 74. <hi>Pamel.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> beareth himſelfe as a companion, and Colleague with <hi>S. Steuen, and S. Cornelius</hi> both Biſhops of Rome, euen in the Vniuerſall gouernment of the Church; and ſpareth not to hold his owne againſt them. <hi>S. Firmilian</hi> B. of Ceſarea in Cappadocia handleth the ſame Steuen of Rome very homely, and ſetteth nought by his excommunications.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſeb. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>Iulij Epist. ad Orientales &amp; Socrat. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp; Sozom. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 5 <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> The Church hiſtories are plentiful in ſhewing, how lightly <hi>S. Iulius,</hi> though B. of Rome, was ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed by the Biſhops of the Eaſt, and by the Councell of <hi>Antioch,</hi> (which, for the more part
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18039:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>of it, was Catholique, and Orthodoxe) for no leſſe matter, then that he would make himſelfe an Vniuerſall Iudge, euen in the cauſes of the Eaſterne Church, and yet in the end hee was faine to ſit downe, and be quiet. The Councell of <hi>Nice</hi> acknowledgeth not the B.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Con. Nic. can.</hi> 6</note> of Rome for any other, then one of the three then <hi>Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs,</hi> who had their limited iuriſdictions: ſo alſo doeth the firſt Councell of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and the Councell of <hi>Chalcedon.</hi> None of the ancient fathers my deareſt children, for the ſpace of 600. yeeres together, hath any the leaſt impreſſion of the Romane Papacie; by whom the B. of Rome was neuer taken for other, then at the moſt for <hi>Patriarch</hi> of the Weſt. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fricane Church (in thoſe dayes one of my moſt noble daughters,) affronted the Romane Church, and would not in any wiſe, that ſhe ſhould exerciſe any power ouer her in the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of the Eccleſiaſticall policie; and went ſo farre, as in open Councels to reſiſt her, in which euen the renowned <hi>S. Augustine</hi> bare his part. The like hath bene many times practiſed by the Churches of <hi>Rauenna,</hi> of <hi>Aquilege,</hi> &amp; of <hi>Milan.</hi> And <hi>S. Gregory</hi> in oppoſing the title of Vniuerſal Biſhop in the Patriarch of Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18039:18"/>muſt needs oppugne the ſame in the Romane alſo by force of very ſtrong argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p>It is to no purpoſe therefore to ſeeke here vpon earth one Vicar-generall for my Spouſe Chriſt, who hath no need of a ſucceſſour or Vicar, inaſmuch as he is head of my body, and his Spirit is ſufficient for me, onely Miniſters, and labourers are needfull for him, and for me: and thoſe were, firſt the bleſſed Apoſtles, and after them their ſucceſſors. So that, in reſpect of labouring, and working, and ſetting right alſo the externall gouernment of my family,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cypr. l.</hi> 4. <hi>ep.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp; l.</hi> 3. <hi>ep.</hi> 13. <hi>&amp; de Simpl. Prae. lat. Ambr. in</hi> 1. <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 11. <hi>Chryſoſt. hom.</hi> 17. <hi>in Mat. &amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> thoſe Apoſtles all ioyntly, and <hi>in ſolidum,</hi> (as S. Cyprian expreſly affirmeth) hold the place of Chriſt, and are equally his Vicars, but in labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and working for my behoofe: and all Biſhops likewiſe are with very good reaſon by my holy doctors, ſtyled by this title of <hi>Christs Vicars,</hi> and not S. <hi>Peter</hi> onely. And ſo in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of my true Head, and Spouſe, I am vnder a perfect Monarchie: but as for the worke of my Miniſters, they performe their office in a kind of Ariſtocratie, without any Monarchie at all amongſt them. They are like a company of workemen, which haue vndertaken a large
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18039:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>Vineyard, euery man his parcell: or like a troope of many ſhepheards all ſeruants of one great Shepheard, who percel out among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues the feeding of a very great flocke, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of there is one intire Lord, and Maſter, that onely <hi>grand Sheepheard.</hi> And ſurely when the owner of a vineyard hireth many laborers to dig it, hee doth not giue any dominion, or iuriſdiction to any of them, ouer either the vineyard, or their fellow-workemen; and, if it be his pleaſure to appoint any to aſſiſt the workemen, and to direct them in their labors, either hee commeth among them himſelfe in perſon, or ſendeth one of his ſonnes, or his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, or deputy, whoſe office then muſt bee, not to delue, and toyle with the reſt of the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers, but only to ouerſee, and to prouide, that they doe their taske. I pray you aske Saint <hi>Peter</hi> whether he were hyred by <hi>Chriſt</hi> to bee a labourer in his vineyard, or to bee a ſurueyor. Verely hee will anſwere you, that he was one of the labourers, and diggers in my vineyard, and not a factor, or ſurueyor, or deputy. His office therefore was, not to command others, but to worke himſelfe.
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.9. 1. Tim. 5.18.</note> For, all the Apoſtles were <hi>Oxen</hi> for the plough and <hi>for treading out
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18039:19"/>the corne:</hi> nor would Saint <hi>Peter</hi> haue ſuffered his necke to bee withdrawne from this yoake. Let not therefore the Biſhoppe of Rome thus without all ground vaunt himſelfe for the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Vicar of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> nor vnder this title (equally common to all other Biſhops with him) keepe me downe, and oppreſſe me, and together with me all my children.</p>
               <p>Nor may you ſuffer your ſelues to bee delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by a falſe, but very common, imagination, that it behoueth me to haue one viſible Head, and one vniuerſall Gouernor. For, in ſuch ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as this, yee are not to ſet downe for good, that, which mens fancies doe conceaue; but ye are to haue an eye to that, which <hi>Chriſt</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hath ordayned. And foraſmuch as he, as I haue ſhewed, will bee my onely Head, and ſole Commander; and, for externall manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, hath appointed that his laborers ſhould among themſelues in common, and <hi>in ſolidum,</hi> without Monarchy, in a kinde of Ariſtocrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call forme, ioyne together, for the directing of my affaires, by way of Synods and Councels, as neceſſity ſhall require; therefore one ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme viſible Head ouer me neither is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, nor was euer ordayned, nor is deſired. And
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:18039:20"/>if ſo many temporall Eſtates in this world are ſufficiently gouerned, without a Monarch, in a Democraticall, or Ariſtocratical forme, why doe ye ſuffer your braines to be peſtered with a falſe imaginary neceſſity of hauing a meere man to bee the Monarchicall gouernour ouer my houſe? and conſider not what a woe caſe I were in, if I ſhould hang on the ſleeue of one man, who hath no priuiledge againſt any er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, or miſery.</p>
               <p>Perhaps yee will aske mee, how then crept the Papacy into Rome, where now it carieth ſo high a ſayle? whereto I am ſure, that, whilſt I was a yong, and ſmall tenderling, both the Apoſtles, and likewiſe thoſe Biſhoppes, which immediatly ſucceeded them, did indifferently, without any ielouſie of concurring iuriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or affectation of ſoueraignety, agree toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the ordeining of other Biſhoppes, and Miniſters, and committing to them the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Goſpel and planting throughout the world new particular Churches. Which yong daughters of mine beeing thus multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and inlarging mee farre and neere, the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of preuenting confuſion did bring into my houſe, an holeſome, holy, and neceſſary or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:18039:20"/>that there ſhould be diuiſion of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, and in Prouinces diſtinct Biſhopricks, and Dioceſſes; and ſo the Biſhops of one Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince ſhould attend the directing, and gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of their owne precincts onely, and not intermeddle with the Prouinces of others, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they were thereto requeſted, or publique neceſſity ſo vrged. My ſelfe, ſeeing this cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome brought in by neceſſity, approoued the ſame, and did moreouer ordaine, that in euery Prouince the Biſhop of the Mother City (that is of the place, which was the ſeat of the chiefe Magiſtrate, or otherwiſe conſpicuous for ſome ciuile reſpect) ſhould bee the chiefe, and conſecrate the Biſhops of that Prouince, and in the ſteade of the Synode of his whole Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, ſhould diſpatch certaine affaires pertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to mee, that ſo the Biſhoppes of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince might not be encombred with meeting together vpon euery ſmall occaſion. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in the <hi>Romane</hi> Empire, which at the time of my eſpouſall to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and for three or foure ages after, was in its greateſt flouriſh, there were then three moſt renowned Cities,
<note place="margin">Hegeſip. de excid. Hieroſ. l. 3. c. 5.</note> moſt eminent aboue the reſt in honour, and ſecular power; namely firſt <hi>Rome</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> the chiefe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:18039:21"/>and principall ſeat of the Empire; ſecondly, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandria</hi> in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> where the Emperors De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty remayned; thirdly, <hi>Antioch</hi> the mother-Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of all the Eaſt; in regard hereof the Biſhops of theſe three grand Cities were the three firſt <hi>Metropolitanes.</hi> Afterward alſo the number of Churches ſo encreaſing, that theſe three ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced not, and the Prouinces which grew too large, beeing thereupon, for my conueniency, deuided into more, and leſſer Prouinces, (with appointment, that alwayes the Biſhoppe of the principall City of ſuch a Prouince ſhould bee the Metropolitane thereof) the three aforeſaid, in regard that they had beene my firſt Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politanes, were honoured with the titles of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs,</hi> and indued with certaine priuiledges, which I was not vnwilling that they ſhould enioy. To whom alſo I did afterward, by way of priuiledge, adde two other <hi>Patriarchs,</hi> one of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> (as ſoone as that City became a ſeat of the Empire beeing called another <hi>Rome</hi>) and the other of <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus my vnthankfull daughter the Church of Rome, hauing bene courteouſly entertei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ennobled, enriched, and exalted by diuers deuout Emperours, vſing the aduantages,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:18039:21"/>which by little and little ſhe gained, partly by temporall greatneſſe, which then ſhined faire vpon her, partly for that I had often good vſe of her helpe in the midſt of my troubles, and garboiles, which hereſies brought vpon me, wherein ſhe ſtood me in good ſtead, by procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring mee fauour, and countenance of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Emperours, as alſo by the credit and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation ſhe had abroad fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe great Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and S. <hi>Paul,</hi> which were her foſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and breeders vp, yet ſhe, I ſay, impudently abuſing all this, did about a thouſand yeeres agoe enter into a bold rebellion againſt me, not vouchſafing to remaine ſtill my daughter, nor acknowledging me for her mother in any wiſe, but ſeeking to make herſelfe my mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, and to domineere ouer me. But moſt of all about 550. yeeres after, ſince the times of that firebrand <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> and ſince the totall ruine of the Romane Empire, this daughter of mine, being high-growne in greatneſſe, and pride, as ſhee began to withdraw her necke from the yoke of a temporall Lord, who with his rod might hold her in obedience to me, ſo would ſhe needs alſo abandon her due place, which ſhe held with me, of being a member
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:18039:22"/>of my body, from which ſhe rent herſelfe by an horrible ſchiſme; and diſdeyning to bee a member of it, would haue no nay but perke aboue me, and make herſelfe my Head by ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannicall vſurpation. And whereas, firſt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the appointment of my Spouſe, ſhe ſhould receiue life, and vigor from me, as euery member of the Body doeth, from its coniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with the whole, as being a part thereof, ſhe, by tearing herſelfe off from being a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, to put forward for the Headſhip, hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly loſt all that ſpirit, and vigor, which eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry particular Church partaketh with and from mee,
<note place="margin">Cypr. de vnit. eccleſ.</note> 
                  <hi>euen as branches deriue their vigor from the roote, ſtreames from the fountaine, and beames from the Sunne;</hi> which is <hi>S. Cyprians</hi> compariſon. And moreouer ſhe hath bene ſo bold with me, as to diſpoile me of my robes, and ornaments, and to rob me of my proper name; and now ſhee, ſhe onely muſt be ſtiled the vniuerſall Church, the Catholique Church, the mother of the faithfull, the pillar of trueth, the Spouſe of Chriſt, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Behold therefore here an infamous, and dreadfull rocke. For, whoſoeuer abandoneth me, to cleaue to her, hee is out of the Arke of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:18039:22"/>
                  <hi>Noah; he, not hauing me to his mother,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cypr. ibidem.</note> 
                  <hi>hath not God to his father.</hi> Whoſoeuer is a follower of that tyrant, which vſurpeth my dignity and tramp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth downe my authoritie, he certainely fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth not Chriſt my true Spouſe, but <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ.</hi> No Church can be vnder Chriſt, vnleſſe it be firſt vnited to me: and all Churches, that enioy the graces flowing from Chriſt, doe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take them by my meanes, and ſo farre forth, as they are my daughters, and limmes growing vnto me, who am the Body of Chriſt. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Romane Church, inaſmuch as a daughter, or member ſhe will not be, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or Head, which faine ſhe would, ſhe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be, betweene both ſure ſhe hath no part in me. And whoſoeuer danceth after ſuch a ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical and rebellious ring-leader, muſt needs himſelfe be a ſchiſmatique, and rebel: and who ſo followeth the vſurping Pope, muſt engage himſelfe to beleeue euery falſhood, and fiction that is thruſt vpon him, and ſo ſhall be ſure to tumble downe headlong after ſuch a guide. Thus the Papacie ſheweth it ſelfe to bee the grand and moſt dangerous rocke of all the reſt, againſt which ſo many poore Chriſtian ſoules daily daſh themſelues. And ſo much for this
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:18039:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>mother-Rocke. The reſt I ſhall paſſe ouer more briefly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="rock">
               <head>¶ The ſecond Rocke. Temporall Power.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O farre haue my Churchmen bene puffed vp with Ambition, that they haue not onely claimed, but alſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, and exerciſed temporall power in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny meerely ciuill, and temporall affaires, chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenging to themſelues, as in my right, a power ouer Clerkes to impriſon, and baniſh them, and to inflict reall forfeits, and corporall paines vpon them; yet can none of my Prelats pretend for any power otherwiſe, then as the ſame belongeth to mee. And I, for my part, from my conſcience confeſſe, that I haue not receiued from my Spouſe any the leaſt tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall power concerning any temporall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faire whatſoeuer: but all the power I haue, is wholly and meerely Spirituall. For, the end, whereto I am ordeined, being wholly, and onely ſpirituall, (namely to guide the ſoules of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:18039:23"/>my children vnto eternall bleſſednes, which is ſupernaturall and ſpirituall) it followeth, that all the meanes which I am to worke by, muſt be of their owne nature Spirituall, and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall: and therefore mine owne, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per power can extend it ſelfe no further, then to things Spirituall onely. My Lord <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, what other power did he exerciſe, then meerely Spirituall? Did hee euer thruſt himſelfe into any temporall affaire? S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Thoſe that are ſet ouer my children,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 13.17.</note> 
                  <hi>are to watch ouer their ſoules, and to render accompt of them.</hi> My care therefore properly, and wholly concerneth mens ſoules. As for their bodies, and bodily, or ciuill affaires, they haue other gouernours, namely temporall Princes. The ſame <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith alſo, that <hi>No man,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.4.</note> 
                  <hi>that warreth vnto God, entangleth himſelfe with the affaires of this life.</hi> Moreouer, by the ioynt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of my holy doctors, it is manifeſt, that my employment is wholly and onely in cure of ſoule, which alſo is not denied by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers the moſt renowmed Biſhops of Rome: as <hi>Hormiſda Epiſt.</hi> 21. <hi>Gelaſius de Anath. vinc. &amp; Epiſt.</hi> 10. <hi>Symmachus in Apologet. Nicolas the</hi> 1. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 8. And why, I pray you, is my power deſcribed
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:18039:24"/>ordinarily in holy writ by the name of a <hi>Chaire,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>th. 23.2.</note> but that it conſiſteth in teaching, and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting, this power of mine being principally inſtructiue, and doctrinall? <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaid to his Apoſtles,
<note place="margin">Luke 22.25.</note> that <hi>The Kings of the Gentiles exerciſe Lordſhip ouer them, But ye ſhall not be ſo:</hi> thereby inferring, that it belongeth not to the officers of my family to exerciſe dominion, or ciuill coactiue iuriſdiction. S. <hi>Hierome</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Kings rule ouer men,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hieron. ep. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>will they, nill they; but the prieſt ruleth onely thoſe, that are willing to be ſubiect to him.</hi> The reaſon is, for that it is not in my reach to enforce any man. S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> very well ſaith of me,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Chryſ. hom.</hi> 3. <hi>in Act. Apo.</hi>
                  </note> that <hi>I cannot impoſe any thing by authoritie;</hi> that is, in ſuch maner as pretending power to compell others to obey me.</p>
               <p>True it is, that religious, and deuout Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to doe mee honour, and for my ſake to vouchſafe ſome priuiledge to my officers, haue afforded mee the fauour, to haue the exerciſe of a certaine ciuil, and criminall Iuriſdiction o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer my owne Miniſters: but ſuch grants as theſe are at the courteſie, and in the liberty of the grantors. And yet hereupon my Prelats cary their heads too high, and lay claime to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt from the ciuill Magiſtrate, all Clearkes,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:18039:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>and Monkes, with their very hangbyes, and lickſpits. And this Rocke is very dangerous, euen to my Clergy themſelues, who not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are heereby emboldened openly to diſobey the Magiſtrate in his ciuill gouerment, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo hide vnder this cloake of exemption a foule heape of heynous ſins, and enormities, liuing as they doe, debauchedly, and without feare, either of God, or of the ciuill ſword: the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of iuſtice in ſuch caſes by my Miniſters being either too too gentle, ſlacke, and ſleepy, as it is ordinarily, or, on the contrary, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times too cruell, bloudy, and barbarous.</p>
               <p>This Rocke is ſo much the more harmefull, and dangerous, in that the Biſhops of Rome, cloaking themſelues with my mantle, thereby make pretenſion to mount aboue Princes, Kings, and Emperours, and to bee iudges ouer them, arrogating to themſelues authority to ouerrule them at their pleaſure, in their ciuill gouerment, and in their lawes; nay, moreouer to depriue them of their kingdomes, and free their ſubiects from their bounden duty, and oath of fealty: and this not onely in caſe of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, but vpon any other occaſion which the Popes in their humor ſhall conclude to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:18039:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>and ſufficient. An horrible and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable pretenſion, and altogether contrary to the law of God. This Rocke ſurely is foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Diuell himſelfe, wherat ſo many of my children ſplit themſelues, and for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the Pope's ambitions, forfeit their goods, honours, fame, liberty, life, and ſoule. By this helliſh pretenſion, rebellions are ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp in Kingdomes, infamous and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable murthers of Kings are plotted, the peace of the whole world is troubled, brutiſh enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities are committed: and all this ſpringeth only from Papall ambition.</p>
               <p>It is moſt certaine, and notorious, that by the law of God, and of nature, expreſly confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the holy Scriptures, euery one ought in conſcience, vnder the guilt of moſt heynous mortall ſin, to obey his lawfull Prince, in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters concerning the ciuill eſtate, whether the ſame Prince be good, or euill. <hi>Let euery ſoule bee ſubiect to the higher powers.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 13.1. 1. Pet. 2.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Bee ſubiect to your Maſters, not onely to the good and gentle, but alſo to the froward.</hi> And for certaine, I neuer receiued any power to diſanull the bond of God's lawes. Whence therefore hath the Pope gotten ſuch power, that he preſumeth to diſoblige ſubiects
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:18039:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>from that naturall bond, which tyeth them to be entirely ſubiect to their lawfull Prince in ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill maters, and thoſe things which concerne the temporall gouerment? It is a meere gull, &amp; foppery, that hee ſhould pretend to depoſe Kings from their thrones, and depriue them of their crownes, and in this wiſe to let looſe their ſubiects from their obedience, whenas, without all dobut ſuch depriuations, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, are meere <hi>temporall buſineſſes;</hi> and no power of mine extendeth it ſelfe beyond ſpirituals. The Pope's arch-flatterers confeſſe, that it followeth hence, that he cannot <hi>directly</hi> depoſe Kings; yet will they haue him enhabled to doe it <hi>indirectly,</hi> namely as ſuch matters are occaſion of ſome ſpirituall good, or euill. But this, ſay I, is impoſſible. For, a thing is ſaid to be done <hi>indirectly,</hi> when it neceſſarily followeth vpon another thing which is done <hi>directly.</hi> As for example, when a thiefe robbeth a trayuai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of his cloathes, and he, thus left naked, dieth with cold, this thiefe hath robbed the man <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly,</hi> but killed him <hi>indirectly.</hi> In like maner it ſhould be ſhewen what ſpirituall action the Pope doth <hi>directly,</hi> by his ſpirituall power, whereupon neceſſarily, but <hi>indirectly</hi> the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:18039:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>of a King, or depriuing him of his temporals doth enſue. But it is impoſſible that any ſuch action ſhould bee ſhewed. For there cannot be any greater ſpirituall action atchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by my proper power, then Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. And who would euer come to that height of abſurdity, as to ſay (and yet ſome haue ſaid it, and beleeued it) that a Prince being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated is held in the ſame inſtant to be alſo depriued of his kingdome, and depoſed? And yet my very nouices know, that excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication medleth not with any temporalls. A rich man beeing excommunicated doth not thereby loſe his poſſeſſions; nor a noble man his nobility; why then ſhould a King by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication loſe his crowne?</p>
               <p>Now therefore ſee what a terrible Rocke this is. A toy takes the Pope in the head to beare the people in hand, that their Prince is an heretique, and excommunicate, and ſo depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of his kingdome, and that they are to riſe againſt him, and to call in another to reigne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them: Theſe ſimple wretches, being miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the Popes falſe doctrine, will needes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey God, to obey the Pope. And thus firſt they herein ſinne mortally, and caſt away their
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:18039:26"/>ſoules; then are they alſo moſt iuſtly puniſhed for traytors, as they are, and ſo farewell goods, life, and all. Neither will the matter bee ſalued vp by that, which the Romaniſts reply, ſaying, Obey your Prince, and ſweare fealty to him in ciuill obedience: but when the caſe ſo falleth out, that the Pope commandeth you other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, then renounce this obedience. Nay, but obedience due to Princes is perpetuall, abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, and without any reſeruation, or conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for, God ſo commandeth.
<note place="margin">Act. 5.</note> And <hi>wee must obey God, rather then men.</hi> It behooueth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by God's law to ſweare obedience, and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, in matters concerning the <hi>temporall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment,</hi> vnto euery naturall liege Lord, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any reſeruation; and conſequently euery ſubiect ought to declare himſelfe, when hee is ſo required, that hee ſweares, and promiſes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall, and abſolute obedience, any whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, or whoſeſoeuer, declaration, commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, excommunication, or ſentence to the contrary notwithſtanding. For, in this world there is no power, that can diſoblige a man fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this perpetuall, and abſolute obedience com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the law of God himſelfe. And in like manner the depoſing, or depriuing Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:18039:27"/>Princes is to bee attempted by none but God's immediate hand, to whom onely it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth <hi>to tranſlate kingdomes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 4.25.</note> And, as for any power of mine, eſpecially that cannot in any maner, neither <hi>direct</hi> nor <hi>indirect,</hi> lawfully at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt any ſuch depriuations. Let euery one therefore remaine ſubiect, and obedient vnto his owne Prince, in things concerning <hi>tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall gouernment:</hi> nor let him thinke, that hee euer can bee aſſoyled by any power on earth, though Eccleſiaſticall, from ſuch his entire o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="rock">
               <head>¶ The third Rocke. Implicite Faith.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ruell, and peſtilent ambition! The Pope, to the end that his vſurped ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie may not be diſcouered, and that he may be taken for a god vpon earth, by ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſeduced people, or rather that they may be made pliable, and capable to admit for good any falſhood, and forgery, which the Pope, for the aduancing his owne greatneſſe, ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:18039:27"/>to them, cauſeth them to be perſwaded, and taught, that in matter of faith, it is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for euery of them to beleeue, whatſoeuer the holy, Catholike, Romane mother-Church doth hold, and beleeue. Verely I, that am the vniuerſall Church, I,
<note place="margin">Mat. 28.20. 1. Tim. 3.15.</note> to whom the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall aſſiſtance of the Spirit of my Spouſe is promiſed, (and not to the Romane) I, that am the pillar, and ground of truth, yet dare not be ſo bold, as to aſſure my children, that this <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folded faith</hi> ſufficeth them, namely, to beleeue vnder generall termes, whatſoeuer I beleeue. How then ſhee, now ſwarming with errours, and falſhood, and being nothing, but ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and auarice, how dares ſhee bee thus bold? My beloued Saint <hi>Paul</hi> would not haue his <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians</hi> thinke,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.24.</note> that hee would <hi>beare dominion ouer their faith,</hi> which hee did ſweetly inſtill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, and not thruſt it vpon them by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and domineering. But Rome will haue euery man, will hee, nill hee, by all meanes to beleeue, and reſt in, whatſoeuer ſhee determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, and commandeth, and to ſubſcribe his beleefe to all that ſhee beleeueth and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, or rather to whatſoeuer ſhee inuenteth and imagineth, though indeed herſelfe beleeue
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:18039:28"/>it not, nor hold it for any point of faith, but for a matter of ſtate; &amp; vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this point of policy ſhe taketh order, that thoſe inuentions, which ſhee knoweth to bee no matters of faith, but onely to ſerue her ambition, and couetouſneſſe, muſt be giuen out for points of faith.</p>
               <p>Rome cannot abide, that yee, my children, ſhould bee zelous in ſeeking to know what it is that yee are to beleeue; for, by ſuch enquiry you would diſcouer her trickes: and therefore ſhee telleth you, that you are ſafe, if yee haue this <hi>enuelopped faith,</hi> and beleeue all that ſhee beleeues. And if ſo be any of you make a ſtand vpon any particular, beeing one of thoſe arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, which ſhee in point of policy hath inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, (and which ſhall hereafter be declared by me in my deſcry of theſe Rockes) then ſhe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently mufleth vp your eyes, and blindeth you, and ſendeth to you her owne attendants, the Prieſts, and Friers, preachers, and confeſſors, who wholly depending on her, are all at her deuotion, &amp; they declare vnto you, that <hi>Rome</hi> hath decided the point to be an article of faith. And thus, when yee are bound to beleeue all that the Church of Rome beleeueth, and maintaineth, that is, whatſoeuer ſhe teacheth,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:18039:28"/>and auoucheth, as fit to be held, and beleeued, ye muſt needs play at hoodman-blind, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing loaden with dangerous ſcruples, ſtumble vpon the rocke of many an error, and fiction, and ſo incurre miſerable ſhipwracke.</p>
               <p>There is indeed a kinde of vnweeting obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, which is holy, and good, nay neceſſary, but vnfolded, which concerneth the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall articles of my faith. Such as are, the vnitie of the Godhead, and Trinitie of perſons in one eſſence, and nature: the incarnation of the Word, with the conioyning of two di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct natures, the diuine and humane, in the one onely diuine perſon of my Spouſe <hi>Chriſt:</hi> that he ſuffered, and ſhed his blood, and gaue his life vpon the Croſſe for my redemption: that he roſe againe by his owne power: and that hee aſcended, and is glorified in heauen, where he remaineth my true Mediatour, and continuall Aduocate with the Father: and that he is to bee iudge of all men, to giue to euery one according to his owne workes, either life, or death euerlaſting. In the beleeuing theſe, and other ſuch Articles, euery childe of mine muſt yeeld his eyes cloſed vp by obedience, without curioſitie, or recalling them to the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:18039:29"/>principles of humane reaſon. For theſe are the fundamentals, wherein all Catholique Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome is well reſolued, and ſetled with ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute agreement. But in many other points, either neceſſary, or not neceſſary to ſaluation, there is danger,
<note place="margin">2. Cor 21.</note> that ye may be deceiued. (For, oftentimes <hi>Satan transformeth himſelfe into an Angel of light.</hi>) Therefore euery of you, that hath any heart, and ſpirit at all, ought to open his eyes, and looke well into that, which is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to him, to be beleeued, either by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, or expreſly, and to examine it with Chriſtian, and ſober diligence, whether that, which your Preachers, and confeſſors, and writers teach you concerning ſpiritual things, (who too often, vnder the name of my Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, are wolues in ſheepes-cloathing, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els, but the miniſters of humane ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and auarice) be conformable to the holy Scriptures, and vnto my refined and through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-eſtabliſhed iudgement; mine, I ſay, that is, of the Vniuerſall Church, ſuch as I was for the firſt foure, or fiue vncorrupted ages, and ſtill am alſo in regard of my ſelfe; but not ſuch as the <hi>Romane,</hi> by vſurping my name, doeth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe, and vaunt herſelfe to be. For if you ſhall
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:18039:29"/>walke on blindfold, vnder this <hi>enfuddling faith,</hi> after blinde guids, ye ſhall, they, and you too, hit vpon the rocks, and tumble into the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernall pit.</p>
               <p>For theſe reſpects, which I haue named, <hi>Rome</hi> would faine haue you remaine ſtill muf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fled vp with this <hi>cloudy faith;</hi> and, to keepe you in your ſpirituall blindneſſe, ſhe hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued you of the vſe of holy Scripture; ſhee will not ſuffer it to be imparted to all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the vulgar tongues; ſhe prohibites it, ſhe hinders it. Verily a moſt horrible crueltie. God commanded, not onely <hi>Moſes,</hi> not <hi>Aaron</hi> onely, and the reſt of the Prieſts, not onely the Scribes, and doctors of the Law, and Phariſees; but generally all his people, that they ſhould alwayes haue the Scripture before their eyes. In this is ſtored vp your daily bread: but in ſtead of making you abound with this bread, thoſe, whom you call your ſpirituall fathers, take it from you; and ſo may yee ſtarue, for them. Nay, in ſtead of this bread, they put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your hands either the ſtones of ſtrange do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, which are marueilous hard for you to chew, as that you are to ſpend your liues for the maintenance of the Pope's humors, or elſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:18039:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>the ſcorpions of errors, and falſhood, which bite, and ſting your very ſoules, or, at the moſt, the courſe browne-bread of their pamphlets concerning Chriſtian doctrine, and other ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuels which they name ſpirituall. Wherein, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they can doe no leſſe, (for, then ſhould they appeare to bee open profeſſed wolues) there are ſet downe ſome good foundations of many good Catholick verities, but vnder the cruſt of this good wheaten-bread, the courſe crumbe is deliuered to you, or rather the poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the manifold errors, and ſuperſtitions of humane, if not diueliſh, doctrine; thereby to cheriſh in your ſimple ſoules ſuch reuerence, and obedience to the Pope, Prelates, Prieſts, and Friers, as their ambition, and auarice ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth after. As for other bookes, which diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer theſe their iugglings, <hi>Rome</hi> doeth ſlande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly bruit them to be hereticall, and prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biteth them by vaine, and childiſh terrors of excommunications: and all this, that ye may not open your eyes, but remaine blinde for euer. Looke well to this.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="rock">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:18039:30"/>
               <head>¶ The fourth Rocke. Excommunication.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a wonderfull, or rather miſerable deuiſe and craftie tricke of the Popes, for the mainteining their tyrannie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer your ſoules, and making themſelues to be reuerenced, feared, and held for gods vpon earth; that they proiect to beare you in hand, that the keyes, giuen me by <hi>Chriſt</hi> my Spouſe, are thunderbolts, and fierie darts in the hands of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> as being the ſucceſſor of <hi>Iupiter Capitolinus.</hi> Behold the deceipts, and cunning of this new <hi>Iupiter.</hi> There was neuer any thunderbolt, that ſtrake, or hurt any man, vnleſſe it were actually darted out: but they put a vaine ridiculous ſcare-crow vpon you, making you beleeue, that they haue certaine cloſe thunderbolts in a corner, which of themſelues fly abroad, and ſmell out, euen in the moſt ſecret cloſets, thoſe that doe, or ſay any thing which may diſpleaſe the Pope, though neither the parties themſelues bee knowne to him, nor any hint giuen what they
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:18039:31"/>doe. Alas, what poore fooles are they, that giue credit to this?</p>
               <p>Theſe my keyes, which you ſee in my hands, no doubt, are mannageable by my Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats and Miniſters, and haue power ſometimes alſo to thunder out an <hi>Excommunication.</hi> But you muſt know, that I am to cary an hand in the guiding of ſuch thunderbolts: and, if they be darted foorth contrary to my order preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed me by my Spouſe, they are of no force at all, and haue no other operation, then to make a vaine rumbling to ſcare yong children withall.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Excommunication,</hi> my beloued children, is of diuers ſorts in my family. The firſt is, when any of my children, hauing committed ſome grieuous, publique &amp; notorious crime, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he hath ſcandalized all his brethren of that particular Church, where he remaineth, for the recalling him vnto true, wholeſome, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward repentance by outward medecinall ſhame, is not onely reproued by the Prelate in the publique Congregation, when my chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren come together vnto ſpirituall exerciſes, but alſo is expreſly forbidden to receiue the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred communion of the holy Euchariſt, and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:18039:31"/>of the Lord's Supper: and ſo is kept off for ſome time, vntill he make ſatisfaction vnto God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, and to the Church outwardly, by pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentiall workes impoſed vpon him by the ſaid Prelate.</p>
               <p>A ſecond ſort of <hi>Excommunication</hi> is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more rigorous; when as one of my chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, being a publique, and notorious ſinner, is, for one, or more, grieuous, and ſcandalous faults, not onely put backe from the holy Communion, but alſo from all other meetings, that is, from all holy aſſemblies, and is prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited from entring into the Church with the reſt of the faithfull brethren to whatſoeuer ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred exerciſe, whether hearing of the word of God, or receiuing the holy Sacraments, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſent at the publick holy Seruice, &amp; prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: and this reſtraint to endure for a time, by way of wholſome &amp; medicinall penance, that by this his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion of face, both he may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue griefe for his ſinne committed, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may take example by him, and be ſtriken with an holy terror, for the ſhunning of ſuch ſinnes. Both the one, and the other of theſe two <hi>Excommunications</hi> is taken away by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Reconciliation, when he, hauing with
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:18039:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>due humiliation performed what was impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed on him, and giuen the Church outward e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of his true inward repentance, is now readmitted both to the Church, and to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Communion: and both theſe may truely be called <hi>the leſſer Excommunication.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third, and moſt terrible <hi>Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> which I haue learned out of the Goſpel is, when one of my children, hauing bene giuen ouer in prey vnto grieuous, publicke, notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and ſcandalous ſinnes, after he hath bene tried, but all in vaine, by the two precedent me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicinall <hi>Excommunications,</hi> being now incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigible, is wholy cut off from the number of the faithfull, and vtterly caſt off from being my child, and ſeuered from my body, that is, from the body of <hi>Christ</hi> my Spouſe, and cut off, as a dead, and rotten member, and conſequently deliuered vp vnto Satan, and held as if he were a Gentile and Publican, depriued of all the bleſſings, graces, and heauenly riches, which are to be found within my houſe. This is the true, and dreadfull thunderbolt, which may moſt fitly bee called <hi>the greater Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus you ſee that the two firſt <hi>Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:18039:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>are rather outward, then inward, rather medicines, then puniſhments; hauing exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall effects, and not inwardly working vpon the ſoule, otherwiſe then indirectly, and by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers deductions: namely ſo farre, as vpon the two firſt <hi>Excommunications</hi> the remiſſion of the ſin remaineth in a ſort ſuſpended, <hi>etiam in coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo,</hi> euen in heauen alſo, vntill it be remitted him by me on earth according to the promiſe made vnto me by <hi>Christ</hi> my Spouſe. And only the third (if it bee executed without any errour in the keyes) hath its operation directly vpon the ſoule. But all theſe three <hi>Excommunications</hi> then onely are <hi>Excommunications,</hi> and then only haue their operation, when they are made in ſpecial, and actually ſent forth, and employed, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the fact done, but when the crime is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in being.</p>
               <p>Therefore obſerue what a trifle that is, which the Popes, and their flatterers haue inuented, in enacting one <hi>Excommunication à iure, &amp; ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo facto,</hi> and another <hi>ab homine,</hi> that is to ſay, that there is an actuall <hi>Excommunication,</hi> which worketh actually, and by the deede it ſelfe, and not by way of threatning onely; and that, by vertue of the law before made, and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:18039:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>written, it alwaies worketh of it ſelfe, without comming to any ſpeciall act of <hi>excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> the particular offender, as often as he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth ſuch, or ſuch an offence before forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by the Law: The other is that, which, without beeing made vniuerſall by the lawes, is, from time to time darted out by the Prelate againſt a particular man by name, for ſome fault committed by him. This diſtinction is both falſe, and manifeſtly deceitfull; and it is that very deuiſe, whereof I ſpake before, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to dreame of a thunderbolt, which doth not onely affright a man, but alſo beat him downe to the ground, without beeing darted foorth: and ſo there can bee no ſecret among Chriſtians, which by this meanes the Pope cannot pierce into. Surely as for the two firſt <hi>Excommunications,</hi> if they bee not ſent forth from time to time againſt the parties by name, no man will euer abſteine from the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or from ſpirituall conuerſation in ſpirituall meetings, (for as for ciuill and humane com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, no <hi>Excommunication</hi> can hinder it.) In the third <hi>Excommunicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> likewiſe, it is certaine, that no effect can follow vpon it, vnleſſe it bee actually (but without errour) thundered out.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:18039:33"/>Where was it euer ſeen, that a Delinquent was bound to execute a penalty vpon himſelfe? True it is, that euery man is bound to beare with patience his owne iuſt puniſhment; but no man can bee bound to execute it on him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and to be his owne hangman. How then is it poſſible, that any of my children, by vertue of a wandring, vncertaine, vniuerſall <hi>Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication,</hi> which is indifferent by the law, ſhould, vpon an <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> be truely, and actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>excommunicated:</hi> that is, diſſeuered, and cut off from my body, vnleſſe he himſelfe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the onely man, that knoweth himſelfe to haue committed that fault, ſhall of himſelfe bee executioner of the puniſhment vpon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe? For my part, I haue no ſpirituall power to chaſtiſe ſecret ſinnes, no nor open neither, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they come vnto my notice: and yet theſe men would moſt fondly inflict actuall puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for faults vnreuealed to them, and vpon Delinquents vtterly vnknowen.</p>
               <p>Let no man therefore bee afraid of theſe <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communications iniure,</hi> although they bee <hi>ipſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto,</hi> vpon the very deede, or <hi>latae ſententiae,</hi> vpon the generall ſentence, which is an errour: nor is it poſſible that ſuch <hi>Excommunications</hi> ſhould
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:18039:34"/>worke <hi>ipſo facto:</hi> neither doth God hold any man for <hi>excommunicate,</hi> vntill hee be namely bound, and actually <hi>excommunicate.</hi> Let eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one bee affraid of ſinne, though neuer ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, and let him looke for puniſhment from God; but let him not feare any <hi>excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of mine, vnleſſe it be actually brandiſhed out againſt him by his lawfull Prelate, and that vpon good cauſe: nor can this third <hi>Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication</hi> otherwiſe worke any whit vpon the ſoule.</p>
               <p>Moreouer I aduiſe you, that, if a Prelate <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate</hi> any of you, and that vpon iuſt cauſe, for ſome offence deſeruing <hi>excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> if he doe not either by word, or deede, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare with which of theſe three <hi>Excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> he doth ſtrike you, this his <hi>excommunicating,</hi> though it be ſpeciall, and actuall is either none at all, or at the moſt it is to bee vnderſtood of the ſecond, and not of the third. Neither can that ſtand, which the new Canoniſts auouch, that by the indefinite name of <hi>Excommunication</hi> the greater is to be vnderſtood. For, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the ſecond with the third, which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding are moſt different one from an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others; and they would haue the ſecond to bee
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:18039:34"/>the greater, becauſe it taketh away Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call conuerſation from the <hi>excommunicate</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. It muſt be vnderſtood therefore of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, but as not amounting vnto the third, which third is the true <hi>Excommunicatio maior,</hi> the grand <hi>excommunication.</hi> For, it is true, that in the later, the former are included, but not the later in the former.</p>
               <p>Beſides this, you are to vnderſtand, that, by my rules taught me by my Spouſe, none of theſe <hi>Excommunications,</hi> eſpecially the third, can be of force, but when the crime is grieuous, publique, notorious, and very ſcandalous, and ſuch as giueth, firſt very great offence to God, and moreouer much ſcandall to the Church. And hee, that is cleere in his owne conſcience, and knoweth that hee doth not offend in the ſight of God, and that the act, for which he is <hi>excommunicated</hi> (eſpecially by the <hi>Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in iure</hi> onely) is not of it ſelfe abhominable, nor repugnant to Gods Law, let him neuer feare any <hi>excommunication</hi> at all, as making him guilty before God. Whilſt therefore a Prelate commandeth, or forbiddeth any act of its own nature indifferent, which is neither com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, nor forbidden by the word of God,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:18039:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>and impoſeth this his command vnder paine of <hi>Excommunication,</hi> you may laugh in your ſleeues at it. For the not obeying a Prelate in ſuch things, as in their owne nature are indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, ſeldome amounteth to a mortall ſinne; and, though it were mortall, yet it is not ſuch, as can deſerue the third <hi>Excommunication.</hi> And ſo when you heare <hi>Excommunications</hi> thundred out for reading of bookes, for not paying of penſions, for puniſhing Prieſts, and wicked Friars, according to law, with ciuill puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſuch like cauſes, you may take ſuch <hi>Excommunications</hi> to be made in ieſt, and neede not bee afraid of them: for I hold them to bee nothing worth; neither was it euer my mind, that this ſword of mine ſhould euer ſerue the turne, either for temporall affaires, or for the priuate ends of my Prelats.</p>
               <p>Take alſo this with you, which is one of my principall ordinances concerning <hi>Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations,</hi> that none can <hi>excommunicate</hi> any other then thoſe that bee in proper ſubiected to him, and of his Dioceſſe. And ſo the Biſhoppe of <hi>Rome</hi> cannot <hi>excommunicate</hi> thoſe, that are out of the Dioceſſe of <hi>Rome.</hi> And whoſoeuer <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicateth</hi> any, that are not ſubiect vnto
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:18039:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>him, his <hi>Excommunication</hi> holds not: and in this caſe the Popes thunderbolt is of no more force, then that of the Biſhop of
<note n="*" place="margin">A pety Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricke in <hi>Italy,</hi> in the dominions of <hi>Venice.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Caurole.</hi> Indeede any Biſhop, vpon great cauſe, may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to another Biſhop his communion, that is his communication, and brotherly comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſpirituall correſpondence. So alſo may any particular Church deny its communion to another, (and this may bee called a fourth kinde of <hi>Excommunication</hi>) but it hath no ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration vpon the ſoule, nor is exerciſed with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny power, or iuriſdiction of one Church ouer another: and the action it ſelfe is meerely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue, not poſitiue, nor operatiue: namely, when, vpon euidence, or deepe ſuſpicion of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothers ſpirituall corruption, mutuall correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondence is ſhunned. And yet in this ſort of <hi>Excommunication</hi> there is very great danger, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as vpon it foule, &amp; turbulent ſchiſmes doe enſue.</p>
               <p>This Rocke, as you ſee, becommeth very dangerous vnto you, whileſt it makes you ſtumble vpon feares, and terrors, which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold you from many actions, that would bee profitable, and commodious to you, and alſo it maketh you run headlong into the actions of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:18039:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>blindefold obedience, whence indeede com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth your ruine; ſeeing they will not ſuffer you to walke in the high-way of your ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but amuſe you in the by-wayes of eternall perdition, and hold you in ſubiection to an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doll, and to him that would haue you deeme him a god vpon earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="rock">
               <head>¶ The fift Rocke. The Commandements of the Church.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His is a very great Rocke, or rather a maine Sea of Rocks, and ſhelfes hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped vp together, and appointed for the ſpirituall ruine of you, my deere Children. The ambition of Popes hath hitherto vſurped a Law-making power through my whole fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily; and would haue me bound, vnder paine of mortall ſinne, to obſerue their lawes. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely it belongeth to mee in my Synods, and Councels, to ſet down certaine practicall rules concerning rites, and outward worſhip: which rules are nothing elſe, then certaine good di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, and publique inſtructions, requiſite,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:18039:36"/>and neceſſary, for the eſtabliſhing of good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, for the preuenting of confuſion, and for the increaſe of piety. But I neuer pretended, that they ſhould haue the very nature of lawes, but onely of good ordinances: and therefore my will was to call them <hi>Canons,</hi> that is to ſay, Rules, but not Lawes, nor <hi>Commandements,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe I procure the ſecular power to giue them the force of lawes. From which ſecular pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath not freed either mee, or any of you, as hee hath freed vs from the legall Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, and from the yoake and burden of that law, which, beeing no part of the <hi>Decalogue,</hi> perteyneth to the gouernment of the ſoule: there yet remayning moſt full power in Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and Magiſtrates, as farre as concerneth temporall gouernment, whereto all the ſort of you are ſubiect, not onely by conſtraint, and for feare, but alſo for conſcience-ſake, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> inſtructeth you. True it is,
<note place="margin">Rom. 13.5.</note> that there is alſo an obedience due vnto the ſpiritual Ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers; but this is to be vnderſtood of follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their good inſtructions in matter of faith, and concerning Chriſtian life. Neither was it the minde of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to load mee with a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of externall obligations, ouer and aboue
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:18039:37"/>the morall naturall law, and a few other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, when as himſelfe commanded me, that I ſhould beware of making his yoake hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy vnto my Children, by multiplying vpon them humane <hi>Commandements,</hi> and precepts: and ſharply rebuked the Scribes, and Phariſes of his time, vpbraiding them with that ſpeech of <hi>Eſay;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay 29.13. Matth. 15.8.</note> 
                  <hi>This people draweth nigh vnto mee with their mouth, and honoureth mee with their lips; but their heart is farre from me: in vaine doe they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip me, teaching for doctrines the commandements of men.</hi> They ouerpaſt the <hi>Commandements</hi> of the law, and taught the ſilly people, certaine obſeruances inuented by themſelues, and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by humane traditions only. In a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner euen ſo it befalleth you, my Children, now a dayes; yee are plyed might and maine, with certaine precepts, which, vſurping my name, they call <hi>the Commandements of holy Church,</hi> in which notwithſtanding I haue no part at all, and as for God's <hi>Commandements,</hi> they lie by the walles. You take farre more heede, that you omit not a Maſſe vpon an holy day, and many of you alſo vpon the working-dayes, then that you leaue not your neighbour without helpe, when he is in great miſery. Yee take more care
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:18039:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>of offending in eating fleſh on prohibited daies, then of committing fornication, or adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery. And hence it is that more ſcruples are ſtarted vp in your conſciences, and more adoe againſt you by your Confeſſors, Preachers, and Inquiſitors, if you haue but once ſupped halfe a meſſe of fleſh-pottage vpon a Friday, then if you had committed fornication an hundred times.</p>
               <p>Know ye therefore, that, in vndergoing ſuch ſcruples vpon theſe <hi>Church-commandements,</hi> yee are plainely tyrannized ouer, and are brought vnto a butchery, ſhambles, &amp; ſlaughter-houſe of the conſcience.
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.17. Gal. 4.31.</note> 
                  <hi>Where the Spirit of the Lord is, there is libertie,</hi> concerning all indifferent things: which libertie <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath beſtowed on you. I haue indeed authoritie vpon occaſion of publique ſpirituall affaires, to intimate fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtings, prayers, and almes; but with ſweetnes, and gentleneſſe, without impoſing any yoake, or impeaching this libertie, to the end that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of you likewiſe ſhould of your owne voluntary ſweetly, and charitably compoſe himſelfe to ſuch holy exerciſes, and thereby conforme himſelfe to my intention, which is alwayes hortatory, rather then mandatory,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:18039:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>with compulſion. I doe not hold my ſelfe to haue authoritie to command vpon the guilt of mortall ſinne, which I find no otherwiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined, then to be that, which is <hi>ſpoken, done, or thought against the eternall Law of God;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt cont. Fauſt. li. 22. cap. 27.</note> it is not ſaid againſt <hi>the commandement of the Church;</hi> whereas principally I either co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand or forbid that, which in it ſelfe is indifferent, and neither commanded, nor forbidden, by God's Law. So the holy Apoſtles, gathered together in the Councell of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> did reſolue, that the new Chriſtians, eſpecially thoſe that were conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from Gentiliſme, in reſpect of outward ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation, beſides the morall naturall Law of the <hi>Decalogue,</hi> ſhould not be bound in conſcience to any other thing,
<note place="margin">Acts. 15.29.</note> except <hi>abſteining from meats offered to Idols, and from blood, and from things ſtrangled:</hi> and moreouer to <hi>beware of fornication,</hi> not that this is not compriſed in the <hi>Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue,</hi> but for that the Gentiles for the moſt part were in this error, to thinke that ſimple fornication was not forbidden by the Law of nature. In other things the Apoſtles left them entire libertie of their conſcience.
<note place="margin">Rom. 14.3.</note> And S. <hi>Paul</hi> aduiſeth,
<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 2.16.</note> that <hi>he, which eateth not, ſhould not iudge thoſe that eate,</hi> and <hi>that none ought to iudge the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:18039:38"/>faithfull for eating, and drinking.</hi> Briefly, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, you are to conforme your ſelues vnto the well-grounded and well-inſtructed deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of abſtinence, of faſting, of prayers, of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Seruice, and other ſpiritual exerciſes; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially vpon the Sundayes, and more ſolemne Feaſts. But beware of two extreames; On the one ſide, leſt you fall into ſuperſtition, and bring your ſelues to ſuch anxietie, and ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſitie, as will oppreſſe the inward libertie of the conſcience; and therefore you are to put from you all feare of mortal ſinne, if ſometime by negligence, or for your owne conuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie (ſo it be without contempt, or ſcandall) you omit ſuch deuotions appointed, and ordeined by me, who am your indulgent Mother: and pretend not to hold you to it with ſuch rigor. The other extreame which you are to beware of, is, that hereupon you doe not runne into carnall libertie, by contemning, and vtterly neglecting my good, and holy ordinances, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at nought the pious, and deuout exerciſes appointed by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> whereby the holy worſhip of God is mainteined, and the inward ſpirit is furthered in Chriſtian vertues, eſpecially in Religiouſneſſe.</p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:18039:39"/>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Commandements</hi> therefore, in ſuch ſort as they are impoſed on you by the Pope, are very Rocks, he making vſe of them principally to the end he may exerciſe his dominion ouer me, with a Law-giuing power; but ſecondari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly alſo for other indirect ends, tending vnto couetouſnes: they are (I ſay) Rocks, becauſe, when as by Preachers, Confeſſors, and pettie doctrinall pamphlets, it ſtill ringeth in your eares, that thoſe <hi>Church-precepts</hi> doe binde you vnder the paine of mortall ſinne, they being little obſerued: by this your erronious conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence you make the omiſſion of them to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come in you mortall ſinne indeed; whereas otherwiſe it would be no ſinne at all. An erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious conſcience is that, which beleeueth a thing to be a ſinne, which in trueth is none: and whoſoeuer committeth, or omitteth that, which hee deemeth a ſinne to be done, or not done, though in trueth this be not a ſinne, yet he by his erronious conſcience ſinneth mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally herein: and this is a dangerous pit, and deepe breake-necke of ſoules. Now therefore when as you learne by mee, that my precepts (thoſe that are meerely mine) doe not include any obligation vnto mortall ſinne, be not you
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:18039:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>troubled with ſcruples, when, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, or ſcandall, you finde them not obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by you: and ſo much the rather, becauſe ſome of thoſe obſeruations haue a tang of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, whereupon it is not onely no ſinne to omit them, but alſo it would be often-times a ſinne to obſerue them: I will declare my ſelfe more particularly.</p>
               <p>There be fiue precepts, which ordinarily paſſe vnder the name of my <hi>Commandements,</hi> as common to all the faithfull: and yet in very deed there are to be found in <hi>the body of Canons</hi> now a dayes in force, a thouſand ſuch precepts, euen more then euer the <hi>Iewes</hi> were burthened withall; which is a thing very intolerable. Thoſe fiue are theſe; 1. To heare Maſſe on Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes, and eſtabliſhed holy dayes: 2. To faſt in Lent, in the foure Ember-wekes, in the Vigils, or Eues; and to abſtaine from fleſh on Fridaies, and Saturdaies: 3. To be ſhriuen by your owne Prieſt at leaſt once a yere: 4. To be houſeled at Eaſter: 5. To pay tythes according to cuſtome.</p>
               <p>The keeping of the Lords day, which ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded the ancient Sabaoth, is deriued rather from the diuine, or morall Law, then from mine: but let the obligation of that obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:18039:40"/>bee what it may, I meane not now to trouble you with it. I muſt remember you, that the Sunday, and other ancient Feaſts eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by me vpon mature deliberation, are to be fully obſerued by you according to my an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient vſe, and declaration, with abſteyning from ſeruile works, as much as morall neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and other vrgent occaſions will ſuffer; that you may then apply your ſelues to the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, and to the ſpirituall profit of your ſoules; namely, by gathering together, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to heare the word of God; to ioyne in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke prayer; and oftentimes to bee refreſhed with the moſt holy Sacraments. What hath <hi>Rome</hi> done by adding this particular com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of hearing Maſſe, (ſince the Maſſe is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated into an abuſe, as I will ſhortly ſhew you, and hath much ſuperſtition in it,) but that all you ſhould hold your ſelues to haue ſufficiently diſcharged your duety of keeping holy all Feaſts, by abſteyning from ſeruile workes and hearing the Maſſe, and nothing elſe? For your Confeſſors require nothing elſe of you vpon the commandement of ſanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Feaſts. The word of God either is not preached at all, or, if it be preached, it is not
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:18039:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>heard, or, if heard, that is onely vpon curteſie, and curioſitie, and not vpon duetie. The di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Seruice is ſaid, or ſung, but in a language not vnderſtood by the vulgar: whereupon it falleth out for the moſt part, that thoſe, that are there preſent, ſpend the time in pratling, whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering, and, which is worſe, in courting, and obſenities, and other ſuch intertainments, very abhominable to be vſed in the houſe of praier. As for the Sacraments, I will ſpeake of them af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards. And this is your firſt <hi>Church-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement,</hi> which doeth much more hurt then good. You, my children, ſhall duely ſanctifie the Feaſts, if vpon ſuch dayes, auoyding theſe vaine, and ſuperſtitious, (and I would to God I might not ſay Idolatrous) Maſſes, and, now that your ſpirituall fathers, or rather ſtep-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, afford you no good ſpirituall exerciſes, forbearing alſo to heare the Sermons of your Friars, which are full of leaſings, and deceipts, you would ſpend ſome time in your owne houſes in reading, in godly meditations, and prayers; and thus ſhould you very well keepe holy-day, till it ſhould pleaſe God to giue you true, pure, and vncorrupt exerciſes in your owne Churches.</p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:18039:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>In the ſecond precept, which concerneth fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, and abſtinence, I like very well, that thoſe, who can, doe faſt on the faſting-dayes, eſpecially in the <hi>Lent,</hi> which is a very ancient inſtitution. And let this be a true faſt, tending to the mortification of the fleſh, with abſtei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, not onely from eating fleſh, egges, and whitmeats, as the manner is, but alſo from all delicate, and high feeding viands, eſpecially, if they be incentiue, as are ſalt meats: Let the faſt be kept with hearbes, with pulſe, with cheape ordinary fiſh, and only one meale a day. Your faſting is very ridiculous, and loathſome, both to me, and my Spouſe: to abſteine from ſuch courſe meat as beefe, and to ſeeke out the moſt delicate fiſh of the higheſt price, and other choiſe dainties, to pleaſe the palate, with vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety alſo of ſpices, and ſauces. O, how much more perfect a faſt would it bee, and more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God, to take one light meale of fleſh, then a delicious banquet of fiſh. But, as I ſaid, if any of you bee not diſpoſed to faſt, or to forbeare fleſh, euen in <hi>Lent,</hi> let him not bee ſcrupulous thereupon: for, my precepts do not binde on paine of mortall ſinne: yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he ſhall bee very blameworthy, if, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:18039:41"/>able, yet he do not accommodate himſelfe to the reſt of the faithfull. Of Confeſſion, and receiuing the Communion, I will ſpeake after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
               <p>As for tithes, they are ill ranged vnder my precepts: for, I hold them to appertaine to God's law, either naturall, or poſitiue, at leaſt, where my Miniſters receiue from thence their neceſſary ſuſtenance, and in ſuch quantity, and manner, as cuſtome hath long confirmed. And this charge of ouerruling matter of tithes, where they neede rectifying, is proper to the ſecular Princes, euery of them in their owne dominions, inaſmuchas tithes are externall goods: and they are to ſee to it, that, where neceſſary Miniſters haue not decent mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, ſupply bee made by the Pariſhioners; and where too much aboundance, and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluity is, and the ſame luxuriouſly employed, that it bee moderated, by transferring from thoſe Prieſts, which haue too much, vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which haue too little. They are alſo to prouide that the Biſhops entertaine ſo many Clearkes, as are neceſſary for their Churches, and to reſtraine them from making a number of idle, and ſuperfluous Prieſts: and ſo ſhall
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:18039:42"/>all of them bee well prouided for: but much the better, if, by the authority of Princes, and temporal Lords, the world were diſburthened of ſuch rabbles of Friars, and Monkes, and Regulars, of the Religions now out of ſquare, and diſſolute: reducing alſo the other Orders, which keepe as yet ſome forme of regular life, vnto the entire obedience of thoſe Biſhops, in whoſe Cities, and Dioceſſes, thoſe Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uents are; and withall vtterly diſſoluing, and annulling, all forme of Common-wealth amongſt them, wherein all the Regulars are combined toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; ſo that they may remaine either meere Clearkes, and ſimple Prieſts, or elſe become Monkes of the old faſhion, without holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and without reuenues. And ſo their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitant poſſeſſions will make a ſupply to helpe Biſhops of ſmall meanes, and poore pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh-Prieſts, and will ſerue the turne to eaſe the people, in maintayning their pariſh-Prieſts, &amp; in founding of Colledges, and Seminaries for ſtudents in the Vniuerſities, and ſome-where alſo for the ſupport of the Military profeſſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="rock">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:18039:42"/>
               <head>¶ The ſixt Rocke. Falſe Vnion.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Erely I am but one, beeing the onely Spouſe of <hi>Christ;</hi> and though my daughters, the particular Churches, bee many, yet I am nothing elſe, but they all ioyned together. And foraſmuch as I am only one, and they altogether are one with me, euen as all the members <hi>vnited</hi> make onely one bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and the head of this my body is no other but <hi>Chriſt</hi> alone; therefore this my <hi>vnion</hi> conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in our being built all vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one, &amp; the ſame foundation, which is onely one and the ſame <hi>Chriſt,</hi> onely one and the ſame Goſpell, onely one and the ſame faith, onely one and the ſame Baptiſme; and in that wee loue, and imbrace one another in perfect charity. And thoſe Churches, which do not in this manner <hi>vnite</hi> themſelues vnto me, haue no part in this <hi>vnion,</hi> nor pertaine to this body. And in theſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, my holy Fathers haue alwaies declared this neceſſary <hi>vnion</hi> to conſiſt, the foundation whereof is faith, and charity the bond which combineth it. It muſt needs be therefore very
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:18039:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>lamentable to behold ſome Churches my daughters, or my parts, or members, that is, limbes of my body, to agree with mee in the foundation, but will not be <hi>vnited</hi> by charity, vnder vaine pretences of friuolous diſſenſſions in points, that are not fundamentall: and thus they fouly breake me this <hi>vnion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But that, which moſt of all offends mee, is, that the Pope, my Capitall enemie, doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, and breake, and diſſipate this my ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant <hi>vnion,</hi> drawing it miſchieuouſly to himſelfe, and vrging, that <hi>vnion</hi> conſiſteth in beeing ſubiect vnto him, as a viſible head. Yet haue I ſhewed, that there is no relation of an head in him, and that hee is meerely my mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and ſeruant. Indeede he is, as euery other Biſhop, the viſible head of his owne Church onely, my daughter of <hi>Rome:</hi> and he it is, that giueth <hi>vnion</hi> to that Church; for, euery parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church is viſibly one, whileſt it depends of her owne only principall miniſter. <hi>A Church</hi> (that is, a particular Church) ſaith Saint <hi>Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cypr. lib. 4. Ep. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>is a people vnited to their Paſtour:</hi> But in mee, that am the vniuerſall and totall Church, there is no <hi>vnion</hi> made by any other then by my true and onely head <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and all particular Churches bring forth that goodly, and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:18039:43"/>
                  <hi>vnion,</hi> by beeing <hi>vnited</hi> with me vpon the ſame foundation, and vnder the ſame head <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and that by way of charity, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord.
<note place="margin">Idem. lib. 4. Ep. 2.</note> To this purpoſe well ſaid the ſame <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian,</hi> that <hi>the Church of Chriſt is one, beeing diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded throughout the world into many members, and that there is only one Biſhopricke, which is diffuſed by the agreeing multitude of many Biſhops:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibidem. Ep. 3.</note> More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer he ſaith, <hi>though we be many Paſtors, yet wee feede one flocke onely.</hi> And againe, <hi>being that the Church, which is one and vniuerſall, is not broken, nor diuided, ſhee is alſo vnited, and combined by the bond of Prieſts conioyned among themſelues.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Cyprian</hi> neuer could finde, that this <hi>vnion</hi> conſiſted in one of the Biſhops, by the redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing all others to him, as to an head, but that all Biſhops <hi>vnited</hi> together in faith and charity did cauſe this <hi>vnion</hi> of mine.</p>
               <p>It is a grieuous iniury, which my vngratefull daughter of <hi>Rome</hi> doth offer me, whileſt ſhe, forgetting that ſhe is my daughter, maketh her ſelfe my Miſtres, and vſurpes my Robes, and my Titles, as if ſhe were the vniuerſall Church, when ſhee her ſelfe is a particular Church, one of the many. It is I, that am the truely vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall, who ſtretch forth my armes from Eaſt to Weſt, and from North to South: and how
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:18039:44"/>can ſhee be vniuerſall, or totall, beeing onely a part, and member? All the many are gathered together and <hi>vnited</hi> in me, and not in her: for euen ſhe, if ſhee will be Catholike, muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity bee <hi>vnited</hi> to me, as a part to the whole, as a member to the body, vnder mine, and her head, <hi>Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Behold therefore the Rocke, whereupon yee run, whileſt yee are willing to reduce your ſelues vnto an <hi>vnion</hi> inuented by the Pope, that hee might thereby become my head, and tyrannize ouer me, and whileſt ye yeeld obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to him, inſtead of remayning in <hi>vnion</hi> with me, ye ſeparate your ſelues from me, and, inſtead of making and procuring <hi>vnity,</hi> you breake it, and diuide it. For, he is not in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church, that is not in the vniuerſall Church, which am I: and whileſt the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> packeth a faction, which receiueth <hi>v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> from him onely: ſurely that ſect of his can bee neither Catholique, nor vniuerſall, nor Church: therefore his party is not the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Church, but a diueliſh ſchiſme, wherein there cannot be any ſound and holy <hi>vnion,</hi> but a conſpiracie and combination of a Sect, not of a Church. Now let vs paſſe on to the Rocks of <hi>Auarice.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:18039:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE SECOND PART. ¶ The Rocks founded on Auarice.</head>
            <div n="1" type="rock">
               <head>
                  <hi>The firſt Rocke.</hi> The Maſſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT exerciſe, wherewith I haue bene furniſhed ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for aboue foure hundred yeeres, which now adayes you call the <hi>Maſſe,</hi> was, by the firſt inſtitution thereof, nothing elſe, but a conſecrating of the Bread of the holy <hi>Euchariſt</hi> for the communion of the faithfull, and that to repreſent the Paſſion and death of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and to make commemoration of that moſt bleſſed ſacrifice, wherein <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, being both Prieſt, and Sacrifice, did offer vp his moſt ſacred Body, and pretious blood, vpon the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar of the Croſſe, onely once for my redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and for remiſſion of ſinnes: and this was then inſtituted by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> when in his laſt Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per he made his Apoſtles Communicants of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:18039:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>that myſterious Bread, and Wine, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented his Body and Blood, ſaying vnto them, <hi>Doe this in remembrance of mee.</hi> That therefore, which <hi>Chriſt</hi> gaue vnto his Apoſtles, namely. Bread, and Wine, for them to eate, and drinke, was the Sacrament, a true, and reall Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, but not a true, and reall Sacrifice, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then commemoratiue. For, this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was giuen them, as in very deed an actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Sacrament, and bearing with it Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall fruit and benefit, but as a commemoration onely, and repreſentation of the future ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. When therefore he ſaid vnto them, <hi>Doe you this,</hi> What elſe could he vnderſtand, but this, ye alſo ſhall deliuer vnto others actually this true, and reall Sacrament, but ſo, that it be commemoratiue, and repreſentatiue of my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice then ouerpaſt. And in this ſenſe did all my ancient Fathers alwayes vnderſtand this ſacred exerciſe (now called the <hi>Maſſe</hi>) for the introductions vſed in the making a reall, and actuall Sacrament, and for a Sacrifice, not actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, but onely commemoratiue, and repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatiue.
<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in epiſt. ad Heb. hom. 17.</note> Liſten to <hi>S. Chryſoſtome, We make an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fring euery day, but we doe it in remembrance of the death of</hi> Chriſt: <hi>there is onely one Sacrifice, which
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:18039:45"/>was onely once offered in the Holy of holies: but this Sacrifice is a type or modell of that: And this which we now performe, we doe onely in commemoration; As he ſaid,</hi> Doe this in remembrance of me. <hi>We performe not another Sacrifice, as the Prieſt then did; but we offer alwayes the ſame, or rather, we doe cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate the memory of that Sacrifice.</hi> So plainely ſpeaketh <hi>S. Chryſoſtome,</hi> that this action now called the <hi>Maſſe,</hi> is not it ſelfe a Sacrifice, but a memory, and repreſentation, &amp; after-draught of a by-paſt Sacrifice.</p>
               <p>What hath the <hi>Auarice</hi> of Rome done in this? This ſacred exerciſe, which, in regard of the reall action, produceth the Sacrament, is by them intituled to a true and reall vn-bloody Sacrifice vnder the name of the <hi>Maſſe,</hi> and ſo they will needs haue their Prieſts truely, and really to ſacrifice <hi>Chriſt:</hi> And to this their Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, as reall, and properly ſo called, they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute the true properties of an actuall Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, making it propitiatorie, impetratory, and ſatisfactorie: their end herein is, that you, my poore, and ſimple children, beleeuing theſe their fictions, may ply them to ſay <hi>Maſſes</hi> for you, but tendring beforehand your money to the prieſts, and oftentimes driuing the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:18039:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>for more or leſſe to eeke it out for the quicke, and the dead. And ſo you, finding your ſelues deepely drenched in ſinne, that you may ſaue the labour of a true, and due ſacrifice <hi>of an humble and contrite heart:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.17.</note> thus truſting more to this vnbloody Sacrifice, which will ſtand you in but a few pence, you thinke that you bring with you in your pocket an vndoubted remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of your ſinnes. O fearefull rocke! O dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full wracke! O hatefull auarice!</p>
               <p>The Pope will needs haue a great Armie of innumerable Prieſts, and Friars, whom he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth, and, in deſpight of Secular Princes, mainteyneth, to bee his onely, his Subiects, ſouldiers, and ſeruants: but, he is more thriftie then to allow them wages of his owne pay, or table of his prouiſion; and therefore hee hath inuented, for their maintenance, ſuch deuices as this, to nimme the coyne out of your purſes: Which yee giue downe very gently, that you may haue your part in theſe ſweet Sacrifices, not by way of commemoration of the benefit which you haue receiued by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but by way of bargaine, and hier for the remiſſion of your ſinnes, and the freedome of ſoules out of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie for pettie peniworthes. And that you
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:18039:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>may ply their ſhop the oftner, and become dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cuſtomers for <hi>Maſſe</hi>-bargaines, they tell you that one <hi>Maſse</hi> will not doe the feat; that you are not alwayes rightly diſpoſed to be capable of the benefit of this Sacrifice; that for euery ſinne you muſt haue at leaſt one <hi>Maſſe;</hi> with ſuch like deuiſes: and then let them alone to make their ware ſaleable: they will finde you miracles ynough begotten by their <hi>Maſſes,</hi> and ſtoare you with viſions, reuelations, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other ſuch tricks, and ſlights coyned in the forge of couetouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>But what thinke you of the ſuperſtitious ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of the <hi>Maſse?</hi> they are a many of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſes broached to aſtoniſh the ſimple vulgar, and to rauiſh them with admiration of hidden and vnknowne myſteries, without common ſence, without ſignification, without any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents in them, other then meere ſuperſtition. The <hi>Maſse</hi>-prieſt ſometimes beats his breaſt; one while lifts vp his eyes, other-while caſts them downe; one while ioynes his hands to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, other-while ſpreads them at large; one while holds his fingers cloſe, other-while diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playes them: ſometimes he makes croſſes in the aire, in a certaine prefixed number, and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:18039:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>with ſo nimble motion, as if he would beat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way flies, ſometime he bends himſelfe downe, lowting low with Spaniſh crindges: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time hee ſtands vpright, ſometime ſtoopes, ſometime mumbles in ſecret, other-while hee chaunts it alowd: one while hee turnes to the people, otherwhile to the Altar: which are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticulations fitter for the ſtage, then for the Church, and to procure laughter, then to ſtirre vp deuotion. Set habits I miſlike not; for, in my firſt, and beſt times my Miniſters were in their holy functions adorned with proper ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits for that purpoſe, which indeed were not ſo coſtly and ſtately, as now adayes I ſee them in ſome Churches, nor ſo ſlouenly and naſtie, as I ſee them in other, eſpecially amongſt thoſe Friars, which loue their broath well, and take more care to haue their diet large and fat, then to haue their Veſtrie furniſhed and neatly dight.</p>
               <p>As for the Sacrament, whileſt the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the faithfull, either all, or many, or ſome is in celebrating, then is the fit time for that, which is called <hi>Maſse,</hi> which ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede bee the Liturgie, and, not a priuate, but publique exerciſe, euen for the ſaid Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:18039:47"/>and no other vſe: for, this onely was the firſt, and pure inſtitution thereof. But <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi> haue brought-in an innouation, that for the moſt part the Communion ſhould bee ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated without <hi>Maſse,</hi> or Liturgie: for, they make boxes to be kept full of theſe <hi>Hosts:</hi> there one comes, another goes, and the Prieſt, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Maſſe,</hi> without prayers, affords to euery ſtander-by the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion, or rather the halfe Communion; it being a maymed Sacrament, and full of vndecent enormities. Hence I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre, that the priuate <hi>Maſſe,</hi> as it is now adaies celebrated, is in many reſpects friuolous, and cauſeth the ruine of many ſoules. One refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of it would bee, by cutting off many parts of it, and generally all thoſe ſtrange ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, and by celebrating it for the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on onely. Whereupon it followes, that in one and the ſame Church all the Altars, except one principall, ſhould bee demoliſhed, as ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. For, in one Congregation one <hi>Maſſe</hi> is enough for the peoples Communion, where the multitude of Altars, and <hi>Maſſes</hi> is nothing but a meere ſuperſtition, and erronious opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Sacrifice.</p>
               <p>But the greateſt enormitie, and moſt intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:18039:48"/>error of the <hi>Maſse,</hi> now adayes is, that you, poore ſoules, are made beleeue, that in it the bread is conuerted, or (as they ſpeake) <hi>tranſubſtantiated</hi> into the true, and reall body of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> ſo that the bread after the conſecration muſt bee no more bread, no not in ſubſtance, but <hi>Chriſt's</hi> true and reall body, with his true, &amp; reall preſence in body, and ſoule, and the Deity vnited thereto; with his head, eies, hands, and feet, the very ſame, that was borne of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary,</hi> which was faſtened on the Croſſe, which roſe againe, and aſcended into heauen, and ſitteth at the right hand of God the Father; a thing beyond all vnderſtanding, and vtterly imperceptible, which I could neuer appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, nor approoue. Surely the Scripture al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes calleth the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> euen after conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration, bread; Saint <hi>Luke</hi> calleth it the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of <hi>breaking of bread:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 2.46.</note> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> alſo ſaith,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.16.</note> That <hi>the bread, which wee breake, is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the body of Christ;</hi> and ſpeaking of the due preparation before the Communion, after a man hath prooued himſelfe, and purged his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.28.</note> 
                  <hi>then,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>let him eat of that bread, and drinke of that cup.</hi> So likewiſe all the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Fathers acknowledged true bread in the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:18039:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Euchariſt;</hi> neither euer heard they newes of this <hi>tranſubſtantiation,</hi> it being an vtter ſtranger in my houſe; and for aboue eight hundred yeres after <hi>Chriſt</hi> neither heard of, nor thought on. And whenſoeuer the ancient Fathers doe call the <hi>Eucharist</hi> by the name of <hi>Chriſt's</hi> body, their meaning is, that the bread is <hi>Chriſt's</hi> body <hi>Sacramentally,</hi> without ceaſing to be bread ſtill: euen as the water of holy Baptiſme is ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally the blood of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which waſheth the ſoule, yet notwithſtanding remayneth it ſtill water.</p>
               <p>And, if yee aske mee, what the <hi>Eucharisticall</hi> bread doth get by conſecration more then it had before, and what maner of tranſmutation, or change that is, which the holy Fathers ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge to be in the bread after conſecrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; I anſwere, that the bread before conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is nothing elſe, but ordinary bread, and onely materiall food for the body; but vpon conſecration it is altered, and changed, and that ſpiritually, and not materially: for, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth Sacramentall bread, and by ſo being it attayneth a very great and meruailous priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that whoſoeuer doth worthy lie eat it in the holy Communion, doth receiue the true
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:18039:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>body of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in a certaine vnſpeakeable, but ſpirituall, and Sacramentall maner: <hi>Chriſt</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ordeined and promiſed, that whenſoeuer this bread beeing made Sacramentall by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration, ſhall be eaten worthy lie, he will giue his body ſpiritually, and all other admirable ſpirituall benefits for the nouriſhment of their ſoules, to thoſe that ſhall thus worthylie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate. And, in regard of this ſpirituall ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of receiuing the body of <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſpiritually, as often as the conſecrated bread is worthylie receiued in the act of communicating, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are wont to call that bread the body of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> And in this ſenſe, <hi>Chriſt,</hi> when he gaue the Communion to his Apoſtles in his laſt ſupper, did call that bread, which he deliuered to them, his body. So alſo muſt wee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the conſecrated wine, which beeing druncke corporally in the Sacrament, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry blood of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is drunke, but ſpiritually, &amp; not corporally: and ſo in the bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of bread and wine, there is ſpiritually the true body, and the true blood of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> with their true, and reall effects, wrought in the ſoule of the worthy Communicant: but there is neither the body, nor the blood corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:18039:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>and that which is there corporally, is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bread, and very wine, imployed Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally, as I haue declared.</p>
               <p>The like is to be vnderſtood alſo of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of holy Baptiſme: for, that alſo, before the inuocation of the moſt holy Trinity in the act of baptizing, is no other, then meere ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry water, but by that inuocation it is conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the very act of Baptiſme, and ſo at one &amp; the ſame time, both the water is conſecrated, and of ordinary becommeth Sacramental, and withall there is performed the Sacrament of Baptiſme, with the inward effect of purging the ſoule: whereas in the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration goeth before, whereby the bread, and wine are made Sacramentall; and afterwards follow the eating, and drinking of them: in which actions conſiſteth the very Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the body &amp; blood of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is giuen inwardly to him, that worthylie eateth and drinketh this Sacramentall bread, and wine; but whoſoeuer doth eat and drinke them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthylie, without examining himſelfe, and firſt being clenſed from ſinne, he doth not eat, nor drinke any other thing, then bread, and wine. For to thoſe, that are vnworthy, <hi>Christ</hi>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:18039:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>affordeth not ſpiritually his body, nor his blood, howſoeuer they doe eat, and drinke the conſecrated bread, and wine: which conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath this operation, that it maketh the bread, and wine Sacramentall vnto thoſe that Sacramentally receiue them, and are onely fit for them; whereas the vnworthy receiue them not as a Sacrament, <hi>Chriſt</hi> denying vnto them his body, and blood; and ſo to them this eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and drinking is no Sacrament, and that by their own default: This conſecration there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth them no good at all, but is the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion that they eat and drinke, not a Sacrament, nor <hi>Chriſt's</hi> body,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.29.</note> and blood, but <hi>iudgement, &amp; condemnation,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> denounceth, becauſe <hi>they doe not diſcerne the body of the Lord;</hi> that is, they put no difference betweene ordinary bread, and this conſecrated bread, which in the Sacramentall eating doth ſpiritually exhibite the true body of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to the worthy recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers; they making no other preparation for it, then if they were to receiue their common, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, and meere corporall food. So alſo, if, by any miſchance in the time of communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, any vnreaſonable creature ſhould eat that conſecrated bread, it eateth no other then
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:18039:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>meere bread; inaſmuch as <hi>Chriſt</hi> doth not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foord his body with the conſecrated bread, but onely vnto thoſe, who are capeable of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and are made worthy of it, or, at leaſt, doe not vnworthylie approach vnto it.</p>
               <p>And becauſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> performeth not this won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull worke of giuing his body, and blood, (in ſuch ſort as I haue declared) but onely by occaſion of the Sacrament; and foraſmuch as, likewiſe the Sacrament it ſelfe conſiſteth who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the actions of eating, and drinking, who ſeeth not, that ſuch conſecrated bread, whileſt it is not imployed in thoſe actions, remayneth pure and ordinary bread? for, the conſecrating of it ſerued only to make it Sacramental bread, &amp; ſurely it is not Sacramentall otherwiſe then as it is to bee eaten Sacramentally in that ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall banquet, which then is in celebrating, although the ſame ſhould continue many houres, or there were ſome ſicke perſons to communicate of it, who lie in their beds at home, euen though they were ſome ten miles diſtant thence, in aſmuch as this may bee held morally one banquet or Communion.</p>
               <p>Whereupon you may eaſily perceiue the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of thoſe, that terme by the name of the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:18039:51"/>moſt holy Sacrament that conſecrated bread, which after the Communion finiſhed, is kept in Pyxes and cabinets, where it is not to bee ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by any, but after certaine daies, and weeks, and moneths, and perhaps not by men at all, but by mice, or other vermine, and yet ſurely it is no Sacrament, but onely in the act of eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: therefore in theſe Pyxes, and cloſets there is contained, not onely no Sacrament, but not ſo much as Sacramentall bread, the force of conſecration beeing already vaniſhed; inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as that bread was conſecrated onely to the end it might bee eaten in that meeting Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentally; and therefore afterwards it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth ordinary bread: which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, in reuerend regard that this very bread was conſecrated to the Communion, is to bee eaten by thoſe, that are in ſacred functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and not to bee brought vnto the common dining-table, nor to be vſed as ordinary foode. And yet (alas) euen to this bread thus reſerued, there are vſually prayers made, and adoration performed, as vnto the onely true God, which is moſt expreſſe, proper, and formall Idolatry.</p>
               <p>Conſider alſo the groſſe abſurdities, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt impoſſibilities, which they are faine to
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:18039:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>maintaine, who hold <hi>tranſubſtantiation:</hi> that the accidents of bread, namely colour, quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſmell, ſauour, and ſuch like, remaine with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſubiect, wherein they ſhould inheare, or ſubſtance, whereby they ſhould be ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Surely nothing can ſubſiſt in its actuall being whenſoeuer it looſeth its very eſſence; and all Philoſophie proclaimeth, that <hi>Acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis eſse estineſse,</hi> the being of an accident, or qualitie conſiſteth in being ſupported by a ſubſtance, or ſubiect. So that by this reckoning theſe accidents are in being, becauſe they are ſeene, and felt, and yet are not in being, becauſe their owne being is denied them: and that which eſſentially hath no being of it ſelfe, but wholy dependeth of another, it is vnpoſſible that it ſhould exiſt without that, by which it is that it is. So euery accident in its owne eſſence is an appurtenance to another thing, namely, vnto ſubſtance; and he, that withdraweth ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and ſubject from an accident, ſtealeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the very eſſence thereof: and ſo, as I ſaid, theſe accidents are ſomething, becauſe they are viſible, and palpable, and yet are nifles, becauſe there is no ſubſtance left to ſupport them; and ſo they are appendants, and no appendants.
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:18039:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>And, as for diuinitie, that acknowledgeth, that euen to God himſelfe thoſe things, which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply contradiction, are not feiſible.</p>
               <p>But what would they ſay concerning the power of nouriſhing, which is alwayes to be found in the <hi>Euchariſticall</hi> bread? Certainely he, that ſhould eate no other meat, nor drinke no other liquor, then theſe Sacramentall ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſhould finde himſelfe nouriſhed as much as with any ordinary bread and wine: And being that a man's body is not an acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, but a ſubſtance, of neceſſitie it muſt bee nouriſhed with ſubſtances and not with acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, the ſubſtance of meats being alwayes turned into the ſubſtance of the body nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed by them: here therefore is no other ſtarting-hole left, then to run to a miracle, that forſooth God doth create a new ſubſtance, whereby he, that thus eateth, is nouriſhed, and ſo in trueth they might as well ſay, that he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth and is nouriſhed without eating, and drinking: for, to eate and drinke without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing the ſubſtance of meat and drinke is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed not to eate and drinke at all.</p>
               <p>Here I may adde the greateſt impoſſibilitie of all, and euen open contradiction hence fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:18039:52"/>namely, that <hi>Christ's</hi> body ſhalbe a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and no body: it cannot be denied that cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal, and incorporeall ſubſtances are ſo farre in their nature, and eſſence diſtinguiſhed, that neither of them can haue the properties of the other, nor be diſpoiled of their owne proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, without the totall deſtruction of one of them. To be in a confining circumſcribed place; to haue quantitie, and parts one diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed from the other; to be either heauy, or light; to be ſenſible; are properties, which ariſe from the internall eſſence of things corporeal. To be indiuiſible; to be vncircumſcribed by any place; to poſſeſſe no ſituation; to be who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the whole, and all in euery parcell of the whole, are properties of ſubſtances abſtract, immateriall, and incorporeall. Well indeed may it be granted, that God's Almighty power can diſplace ſome of theſe properties in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, by putting in another propertie contrary thereto, but yet corporeal; as he can make a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which is naturally heauy, to become light, and that, which is hot, to become cold; but to make a body ſtill to remaine an entire body, yet ſo, that it ſhall reteine no corporeall quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but aſſume incorporeall properties, is vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:18039:53"/>impoſſible, euen to God's omnipotencie: for it ſhould be at the ſame time both a body and a ſpirit; and ſo a body, and no body. To this are the Papiſts driuen, turning the body of <hi>Christ</hi> into an abſtract, immateriall, and incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreall ſubſtance, and giuing it the true pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of a ſpirit, and depriuing it of all bodily qualities. And yet when the Diſciples, after the reſurrection, vpon <hi>Chriſt's</hi> appearance amongſt them,
<note place="margin">Luke 24.37.</note> and ſaying vnto them, <hi>Peace be vnto you, were terrified and affrighted, ſuppoſing they had ſeene a ſpirit;</hi> for the driuing this error out of their heads, <hi>Christ,</hi> ſhewing them his hands, and feet, and body, ſaid, <hi>Handle me and ſee; for, a ſpirit hath not fleſh, and bones.</hi> It is therefore a ſound poſition by <hi>Christ's</hi> owne argument, that that, which conſiſteth of fleſh and bones, cannot haue the properties of a ſpirit, nor a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit haue the properties of a body; otherwiſe <hi>Christ's</hi> argument would not paſſe for currant, if it were poſſible, that a man's body might bee without palpable fleſh, and bones, and that a Spirit might conſiſt of palpable fleſh, and bones. But the Papiſts will needs driue the body of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which of neceſſitie hath viſible, and palpable fleſh, and bones, to be a meere
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:18039:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſpirit: and ſo they make the ſame body, remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning continually in heauen, and not departing thence, to come downe to the earth, into the hands of the Prieſt, and that without paſſing through the heauens, or the aire: and that the ſame entire body muſt be in the ſame moment of time, both in heauen, and vpon an infinite company of Altars in the earth: and that not onely in the whole contents of the conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Host,</hi> but in euery little particle thereof, though no bigger then the point of a needle, there muſt be the large entire body of a man fully growne, together with all his fleſh, and bones, with his hands, and feete, and with all the reſt of his members. A very meere vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, whereat the Infidels our aduerſaries may well make themſelues merry, and mocke at our faith, for mainteyning things ſo repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to all reaſon, which wee cannot ſalue vp, no not by running to God's omnipotencie.</p>
               <p>There is no neceſſitie at all, whereby wee ſhould be driuen to theſe abſurd aſſertions. True it is, that <hi>Christ</hi> ſpeaking of the holy Bread, ſaid, <hi>This is my body,</hi> but euen ſo it is ſaid of iron heated red-hot, this is fire, not becauſe it ceaſeth to be iron, but becauſe that iron is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:18039:54"/>with fire, together with the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties thereof, as heating, enlightning, and ſuch like. So, this bread is his body, becauſe, in the Communion, the body of <hi>Chriſt</hi> doeth ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually accompany this bread, and doth bring ſpirituall effects with it.</p>
               <p>So alſo <hi>Christ</hi> ſaid of <hi>S. Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> that hee was <hi>Elias,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 17.12.</note> yet he was not in perſon that ancient <hi>Elias,</hi> but he, that was prefigured by him. <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> therefore ſpake myſticallie and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally; as likewiſe when he ſaid of himſelfe, that he was <hi>the liuing bread</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 6.55.</note> that <hi>his fleſh was meat indeed, and his blood drinke indeed.</hi> Some of the holy Fathers vnderſtand this place in <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> not of the Sacrament of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> but of faith, and in a myſterious ſenſe, that he, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued in him, did thereby eate the true bread, which was giuen from heauen. And thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Fathers, which, by this fleſh and blood thus promiſed by <hi>Chriſt</hi> for nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, vnderſtand the Sacrament, doe meane alſo, that this fleſh, and this blood is to be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and drunke by faith, whileſt the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Bread, and Wine is eaten, and drunke by the corporall mouth.</p>
               <p>From this maine error concerning this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:18039:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>and vnconceiuable <hi>tranſubſtantiation,</hi> whereby they will haue a true, and reall tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation of the Bread into the true, reall, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, entire, and totall body of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> doth ariſe a true, and reall Idolatrie in the <hi>Maſse:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the conſecrated <hi>Hoſt</hi> is lifted vp, that it may be adored for very <hi>Chriſt,</hi> very God; and yet in realtie and trueth it is true and reall bread.</p>
               <p>Another branch ſpringing from this error is, that vpon this occaſion they haue maimed the Sacrament in the peoples Communion, by ſaying, that in receiuing of the body of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the Bread, there is receiued the fleſh, and ſo the blood alſo by <hi>concomitancie.</hi> And vpon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of certaine vaine, and fruitleſſe reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, leſt by any miſchance the conſecrated wine ſhould be ſpilt vpon the ground, and ſo the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry blood of <hi>Chriſt</hi> be trod vnder feet, they haue to preuent this miſchiefe robbed the people of the vſe of the cup. Wherein they erre more wayes then one; firſt, in running to this deuiſe of <hi>concomitance,</hi> whereas <hi>Christ</hi> in his Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this holy Sacrament did employ both Bread, and Wine, commanding all both to eate and drinke, and giuing order to his Apoſtles, that they, and their ſucceſſours after them
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:18039:55"/>ſhould in the very ſame man<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>er miniſter the Communion vnto the faithfull people.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, by taking away from the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the ſignification thereof, they doe, in whole, or in part, deſtroy the Sacrament it ſelfe: namely, as farre as the thing ſignified is more, or leſſe defalked. <hi>Christ</hi> hath inſtituted the Sacrament of the <hi>Eucharist</hi> in the forme of a meale, a banquet, a refection, for the increaſe of amitie, and loue among the faithfull, (whoſe charitie is much imployed in theſe mutuall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainements and feaſts) as alſo to ſignifie, that he would hereby refreſh, and nouriſh our ſoules. Now he, that debarres drinke from his boord, and feeds his gueſts with meate onely, ſurely maketh but a dry feaſt; and hee, that feeds onely on meate, without any drinke at all, is but ill refreſhed, and very imperfectly nouriſhed. When therefore the faithfull come together to the Lord's Supper, they ought, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in the outward action, not onely to eate, but alſo to drinke together, to expreſſe in this compleat man<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>er their mutual loue, and vnion: and if they onely eate together without drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they cannot taſte the entire ſignification of this ſpirituall Feaſt, which conſiſts in an
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:18039:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>entire, and totall charitie. And hee that out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly receiueth meate onely, without the Cup, cannot thereby repreſent to his vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the inward receipt of a compleat ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall refection.</p>
               <p>They haue therefore done very ill to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the vſe of the Cup, to the grieuous may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the Sacrament, and robbing of you, my deere children, of a great part of the fruit of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> whileſt they giue it you in this man<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>er, lame and diſmembred. And this reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, which they pretend, is a vaine excuſe: for, ſuch care, and diligence, as by men can bee performed in this behalfe, is ſufficient to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent vndecent handling of thoſe ſacred miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; and there beeing no danger at all, that the very body, or the very blood of <hi>Christ</hi> ſhould be materially trampled or trodden vnder foot; but ſurely, their keeping their Sacrament thus in boxes and ſhrines (which is indeede no Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament whileſt it is not thereto imployed) is heereby expoſed to danger of beeing gnawen, and conſumed by mice and wormes: and in this their caſe of danger, they are driuen to ſay, that a mouſe, eating thoſe <hi>ſpecies,</hi> doth receiue into it ſelfe the very body of <hi>Christ,</hi> and the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:18039:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>Sacrament, though it receiue not <hi>rem, &amp; effectum Sacramenti,</hi> the Sacramentall thing and effect thereof: and whileſt theſe <hi>ſpecies</hi> remaine in the belly of this mouſe, it muſt needes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, according to their doctrine, that in the mouſe's belly there is included the true and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all body of <hi>Christ.</hi> And is not this, I pray you, a greater abſurdity, then if ſome droppe of the ſacred wine, though it were indeede the very blood of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſhould be ſpilt vpon the earth, whence it may either be gathered vp, or wiped away without beeing trodden on at all?</p>
               <p>In the meane while heere alſo they vſe their ambitious tyrannie, making themſelues abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Lords ouer holy things, and myſteries or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned by <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, whereof they ought to be diſpenfers onely, and not commanders, nor maſters to giue or deny what they pleaſe, euen to thoſe, who are worthy receiuers of them. And beſides this fuell of their ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereby they mainetaine <hi>tranſubſtantiation,</hi> to make their Prieſts and Friars to bee more highly eſteemed, and reuerenced of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, (as thoſe who manage, and handle <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and cauſe him to come downe from heauen) heereto is to be added alſo the part, which co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueteouſneſſe
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:18039:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>hath in this lot, by ſquieſing your purſes, and drawing from you the larger offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings by this vaine fancie put in your heads, &amp; ſelling their <hi>Maſſes</hi> at ſo much the higher rate, which they ſee cannot haue the name of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiatory Sacrifice, vnleſſe the very body of <hi>Chriſt</hi> bee offered in them. And thus you ſee theſe ſo high myſteries, for the priuate ends of thoſe that manage them, enwrapped with groſſe and palpable errors; from which I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe you to keepe aloofe, as from moſt pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Rocks.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="rock">
               <head>¶ The ſecond Rocke. Auricular Confeſsion.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ne of the precious treaſures, which my <hi>Ieſus Christ</hi> hath layd vp in his houſe, and mine, is the remiſſion of ſinnes, which cannot bee had, or found any<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where elſe, then in my precincts: This in moſt full man<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>er is granted firſt in Baptiſme vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe, who, beeing of ripe vnderſtanding, doe ſeriouſly come to the holy lauer. And you
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:18039:57"/>my children, by reaſon of your corrupt nature, cannot remaine any long while in this mortall life without falling into ſinnes, whereupon the true and generall remedy for remiſſion of ſinnes committed after Baptiſme, is Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
               <p>But I would haue you be aduiſed, that yee by no deede, that you can doe, though ſupported with God's grace, can euer purchaſe, or merit this Remiſſion, as if doing one or more good actions, and preſenting them to God, ye might pretend, that he is bound to pardon you, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially concerning the act of Iuſtification; wherein of an impious ſinner remayning vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God's wrath, a man becommeth the ſonne of God, and is reconciled to him, and accepted of him. This is a grieuous errour, and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Rocke, inaſmuch as neither repentance, nor <hi>Confeſsion,</hi> nor any other act done by a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, can binde God to affoord him remiſſion, to whom onely it belongeth to remit ſinnes. And this remiſſion hath my only Spouſe your Lord, and mine, <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> purchaſed, and merited with his bitter Paſſion, by ſhedding of his moſt precious blood, and dying vpon the balefull tree of the Croſſe: and the remiſſion
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:18039:57"/>of your ſinnes conſiſteth in this onely, that God through his meere grace and mercy ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepteth <hi>Chriſt's</hi> ſatisfaction inſtead of that ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, which a ſinner ought to pay him for his ſinnes, by the euerlaſting puniſhment of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall damnation. And ſo a ſinner becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth iuſt, whileſt God doth deriue vpon a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the iuſtice of his ſonne, and doth apply it vnto him with this onely condition, that the ſinner by faith doe vnite himſelfe vnto <hi>Christ,</hi> and beleeuing in him doe lay his whole confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence on him onely, and not on any worke or merit of his owne. For, all your workes, if they be meerely naturall, are filthy, &amp; of no worth to obtaine any ſupernaturall good: and if they be done with faith, and by the helpe of grace, beſides that they are alwayes full of imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and tainted with ſome ſpots, they are not indeede to bee counted yours, but to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to God and his grace; and are alſo a debt due vnto him in many reſpects: for, whoſe the tree is, his alſo is the fruit that it beareth; and to him that is maſter of a ſlaue, belong al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the children, the worke, and the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe whatſoeuer the ſlaue getteth. Yee can neuer therefore bring vnto God your workes
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:18039:58"/>as your owne free gift, whereupon you might expect recompence of pardon: and ſo much the more, in that there is no proportion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene your workes, which are finite, and of finite value, (if of any at all) and the offence of infinite demerit. Suffer not therefore your ſelues to bee deceiued by the couetouſneſſe of the Prieſts, and Friars, when they tell you, that you may obtaine iuſtification, and remiſſion of your ſinnes how heynous ſoeuer, by your good workes, eſpecially by giuing almes. Neither put you any confidence toward the remiſſion of ſinnes in any, ſauing <hi>Chriſt</hi> alone, and in his merits;
<note place="margin">Rom. 3.24.</note> for, hee <hi>freely iuſtifieth you,</hi> without any merit of yours.</p>
               <p>True it is (and therefore take heede of the other extreame) that no man can preſent him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to God, nor rely vpon <hi>Chriſt's</hi> merits, that goeth on in a wicked reſolution to continue ſtill in ſin againſt his conſcience. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I told you, that you muſt addreſſe your ſelues vnto <hi>Chriſt</hi> to obtaine this remiſſion, but with faith, that is, with a true and liuely faith,
<note place="margin">Iam. 2.17.</note> not with that <hi>faith, which without workes is dead,</hi> but with ſuch a faith in the mind, which is accompanied with holy affections, and that
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:18039:58"/>is to beleeue in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to bee ſubiect vnto him, to obey him, with deteſtation of faults com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and intending of a new life, and yeeld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vp a man's ſelfe to the keeping of God's ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Commandements. And whoſoeuer doth not this, in vaine ſhall hee rely vpon <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his merits, neither ſhall he euer obtaine remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his ſinnes. This ryſing vp from ſinne, and ſubmitting to the obſeruance of God's Commandements, as farre as humane frailty will afford, is not in you any merit, whereto remiſſion ſhould bee repayed as due, but it is a neceſſary diſpoſition, and taketh away the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments, that otherwiſe would hinder re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes. And herein conſiſteth Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitence, being both the inwards of true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, (which is the moſt principall diſpoſition requiſite for remiſſion) and the outſide alſo of penitentiall workes, as faſting, almes, mortify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fleſh, and other workes of piety, which are indeede no merits, nor cauſes of forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but fruits of inward true repentance, and a fit appurtenance vnto the inward good diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and vnto due humiliation.</p>
               <p>Theſe diſpoſitions being forelaid, as neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, &amp; required by God, let a man hold himſelfe
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:18039:59"/>to his faith, and confidence in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and by his mercy hee ſhall without faile obtaine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion: and the whole conueyance betweene God and a ſinner, is carried in this man<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>er by the meanes of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> mine and your onely Mediatour, without any neceſſity at all of any other <hi>Confeſsion</hi> made vnto man; due <hi>Confeſsion</hi> made vnto God beeing of it ſelfe ſufficient, whereby a ſinner, beeing humbled, doth not any more defend his ſinnes, but <hi>confeſſeth</hi> to God,
<note place="margin">Chryſ. in ep. ad Heb. hom. 31.</note> that he hath ſinned. <hi>I doe not aduiſe thee</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome) to lay thy ſelfe open, nor to accuſe thy ſelfe to others,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſalm. 57.</note> 
                  <hi>but to obey the Prophet, who ſayeth, Reueale thy way vnto the Lord. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe thy ſinnes before God, declare thy offences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Iudge, though not with thy tongue, yet with thy memory, and then hope that thou ſhalt obtaine mercy:</hi> So ſaith that worthy holy Father.</p>
               <p>I doe not know, that I euer intertayned in my houſe any ſuch Sacrament appointed mee by my Spouſe, as a true and proper Sacrament, whereby hee hath obliged himſelfe to giue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes after Baptiſme: I beleeue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, that whoſoeuer groaning vnder the load of ſinne, ſhall with true inward pentience, and reall repentance approach vnto the holy table,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:18039:59"/>and receiue the Communion with due prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, ſhall receiue remiſſion of his ſins. For, although this Sacrament was principally inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted by <hi>Christ,</hi> and committed to mee for the ſpirituall feeding of the ſoule, and for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing of charity among my children; yet in that it is alſo a remembrance of the Paſſion of <hi>Christ,</hi> it auayleth much for the remiſſion of ſinnes; for the obtayning whereof <hi>Chriſt's</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy was ſacrificed vpon the Croſſe, &amp; his moſt pretious blood ſhed: and therefore in his firſt giuing the Communion to his Apoſtles, hee ſaid vnto them,
<note place="margin">Luc. 22.19. Math. 26.28.</note> that that was <hi>his body which was giuen for them, and his blood ſhed for the remiſsion of ſinnes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You muſt vnderſtand alſo, that <hi>Auricular Confeſsion,</hi> and Prieſtly Abſolution, which are the ground of this Rocke, now ſet before your view, is neither practiſed aright, nor well vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by thoſe that follow the <hi>Romane</hi> doctrine, who hereupon haue built a ſhop of money-mart and gaine. Recall, I pray you, to your remembrance that, which I obſerued be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the fourth Rocke of the firſt part, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the two firſt medicinall <hi>Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and you ſhall finde that my ancient cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:18039:60"/>preſcribed vnto mee by my Spouſe, and practiſed by my holy, and learned Miniſters, of at leaſt foure of the firſt Ages, was publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to correct grieuous, and ſcandalous offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, and, according to the authority commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to me by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to binde them in their ſins, and afterwards to looſe them againe, and in this man<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>er to imploy the keyes about the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of ſinnes; namely, to debarre ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders for ſome while from the holy Table, &amp; ſometime alſo from all other Congregations, and meetings of the faithfull for ſpirituall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes, as heynous delinquents drowned in their ſinnes, and vnworthy of ſuch participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, vnleſſe they ſhould firſt recall themſelues vnto due inward penitence, and giue alſo out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſatisfaction vnto mee, by penitentiall workes enioyned them by me, and my Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, when they thus had by ſcandalous ſins diſgraced mee, and not yet made mee any due ſatisfaction. And yet in due time, according to the pious diſcretion of my Miniſters, ſuch as theſe were looſed, and reconciled, and were anew admitted to the holy meetings with others, and to the Communion of the Lord's Supper.</p>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:18039:60"/>
               <p>This was a courſe taken to very good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and at length did work great ſetledneſſe, and comfort in the conſciences of ſuch offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, though perhaps it did goe downe with ſome bitterneſſe, and ſhame. For, ſuch a ſinner being in this man<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>er bound by me vpon earth, was infallibly alſo bound in heauen, nor could obtaine remiſſion at God's hands, though hee were neuer ſo well diſpoſed by penitence and inward contrition betweene God and him: for, that promiſe, made by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and cannot faile,
<note place="margin">Matth. 18.18.</note> 
                  <hi>that he would bind in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen all thoſe, whom I had</hi> (without error) <hi>bound vpon earth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 20.23.</note> 
                  <hi>and that he would withhold and ſuspend all remiſsion from thoſe ſinners, whoſe ſinnes I had withheld,</hi> namely by the aforeſaid retention, or excommunication, or ſolemne penance: and as ſoone as ſuch a ſinner, thus firſt bound by me, was afterward reconciled, and remaunded to the Church, and reſtored to religious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, and to the participation of the holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, he did without faile obteine remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, by vertue of his aforeſaid promiſe, that he would releaſe, and forgiue the ſinne aſſoone as I had looſed the perſon, and releaſed the ſinne by this externall remiſſion:
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:18039:61"/>and ſo the internal remiſſion afforded by <hi>Chriſt</hi> in ſuch a caſe, dependeth vpon the externall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion giuen by me; which truely was a way of dealing on a very ſure hand. And moreouer, many grieuous, and alſo ſecret offenders, nay perhaps all the ſort of them, in regard of the ſuretie of this courſe, came to their Biſhop, or to ſome other deputed by him, who was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward called the <hi>Penitentiary,</hi> or <hi>Confeſsor;</hi> and, ſome openly with a lowd and audible voyce, others more priuily vnto the eare, but in a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique place in the Church, confeſſed their ſinnes, thoſe ſinnes, I meane, that were very grieuous, and enormous; and cauſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in this man<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>er, as I haue ſaid, to be bound or excommunicated, and to haue penance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned them, that they might afterwards in fit time get reconciliation by the power of the keyes, and conſequently forgiueneſſe in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen without faile.</p>
               <p>And here you are to obſerue, that the Keyes were employed onely vpon great and enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous crimes (for as for more light, and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ſinnes, though mortall, there were other externall remedies, as I ſhall hereafter ſhew,) and that by way of accuſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, either by others,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:18039:61"/>or by the delinquent himſelfe: but the bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and reconciling, and whole proceſſe was in the ſame man<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>er. Whereby you may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, that this was not a Sacrament, as the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts would now haue it: for, vpon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation of others, and iudiciall conuiction, they proceeded vnto this binding, and iniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of penance, after which, the partie accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, aſwell not confeſſing, as confeſſing pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely, or priuately, was abſolued with the ſame for me of reconcilement: neither is there to be found in thoſe dayes any other Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or Abſolution. Moreouer, that this was not then any Sacrament, it appeareth in that there was not any verball Abſolution, nor any ordinary forme of abſoluing, but this alone was ſufficient, that the Biſhop, or his Subſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute did giue leaue to the penitent to come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church, euen into the place where the other people remained, which were not in pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and to partake the Communion with them. And this was alwayes called <hi>Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> not Abſolution. And howſoeuer after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards there were brought-in certaine prayers, which were pronounced ouer the penitent in the act of his reconcilement, yet all was by
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:18039:62" rendition="simple:additions"/>way of ſupplication, and not by <hi>authoritatiue Abſolution,</hi> as may be yet ſeene in the Romane <hi>Pontificall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as for other ſinnes, which were not ſo grieuous, and enormous, howſoeuer mortall of themſelues, God, in his mercy, doeth require leſſe diſpoſition, and leſſe adoe concerning them: and ſo ſuppoſing alwayes inward repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, namely deteſtation of thoſe ſinnes, and firme remouall of the will from them, and liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly faith, and due confidence, God hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to acquite them much more eaſily, vpon ſome performances taught, and impoſed in the holy Scripture: as principally the Lord's praier taught by my Sauiour <hi>Chriſt.</hi> For, aſſuredly vpon the preſenting that petition, <hi>Forgiue vs our trespaſſes, as wee forgiue them that trespaſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs,</hi> there followeth the remiſſion of ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and ſmaller ſinnes; which <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi> and other holy Fathers doe vnderſtand of ſinnes, which are in trueth <hi>mortall,</hi> howſoeuer they ſtyle them by the name of <hi>venial,</hi> not that a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall ſinne is not mortall, (for euery ſinne, that is truely a ſinne, is mortall, and, if not mortall, it is no ſinne) but becauſe it is in that ſort mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall that God vouchſafeth to deeme it veniall,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:18039:62" rendition="simple:additions"/>that is, fit to be pardoned with more facilitie, then other heinous offences, which by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Fathers are called <hi>crimes,</hi> and diſtinguiſhed from ordinary faults; yet both the one, and the other are mortall. In like ſort theſe leſſer, or veniall ſinnes are cancelled vpon giuing of Almes, <hi>(for, as water putteth out fire,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ecclus. 5.30.</note> 
                  <hi>ſo Almes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſheth ſinne)</hi> as alſo vpon vndergoing tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations with faith, and patience.
<note place="margin">Ecclus. 2.11.</note> 
                  <hi>God is full of compaſsion, and very pitifull, and forgiueth ſinnes, and ſaueth in time of affliction:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 6.37.</note> Alſo vpon pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of iniuries, <hi>Forgiue, and it ſhall be forgiuen vnto you:</hi> Alſo at my requeſts, and interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſuch ſinnes are remitted,
<note place="margin">Amb. depae. nit. l. 1. c. 1. &amp; l. 2. c. 7. Aug. l. 3. de bapt. c. 17. Chryſ. in ep. ad Rom. home 24.</note> and <hi>gemitu co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumbae,</hi> by my groaning, as you may finde in S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> and S. <hi>Auguſtine:</hi> with other conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent wayes alſo taught, and allowed by holy Scripture, and expounded by S. <hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But beware, leſt you beleeue, that any ſinnes, howſoeuer veniall, are cancelled by the holy-water-ſprinkle: this is a meere ſuperſtition. Where doeth the holy Scripture euer teach, that ſinnes are waſhed away by water of the Prieſts hallowing? This were to bring in a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Baptiſme. They will haue this effect to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, either <hi>ex opere operato,</hi> or elſe <hi>ex opere ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantis.</hi>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:18039:63" rendition="simple:additions"/>That is to ſay; They will haue this effect to bee wrought either by the water it ſelfe, through the vertue of the benediction of it, if there be no impediment in him, that is ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with it; or elſe they will haue it to come of the deuotion of him that vſeth this water. If they ſay <hi>by the deed done,</hi> (as for the moſt part they auouch) this is an intolerable impudency, namely to auouch, that the hallowing of this water doeth giue vnto it a certaine ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall force to cleanſe ſinnes, without any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diuine inſtitution or promiſe, and ſo this becommeth the dotage of the Turkes, who by often waſhings hold themſelues to be purified from their ſinnes without faile: and how then can there be a more formall ſuperſtition, then to giue to things meerely naturall and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine a certaine ſupernaturall force? If they will ſay, that it commeth <hi>ex opere operantis,</hi> to what purpoſe then ſerues that water, otherwiſe then to bring-in the ſuperſtition? The other operation, which they attribute hereunto, is the ſcaring away of Diuels: which certainely this water cannot doe, vnleſſe God doe impart ſuch vertue vnto it: And where, I pray you, hath God bound himſelfe to giue ſuch vertue
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:18039:63"/>to a creature by the bleſſing of a Prieſt? I would haue you therefore to fly from holy Water, as from an idle ſuperſtition; ſo alſo take heed you beleeue not, that bleſſings giuen by Pope, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, or Prieſt, whileſt they make the ſigne of the Croſſe ouer you in the aire, can cancel your ſinnes though but veniall; which is likewiſe a ſuperſtition of the ſame kinde; whereto I may adde the <hi>Agnus Dei,</hi> and other ſuch idle trinkets.</p>
               <p>Well may yee collect out of that, which I haue ſaid, and obſerue how manifold, &amp; great are the abuſes of the <hi>Romane</hi> faction about <hi>Confeſsion.</hi> Firſt, they make a Sacrament where none is, taking the word <hi>Sacrament</hi> in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and ſtrict ſenſe. Secondly, they allow an efficacie to <hi>authoritatiue abſolution,</hi> which is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neceſſary, nor hath any force at all; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation being ſufficient, which in ancient times might bee performed euen by my Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, but ſo as in my name. Thirdly, they make <hi>Auricular Confeſsion</hi> neceſſary (at leaſt in mens deſire of it when it cannot bee had) for the remiſſion of euery mortall ſinne. Yet haue I ſhewed you, that it is left to your liberty thus to worke, or no, your owne ſecurity, by firſt
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:18039:64"/>cauſing your ſelues to be bound by the keyes, that afterwards you may bee let looſe by the ſame. And this retention, or binding, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communing, ought not to bee vndertaken by me for petty ſinnes, but onely for thoſe, that are heynous and ſcandalous; there beeing in my family ſo many other meanes for remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of venials, yet alwayes ſuppoſing Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Fourthly, they doe firſt abſolue, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards impoſe the penance; that is to ſay, they looſe him, whom they neuer bound, and then they bind him againe, whom they neuer looſe afterward. And yet, for my part, I cannot looſe, but that onely, which my ſelfe haue bound; and my order is firſt to binde, and then to looſe; which is the true vſe of the keyes. True it is, that euery ſinne doth preſently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God binde euery ſinner, and of this bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Chriſt</hi> did not ſpeake, when he ſaid, <hi>Whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer yee ſhall looſe in earth, ſhall be looſed in heauen:</hi> inaſmuch as my looſing is a relatiue vnto my binding; and therefore <hi>Christ</hi> there vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not that bond, whereby a ſinner is bound before God, but that bond which is knitte by me; <hi>whatſoeuer,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>yee ſhall binde:</hi> and when a ſinner doth binde himſelfe before
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:18039:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>God by his ſinne, it is not I that binde him, but hee bindeth himſelfe by ſinning. Therefore I let looſe nothing, but that, which my ſelfe haue bound, and ſo the binding goeth before, with impoſing of penance, and ſatisfaction, and then in good order followeth looſing. And he, that is bound onely before God, and not in reſpect of mee, cannot be looſed by me; becauſe I neuer bound him: but he muſt ſeeke his looſing of God, and cary this buſineſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God and him alone, and then he knoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth at the right doore for <hi>Abſolution.</hi> Which if hee deſire to haue at my hands, let him firſt come to haue me binde him, and ſubiect him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to my holſome cenſures, and then in fitte time I may let him looſe againe, inaſmuch as I haue bound him. Thus, and not otherwiſe, ſtandeth the caſe of <hi>Abſolution</hi> by my keyes, there beeing alſo a liberty left to euery grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous offendor to vſe, or not to vſe the benefit thereof; beeing, that euen without theſe keyes he may be aſſoyled from his ſinnes: alwayes excepting thoſe offenders, who being accuſed before mee, though againſt their owne wills, ſtand bound by mee. And for ſuch as theſe, my Spouſe committed the keyes to mee to
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:18039:65"/>binde, and looſe withall; but he dothnot ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige any man to come to me, that I may binde him, and afterwards looſe him, there beeing other ordinary meanes of remiſſion prouided for ſuch, namely Repentance: onely thoſe, that either with, or againſt their owne wills haue beene bound by mee, are obliged by mee to wait their deliuerance at my hands, without which my releaſe (except in caſe of neceſſity) by vertue of <hi>Chriſt's</hi> owne words, they ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer bee looſed in heauen. And in this man<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>er I exhort all of you, my beloued children, in grieuous ſinnes alwaies to ſeeke to haue remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion by my keyes, ſubiecting your ſelues vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily to my binding, but ſecretly, that you may afterward obtaine at my hands Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilement, whereupon infallibly followeth loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in heauen.</p>
               <p>Behold this Rocke of <hi>Confeſsion,</hi> and <hi>Abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> which are ſo corruptly, and prepoſterouſly handled by the Romaniſts. They load you with more bonds then you are liable vnto: they beare you in hand with a Sacrament, where indeede there is none: they ſecure you with Abſolution <hi>ex opere operato;</hi> whereupon you, putting ſuch truſt in the power of this
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:18039:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>Abſolution, eſpecially in that it beareth the name to make you <hi>ex attritis contritos,</hi> it maketh you caſt away all care, and luls you faſt aſleepe, ſo that you looke not after true inward repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, without which it is not poſſible to haue true remiſſion, and you rely too-too much vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Abſolution, which is giuen you with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out firſt beeing exerciſed in penance. And, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, how many wretches be there among you, that lead ſtill a wicked life vpon preſumption of the great force of Abſolution, ſaying thus to themſelues, When I ſhall be at the brinke of death I will confeſſe mee, and receiue Abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo I ſhall ſtand on a ſure ground. But Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> ſaith to ſuch as theſe,
<note place="margin">Aug. lib. 50. hom. 41. &amp; ſerm. 47. de temp.</note> that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede hee will not deny them reconciliation preſently vpon their confeſſion, but he will not bee their warant, that it will boot them at all; becauſe there doth not come betweene their <hi>Confeſsion,</hi> and reconcilement ſuch penitence as is neceſſary. And ſo in a moſt important buſineſſe concerning your ſoules, you my chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, that are blinde, are lead by blinde guides, and both of you fall into the gulfe, and beat your ſhip againſt this infamous Rocke of <hi>Aua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice:</hi> for your Confeſſors (excepting ſome few
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:18039:66" rendition="simple:additions"/>good ones) ordinarily, when as they ſee your almes prepared, eſpecially when it gliſters ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yellow, then white, they preſently abſolue you, when you are nothing fit for it; or, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine the more pay, they ſhuffle vp the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, that they may runne ouer others, and ſo they diſpatch you without examining, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſifting your conſciences, without due con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering your eſtate as well, or ill diſpoſed for <hi>Abſolution.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I paſſe ouer the abhominable abuſes of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king aduantage of <hi>Confeſsion,</hi> either to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the ſecrets of Princes, &amp; States, or to make way for inclinations to forraigne Princes, or to fiſh for inheritances, and legacies, or to ſatisfie their owne wanton luſts. I paſſe by the errors, and groſſe enormities, whereby, vpon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the ſecrecie of the ſeale of <hi>Confeſsion,</hi> rebellions, conſpiracies, king-killing, and ſuch like abhominations are couched, cheriſhed, &amp; ſecured. Iudge you therefore, if this be not an horrible and dreadfull Rocke: Let vs paſſe on to the reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="rock">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:18039:66"/>
               <head>¶ <hi>The third Rocke, with two blind</hi> Rockes abutting, namely <hi>Purgatory,</hi> together with <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> and <hi>Indulgences.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He diſtinction of fault, and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in mens ſinnes, beeing an vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtart inuention, yet ſome Ages ſince deuiſed by my ſtubborne vnruly daughter the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> for the feeding thereby her vnſatiable auarice; this diſtinction, I ſay, hath layd the foundation of that harmefull Rocke of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> inlarging it ſelfe with thoſe two vnderlurking companions, <hi>Satisfaction</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter abſolution, or <hi>Penance,</hi> as they call it, and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences.</hi> I, for my part, through many the purer ages, haue alwayes publiſhed abſolute, and entire pardon, and complete remiſſion of ſinnes; for ſuch I haue learned of my Spouſe, of whom it is long ſince teſtified in the Pſalme, that <hi>with him there is plenteous redemption;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſalm. 130.7.</note> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did I euer finde, that hee, in pardoning of ſinnes, and giuing Abſolution from the fault, did at any time change the eternal puniſhment
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:18039:67"/>into temporall, or euer enioyned any puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<note place="margin">Luke 7.48.</note> or ſatisfaction. Behold the example of the ſinfull woman:
<note place="margin">Matth. 9.2.</note> of the man ſicke of the palſie: conſider the parable of the debtors, <hi>I forgaue thee all thy debt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 18.32.</note> So alſo by <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> that, God, when hee pardoneth a man his ſinnes, <hi>mentioneth them to him no more:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezech. 18.22.</note> whereas, if hee left their debt of puniſhment vnſatisfied, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely he ſhould remember it vntill the ſaid puniſhment were wholly performed. And how can it bee ſaid that a man doeth pardon his enemie, if, forbearing to take away his life, hee ſhould make reſeruation vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe of ſome other reuenge vpon him, though not mortall: Alas, what a pinching pardon were this.</p>
               <p>Are <hi>Christ's</hi> ſatisfactions ſufficient for the whole fault, and are they not for the whole puniſhment? Or rather, hath not <hi>Christ</hi> taken vpon himſelfe intirely all my both faults, and puniſhments? And as for humane ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſo vile as they are, what price can they carry, being alſo due debt vnto God in many other reſpects?</p>
               <p>But if you looke backe vnto my continuall practiſe, which I layed open to you in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couery
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:18039:67"/>of the laſt-touched Rocke, ye ſhall find that after Reconciliation, (which they now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes call Abſolution) I did neuer impoſe any ſatisfaction or penance vpon Penitents. I did indeed, before the looſing ſuch offenders, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe vpon them ſome penall workes, yet not as ſatisfactory, nor that by them they might rid themſelues from the bonds of puniſhment due to their ſinnes, whether temporall, or eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall; (What acceptable ſatisfaction can hee giue, who as yet is in diſgrace) but that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they might ſtirre vp inward repentance, and ſhew foorth their humiliation, and edifie their brethren ſcandalized by their heinous ſinnes. Euen as the penitence vſed by King <hi>Ahab,</hi> when hee faſted, and put on ſackcloth, was approued, and accepted of God, not as ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory, but as an outward ſigne of inward humiliation:
<note place="margin">1. King. 21.29.</note> 
                  <hi>Seest thou</hi> (ſaith God to <hi>Elias</hi>) <hi>how Ahab is humbled before me? becauſe hee humbleth himſelfe, therefore I will not bring that euill in his dayes.</hi> And this is that, which was ſaid by pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent <hi>Dauid, A contrite &amp; humbled heart, O God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.17.</note> 
                  <hi>thou wilt not despiſe.</hi> Contrite by true inward repentance, and humbled with thoſe outward ſignes, namely, lowly, and penall workes, by
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:18039:68"/>which the penitent ſheweth, that hee will not ſtand out with God: but that laying aſide all hautineſſe, hee ſubiecteth himſelfe to God's hand, and mercie; So alſo did the <hi>Niniuites,</hi> humbling themſelues with faſting, ſackcloth, and aſhes, going ſo low, that they made the very beaſts to faſt: Which faſting ſurely could be neither meritorious, nor ſatisfactory: but to the end that the fairer euidence might bee giuen of their owne true repentance, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired that their humiliation might appeare e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in the very beaſts. To this end haue I made the pious inſtitution of <hi>Lent,</hi> which in order of time is to goe before <hi>Eaſter,</hi> to the end that my children might bee the better prepared by fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtings, prayers, and other actions of deuotion, to receiue afterward in the holy feaſt of Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter reconcilement, and full remiſſion of their ſinnes; and by this inſtitution, <hi>Penance</hi> is to goe before Remiſſion, or Abſolution, and not to follow after it.</p>
               <p>It cannot be denied, that oftentimes by the ſcourge of outward afflictions and tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<note place="margin">Hebr. 12.6.</note> God doeth bring thoſe, whom he loueth, to this aforeſaid neceſſary humiliation, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo hereby trieth them, as gold is tried in the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:18039:68" rendition="simple:additions"/>furnace, and is content that ſuch chaſtiſements as theſe, inflicted by him, ſhall ſtand in the ſtead of puniſhment due to their ſinnes:
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.32.</note> but withall hee doeth moreouer apply his owne mercy, and pardon, which he affordeth them both of fault, and puniſhment: and ſuch fauors vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed by God are not halfed, nor pinched, but full and complete. When therefore hee recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth a man vnto fauour, he pardoneth him all: yet doeth God ſometimes before hand, in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning an heinous crime, ioyne alſo ſome no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious temporall chaſtiſement; the execution whereof may endure euen after the remiſſion of the ſinne; which penaltie God himſelfe doth inflict, and expreſly enioyne, and referrs it not to the voluntary vndertaking, or executing by the penitent:
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 12.22.</note> As vpon <hi>Dauid's</hi> Adultery he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted for a temporall penaltie the death of the child; which <hi>Dauid</hi> could not put by, by any humiliation that hee could vndergoe, or prayers that hee could make: So likewiſe that puniſhment of diuiſion of the Tribes, which was the iuſt reward of <hi>Salomons</hi> miſdeeds,
<note place="margin">1 Reg. 11.31.</note> came to paſſe after his death, and perhaps after that his ſinnes had bene remitted, as we may with good reaſon preſume: So likewiſe <hi>Ahab's</hi> pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:18039:69"/>was accompliſhed in his ſonne's dayes;
<note place="margin">2. Reg. 9.29.</note> and in like man<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>er other penalties alſo inflicted by God without remiſſion. But all theſe are extraordinary caſes, and open chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but not ſatisfactory: and all of them executed in this preſent world. As for vs, we are to hold to that, which is ordinary.</p>
               <p>Being therefore that there neither ought, nor can remaine any obligation vnto any pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment after the ſinne is remitted, (for, true remiſſion is of the puniſhment, aſwell as of the fault) therefore <hi>Penances,</hi> and <hi>Satisfactions,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Abſolution muſt needs bee one of theſe two, either workes of humiliation done out of ſeaſon prepoſterouſly, which for the moſt part are alſo neglected, and omitted by the peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, hauing got their Abſolution before hand: or elſe they are the gaines, and purchaſes of the Confeſſors, who ordinarily, as oft as they can, fly vpon money-mulcts vnder the name of Almes, or for ſaying of <hi>Maſses,</hi> which thoſe Confeſſors offer themſelues ready to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, and tell a tale, that they haue in their handes ſome priuate good buſineſſe, which would fitly be ſet forward with ſuch Almes, as themſelues thus impoſe in penance and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction;
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:18039:69"/>and by this meanes they draw ſtore of water to their mill. And, that which is worſe, the Confeſſors contriue certaine neceſſities of reſtitution, and perhaps ſometimes beare them in hand, that they are bound to reſtore, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as indeed there is no ſuch cauſe, and ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound with the penitent, that hee may giue them a ſet price, and by that meanes obtaine complete Abſolution. O what a deale of chaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering doe they vſe vnder this vaine pretence, that after the remiſſion of the fault there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth yet a temporall puniſhment to bee ſatisfied!</p>
               <p>Behold here the foundation of <hi>Purgatory;</hi> a vaine, and groundleſſe foundation, layd in the aire, raiſed by imagination, being a meere tricke to bring-in money to the Prieſts, and Friars, and beſides them to my Grandees alſo. <hi>Purgatory</hi> by deceitfull deuiſes hath founded the richeſt Abbies, and Priories, and other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious houſes: <hi>Purgatory</hi> maketh faire poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and inheritances to ſtart ouer to my ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Churchmen: <hi>Purgatory</hi> makes ſo many idleſbies to ſwimme in delicacie, and voluptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes: thoſe I meane, that defile the liuing, and feed vpon the dead. For the Preachers,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:18039:70"/>and Confeſſors ſtill crying alowd, that it is not ynough to receiue Abſolution, and remiſſion of ſinnes, as farre as concerneth the fault it ſelfe, but that after all this there remaines a debt of temporall paine, which whoſoeuer doeth not vndergoe in this life, it lyeth vpon him to make the ſcore euen with ſmart y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in another life in <hi>Purgatory;</hi> and for as much as moſt men are very backward in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming theſe <hi>Satisfactions,</hi> at length when they come to the point of death, then are they much affrighted with thoſe grieuous paines, which, as they are borne in hand, doe awaite them in <hi>Purgatory,</hi> and then the poore wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, to ſcape this brunt, giue what they can to the Church, that is, to the bellies of the Prieſts, and Friars, by whom they are perſwaded, that this is the onely way to ouerleape <hi>Purgatory.</hi> And if he, that lyes thus at mercy, drop away without paying ſuch ranſome, then they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaguer his children or other his heires, or exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors, vrging them, for the pulling their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or brothers, or huſbands, or ſonnes ſoule out of the horrible torments of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> to make allowance for the ſinging of ſo many <hi>Maſses:</hi> or to found, and endow an Altar, a
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:18039:70"/>Chappell, a Church, a dayly <hi>Maſſe</hi> for euer, and a day, or ſome ſuch like erections. So that this ſame <hi>Purgatory</hi> is the nourſe, and chiefe ſuſtei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of an infinite rabble of moſt irregular, and lewd prieſts, who ſtill ring in your eares, that <hi>Maſſes</hi> are true and propitiatory Sacrifices for the liuing, and for the dead.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>Purgatory,</hi> as it hath no foundation, nor reaſon whereupon to build it, ſo the holy Scripture hath none, no not the leaſt, mention of it: but on the contrary it hath many autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, and grounds, a little afore pointed at by me, which proue that it may not in any wiſe be mainteined. The Papiſts haue long gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſhing to finde ſome place in Scripture, which may make a ſemblance of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> but all in vaine. Surely whatſoeuer God would haue me to know as an Article of faith, or as a neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry point, or very important for the ſaluation of my children, he hath ſet it downe in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in ſuch man<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>er, that I may, and ought thence to draw, and auouch it; but he will not in any wiſe, that any of my family out of his owne capricious conceit, ſhould deuiſe an opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and propound it to my children, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he hath thus of his owne head auouched it,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:18039:71"/>then to goe a begging for ſome fragment of a word in Scripture, to maintaine it, as they haue done about <hi>Purgatory:</hi> alleadging for it ſome places, which are ſubiect to many expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, whereof none at all haue any acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with <hi>Purgatory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Verily I neither can, nor may deny, that from my very ancient times I haue alwayes had a good liking, and ſo haue prouided, that in the death of my children (ſuch as died not in very ill, and deſperate eſtate) there ſhould prayers be made, and other deuotions to God, and that for diuers reaſons. Firſt that funerals, and obſequies, being an vniuerſall, and morall cuſtome, intertained by all Nations, and vſed by all ſorts of men, and in that behalfe not to be neglected, they might be continued in my Family, not barely as humane, and naturall ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, but alſo as Chriſtian and religious, and that with giuing thankes to God, that ſuch, or ſuch a ſonne of mine had rendered his ſoule to his Creator, and had paſſed with his holy faith from this my houſe militant to that other Congregation of the firſt borne: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I did reuiue vnto thoſe, that were preſent at the funerall, the memory of the ſoules immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:18039:71" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the expected reſurrection of that dead body, and of the ſtrict vnion that is betweene me and my deereſt ſiſter now triumphing, to whom in theſe my prayers for the dead I did direct that ſoule, with very good hope that it was to ariue there.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, beſides this, thoſe my prayers, and ſupplications, which ought to haue beene made ouer the party ready to die, whileſt hee beeing now in his laſt agony cannot performe any longer the actions of penitence and humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation before God, nor acknowledge his owne guilt, nor craue pardon for his daylie ſinnes, I, doing the office of a mother, preſent them for him in his funerall, together with the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his brethren, and vtter thoſe prayers ouer him now dead, which ſhould haue beene vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ouer him dying. And if you would tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly ſift your Maſſes framed for the dead, &amp; the ancient prayers, which are ſet downe in them, beeing currant at this day throughout the Papacie, you ſhould find that they are pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to be vſed rather ouer him, who is at the laſt gaſpe, then who is already dead. For in them I pray for remiſſion, not of any temporall paines, but of the ſinnes themſelues, yea euen
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:18039:72"/>mortall ſinnes, and for deliuerance from <hi>hell;</hi> as alſo in Maſſes for the dead, yee ſhall neuer finde any prayers for freeing the ſoule out of <hi>Purgatory,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Libera animas omnium fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um defunctoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de poenis Infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, &amp; depro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundo lacu; li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bera eas de ore Leonis, ni ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorbeat eas Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarus, nec ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant in obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi> In Miſſa pro defunctis.</note> but expreſſely out of <hi>hell. Deliuer the ſoules of all the faithfull departed from the paines of hell, and from the deepe lake: free them from the mouth of the Lyon, that hell doe not ſwallow them vp, and that they fall not into the darke:</hi> ſo that it is a meere foppery to goe about to picke <hi>Purgatory</hi> out of theſe prayers. Likewiſe thoſe <hi>tridualls,</hi> or thirday-maſſes; thoſe <hi>trentalls,</hi> or moneths<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindes; thoſe <hi>anniuerſaries,</hi> or yeeres-dirges, or ſuch like trinkets are the meere inuentions of <hi>Auarice</hi> aforeſaid, and therefore their thruſting of <hi>Purgatory</hi> vpon you is a very colluſion.</p>
               <p>They auouching, and teaching, that there remaine certaine temporall puniſhments for your mortall ſinnes (which ſinnes yet are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen in this life) doe hereupon inioyne <hi>Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factions</hi> after remiſſion. And here wee finde them intangled in many difficulties: which of them knoweth the quantity of thoſe tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall paines, which God left to be vndergone by the penitent, after that hee is accepted into grace? how can they enioyne a true proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Satisfaction?</hi> If they ſhall impoſe more
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:18039:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>then his debt requires, they ſhall doe him wrong, and deale vniuſtly with him: if they giue him ſhort meaſure, they deceiue him, and defraud him of his entire deliuerance, and ſo the <hi>Confeſſor</hi> by his owne fault tumbles this poore ſoule into <hi>Purgatory</hi> after death. For, if hee had impoſed ſufficient <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> hee had cleane wiped out the skore, and had left the penitent neuer a farthing in debt to <hi>Purgatory.</hi> And as for this <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> by what operation doth it cancell the puniſhment? it were fit that they ſhould declare whether it worke <hi>ex opere operato,</hi> or <hi>ex opere operantis,</hi> by the deede done, or by the diſpoſition of the doer. And heere againe they daſh vpon hard difficulties. Beſides this, where hath God bound himſelfe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe the puniſhment of ſinnes by any action of man? When doth hee, pardoning the fault, leaue a guilt of temporall puniſhment? Doe you ſee into what perplexities, into what dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers they thruſt you? They make you beleeue that <hi>Christ's ſatisfactions</hi> are vnſufficient, ſeeing that now ordinarily they doe not take away all the puniſhment with the fault. They make you to truſt vpon your owne <hi>Satisfactions,</hi> as more able to cancell the puniſhments, then can
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:18039:73"/>be done by <hi>Chriſt's Satisfaction.</hi> They make you remaine in a perpetuall perplexitie and doubt whether you haue fully ſatisfied, or no: They make you lazie and negligent in going thorough-ſtitch with true Repentance, ſuch as God requireth of you, and whereupon hee would giue you a full pardon both of fault and puniſhment: for you deeme their Abſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to bee ſufficient for you, and that it doth without faile make riddance of your fault: and, as for the backe-reckoning of puniſhment, ye cheere vp your ſelues, that a little taſt of <hi>Purgatory</hi> ſhall make you free-men: and ſo it falls out that you paſſe to another life perhaps (which God forefend) with your whole load both of fault, and alſo of obligation vnto eternall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. But when you know there is no <hi>Purgatory</hi> at all, you will, for the ſcaping of hell, looke better to your tacklings: and you will not then ſay, as I heare many among you now ſpeake, <hi>I will not performe the penance, that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned me: I am content rather to make it vp after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in Purgatory:</hi> And your inſtructers teach you, that you may lawfully ſay, and doe thus.</p>
               <p>The other hidden Rocke, that groweth to this Rocke of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> are <hi>Indulgences.</hi> It is a
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:18039:73"/>ſhameleſſe boldneſſe to ſay, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> indeede hath fully ſatisfied for all the puniſhments due to euery ſinner, which addreſſeth himſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him: but yet that the applying of <hi>Christ's</hi> merits goes in this man<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>er: the Confeſſor, when he abſolueth thee, applieth the merits of <hi>Chriſt</hi> vnto thee, onely in reſpect of the fault, and the eternall puniſhment, but as for temporall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, that lies ſtill at thy doore: and that therefore, in reſpect of this puniſhment, it is in the Popes power to apply the ſaid merits of <hi>Chriſt</hi> for the remitting the ſaid puniſhment in part, or in whole, as he ſhall thinke good. But I ſay, if the Confeſſor abſolue by the power of the keyes, who hath reſtrayned him in this Abſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the fault, &amp; not to the entire pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment? who hath halfed out vnto him the power of the keyes, that by them hee ſhould apply the merits of <hi>Christ</hi> for the taking away onely of the fault, and of the eternall puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but not of the temporall? Surely the keyes containe entire remiſſion; who then thus hath minced it out? And if the Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor can impoſe ſuch <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi> whereby all kind of puniſhment may beecancelled, (and certainely, as the Papiſts teach, this <hi>ſatisfaction</hi>
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:18039:74"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:18039:74"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:18039:75"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:18039:75"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:18039:76"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:18039:76"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:18039:77" rendition="simple:additions"/>worketh by the power of the keyes, being Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentall) then his power extendeth alſo to the whole puniſhment: and by abſoluing and by <hi>Abſolution</hi> applying <hi>Chriſt's Satisfactions</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the penitent, hee doth apply them with all the power, and vertue, which is either in <hi>Chriſt's</hi> merits, or in the keyes, or in the Miniſter him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that worketh by them: there is therefore no kind of puniſhment, which he hath not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted: and what then remaines behinde for <hi>Indulgences</hi> to worke vpon?</p>
               <p>I ſay nothing of the merits of the Saints Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pererogation, which they ſhuffle into this Treaſure among <hi>Christ's</hi> merits, with as great falſehood, as wrong, and iniury done to <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe: The falſehood lies in this, for that the workes of any Saints whatſoeuer, both as they are maritorious, (if they may bee called meritorious at all) and alſo as <hi>ſatisfactory,</hi> are wholly pay'd for the Saints owne debt; nor is there any ouerplus left for others in caſe they were ſufficient for the Saint himſelfe, as I ſhall afterward declare. To <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe great wrong is done, as if a man ſhould poure a drop of water into the Sea, and ſhould ſay that this drop carries euery ſhip to the hauen: but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:18039:77" rendition="simple:additions"/>he is wronged, in that onely he, and none elſe, beeing appointed of God the Mediator both for faults, and puniſhments of the world, and all men in it, it muſt needes bee an odious blaſphemy, to ſay that the merits of Saints doe ſerue for the taking away of the puniſhments of ſinnes; for the cancelling whereof God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepteth nothing elſe, but the blood of his one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-begotten Sonne: as alſo hee hath ſent none other, nor choſen any other for that office, then this his only Sonne; neither is any other money currant in Gods Treaſury for our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete redemption, either from fault, or from puniſhment, then the treaſure of the blood, &amp; merits of <hi>Christ,</hi> ſtamped with the image of <hi>Christ</hi> himſelfe: all other money vſed for this purchaſe is falſe coine, and is reiected by the mint-maſter of heauen.</p>
               <p>But, beſides this, how is the Pope inabled to apply the treaſure of <hi>Chriſt's</hi> merits? who hath made him Maſter of it? who hath put into his hands onely the keyes of it? I haue heard, that the principall key, which leads to this treaſure, lieth open in publicke, to be vſed by euery one, that will take it, and that the hand, by which euery one may take it, is true, and liuely faith,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:18039:78"/>nor is there any neede to aske this key of the Pope, or of any other man, it lying open to all; nor to beg of any man the fauour to bee made partaker of this treaſure, which <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath made common, without giuing the cuſtody thereof to any man in the world. I haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede a particular key committed vnto mee by him, but without any preiudice to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon key, which lyeth open to all, and this is that key, by which I binde, and looſe; and this is equally in the hands of euery of my Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and ſpecially of my Biſhops: and this key doth after a ſort apply vnto the penitent that treaſure, namely the merits of <hi>Christ,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the promiſe of <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, who, whenſoeuer he remits the fault, remitteth alſo all kinde of puniſhment; neither is it in my power, or in the power of any that vſeth this key of mine, to ſeparate the puniſhment, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny part thereof from the fault: for the money of this treaſure payes all in the totall, and that is the currant rate of it. It is therefore open ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie in the Pope, to incroach this key into his owne hands onely, and to impart it to whomſoeuer he pleaſe, and in what degree hee thinkes good: whereas this key was giuen to
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:18039:78"/>me, and I haue committed it to the handes of all, and euery my Miniſters equally, without diſtinction. And if there were any true <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences</hi> to bee had, it were a great folly in you to ſeeke them of the Pope, when as your owne Biſhops can aſwell graunt them, as the Pope himſelfe: and this is not denied by the doctors of his owne ſide, namely, thoſe that yeeld, that Biſhops haue all their authoritie, power, and Epiſcopall Iuriſdiction from God, and not from the Pope.</p>
               <p>To compriſe this briefly; There are onely three Keyes, which keepe the treaſury of my houſe: The one is common to all my children, lying open to euery man, as I ſaid, and not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſpecially to the hands of any: the other two are in the hands of my Officers, and of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of them; for, by them onely are they to be imployed, but to the benefit of all the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. One is of the holy Sacraments, namely of <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> and the <hi>Eucharist:</hi> the other is for binding, and looſing, as I haue declared. And whoſoeuer brags, that he hath another key be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides theſe (as the Pope vaunteth that he hath the key of <hi>Indulgences</hi>) hee both is deceiued himſelfe, and deceiueth others. For we haue in
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:18039:79" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Scriptures expreſſe Patent for thoſe three ſorts of Keyes: but of that fourth no graunt appeares, but forgery, and vſurpation; and if it be one of theſe three, it cannot haue any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and diſtinct name, nor different effect, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can it be appropriated to any, more then they: neither can it be vſed otherwiſe, then in remitting the whole puniſhment together with the fault, and ſo it will not bee diuers from them.</p>
               <p>There hath bene indeed in my houſe, and ſtill may be the vſe of certaine <hi>Indulgences,</hi> but without imploying any Treaſure in them (from whence thoſe falſe <hi>Indulgences</hi> haue oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſionally taken their beginning, and not from Apoſtolique tradition, as is pretended.) and this was, when as ſome Penitent being bound by me in man<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>er aforeſaid, with iniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of penance for ſome prefixed, and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate time, wherein the Penitent was to giue euidence of his repentance, and to bee taken downe to a fit degree of humiliation, (which courſe of time for performance of penance, was now and then the ſpace of ſeuen whole yeeres together) yet vpon the good behauiour of the partie, and out of my owne compaſſion,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:18039:79" rendition="simple:additions"/>and mercy towards him, as alſo by the inſtance and prayers of my children, I was wont to ſhorten this time, and to moderate theſe penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and ſo to graunt him reconciliation ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> did to the inceſtious Corinthian.
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 2.10.</note> And this was my <hi>Indulgence</hi> which, as you ſee, hath nothing to doe with the puniſhment of ſinnes, nor with <hi>Purgatory.</hi> For theſe workes of Penance inioyned the Penitent before his Abſolution, were not puniſhments otherwiſe due vnto the ſinne by God's iuſtice, but meere ſignes of repentance, and of neceſſary humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: the true puniſhments of ſinne being can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled by his Reconcilement, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by the applying of <hi>Christ's</hi> treaſure in ſuch ſort, as I haue declared, and not by abreuiating the time of precedent trials, and humiliations.</p>
               <p>So here ye ſee the blind-Rocke of thoſe <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences,</hi> that now-adayes are vſed, A Rocke whereat many doe ſuffer ſhipwracke. The maine miſchiefe of it is, that it taketh away cleane out of the world, and diſanulleth true Chriſtian repentance, and ſo robbeth many a ſoule of the true remiſſion of their ſinnes. I will demonſtrate this to you. A ſinner heauie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loaden with heinous crimes, putting his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:18039:80" rendition="simple:additions"/>in the great vertue of Sacramental Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, which, <hi>ex opere operato,</hi> by the deed done, muſt remit ſinnes, and make <hi>ex attrito contritum,</hi> of a bruſed heart a broken heart, hereupon doeth not hate his ſinne, nor ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre it, and ſo he doth not riſe vp from ſinne; but he goes to finde one of theſe triuiall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, with a brace of ſixpences in his hand, and for more, or leſſe vpon the bargaine, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any troubleſome examination, he gets Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution; and now he holds himſelfe ſecured from his ſinnes, in reſpect of the guilt, and of eternall puniſhment; And as for the tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall puniſhment, there are impoſed vpon him ſo many faſts, ſo many Maſſes, ſuch a quantitie of Almes; which he accepts, but with intent to performe neuer a whit of them. He is content to leaue them on the ſcore for <hi>Purgatory:</hi> and yet he hath a tricke to eſcape that paiment too: he will gape after a <hi>planary Iubily,</hi> or rather he will take a gainer way: hee hath in his Bead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, or Roſary certaine beads, croſſes, and medals, which haue bene all to be-bleſt by the moſt holy Father, and theſe containe in them <hi>Indulgentiam plenariam,</hi> a full Indulgence ouer, and ouer: and ſo with chewing ouer three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:18039:80" rendition="simple:additions"/>and three <hi>Auemaries,</hi> and ſeuen <hi>Paterno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> he hath rid himſelfe of all this trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome matter: and thus without <hi>Penance,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> and without <hi>Purgatory,</hi> hee is more then certaine of <hi>Paradiſe.</hi> And when theſe diueliſh inuentions were firſt in vre, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences <hi>à culpâ, &amp; paenâ,</hi> aſwell from all fault, as puniſhment, were granted, euen without Confeſſion, and without Abſolution to all, that would put to their helping hand, ſo that it had money in it. But now-adaies <hi>(gran-mercy Luther)</hi> the <hi>Pardon-mongers</hi> are ſomewhat more moderate, though not reformed. For they doe not now trucke for the fault, but for the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment onely. Where you may note, at leaſt, the goodly beginning of theſe <hi>Indulgences,</hi> with marting the remiſſion of ſinnes, at <hi>What will you giue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And yet notwithſtanding, for the gaine, that commeth of them, they are defended, and extolled by the Papiſts, as likewiſe the <hi>Stations</hi> to ſuch, and ſuch Churches, the viſiting of ſuch an Altar, or ſuch Reliques, with ſo much adoe in iangling the Bells for many dayes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and ſetting vp titles and banners in the chiefe corners, and eminent places of the Citie,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:18039:81"/>with vehement vrging theſe things in the pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit. Such doings as theſe, whither elſe do they tend, but to rob you, my ſimple children, of your money? But ſuch <hi>Stations</hi> as theſe, and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences,</hi> leſt they ſhould paſſe without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to the Pope, they are not granted, but in his Court of <hi>Chancery,</hi> in forme of <hi>Bulls;</hi> and this is a very good meanes for the ingroſſing vp of money at Rome. To preuent murmures of the people, there was a new deuiſe brought into Rome for the ſpeeding of <hi>Indulgences, per Breue, &amp; gratis,</hi> by Breues, without fees, but now-adayes againe he, that will haue any of theſe gainefull <hi>Indulgences,</hi> muſt goe the olde way by the <hi>Chancery,</hi> and by <hi>Bulls;</hi> as for <hi>Breues,</hi> they are rarely graunted, and they alſo now not altogether <hi>gratis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it is an excellent tricke of thrift the Pope hath gotten vp, both in leuying forces and Souldiers in forreine Eſtates for his owne enterpriſes, as alſo in giuing of preſents, which, as a temporall Prince, he is to beſtow on other Princes, and on their Embaſſadors: he, to ſaue his owne purſe, puts his hand into the endleſſe treaſure of <hi>Indulgences,</hi> and loads them with
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:18039:81" rendition="simple:additions"/>whole bags full of bleſſed beads, medailes and croſlets of copper, &amp; paltry pictures printed on paper, with a catalogue of <hi>Indulge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces</hi> belonging to them: whereof more accompt is made by the Pope's gentle cuſtomers then of ſo many Spaniſh <hi>Doublons.</hi> Such trinkets as theſe, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the tricke of a plenary <hi>Indulgence,</hi> and of opening the gate of Paradiſe, fly abroad vpon euery deſigne of the Popes. And yet all this while this treaſure ſhrinketh not, but it bulkes vp euery day by the canonizing of new Saincts, and with their merits and works of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pererogation. O wofull blindneſſe of men, which take no knowledge of ſuch abuſes and deceits!</p>
               <p>The Pope not content with the Keyes of heauen, and earth, will needs haue his keyes reach vnder the earth alſo, and exerciſeth his omnipotence vpon the ſoules, which are in the center of the earth, ſtretching forth his <hi>Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences</hi> vnto the imagined <hi>Purgatory, per modum ſuffragij,</hi> by way of ſuffrage; but ſo, that they may haue their certaine effect without faile, as much as concerneth his authoritie, if the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſition of the ſoules themſelues doe not hinder it: and all this for the whetting on of
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:18039:82"/>ſimple men, eſpecially ſilly women in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of ſuch a ſoule to multiply Maſſes at pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledged Altars, to lay on load of Almes, to giue large legacies to Chapters, Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uents, Schooles, Chappels, and Altars: To this end alſo they bring fabulous <hi>Legends,</hi> they deuiſe miracles, and reuelations from another world, with a thouſand prettie leaſings to gull ſimple people. Behold here new Articles of Chriſtian Religion made out at the fingers ends, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of netts are knit to fiſh for gold, and ſiluer. Theſe be the Rockes, and vnderſhelfes, which ſplit many a poore ſoule: I would haue you, my children, know how to eſcape them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="rock">
               <head>¶ The fourth Rocke. Inuocation of Saincts.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Rocke alſo hath need of warie obſeruation. It is good in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent life, for one to recommend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the prayers of another, and chiefly to the prayers of a whole particular Church. In this man<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>er S. <hi>Paul</hi> oftentimes recommends
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:18039:82"/>himſelfe to the prayers of the faithfull people, to whom he writes; but in this caſe there is no Religious <hi>Inuocation,</hi> neither are thoſe, to whom a man thus recommends himſelfe, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vpon as Mediators betweene God and him, but as companions, and brethren, which both heare, and vnderſtand that, which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended vnto them. There is no doubt at all, but that the holy Angels, and bleſſed ſoules in heauen, according to their inflamed chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, doe intercede with God for me, and all you, they being (as S.
<note place="margin">Cypr de mortalitate.</note> 
                  <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith) <hi>in ſure poſſeſsion of their owne glory, and carefull for the ſaluation of you,</hi> my children: and therefore no Catholique man will euer deny ſuch interceſſion of the <hi>Saincts.</hi> But to make religious <hi>Inuocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> of them, that is, to call vpon them with a certaine affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and opinion of a kind of Deitie in them, whereby they may heare, and attend vs, or, as mediators appointed vs by God, to treat of our ſaluation with him; this is a perilous matter, and ſmells ſtrong of Idolatry. And certainely this cannot be done without great wrong vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who is appointed by the Father for our onely Mediator, and Aduocate. Why therefore ſhould wee here ouerpaſſe <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
                  <pb n="144" facs="tcp:18039:83"/>whoſe proper office it is to be our Aduocate, and, in ſtead of him, hold our ſelues to his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants. They neither doe, nor can heare the praiers of men: and whoſoeuer calls them thus to be his helpe, and inuoketh them, ſuppoſeth an infinite, and plainely diuine vertue in them, that they can heare all. If the moſt bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine the mother of <hi>Chriſt</hi> could heare, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten to all particular men, who throughout the whole earth pray to her, and call vpon her, and very many of them at the ſame moment, ſhe ſhould be God, and not a creature: or, if God were pleaſed to reueale ſuch prayers vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Saincts, and that ſuch <hi>Inuocations</hi> were acceptable to his heauenly Maieſtie, certainely the Scripture would either expreſly deliuer it vnto me, or would imply it in ſome degree, whereas it doeth plainely teach me the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, nor will ſuffer me to inuocate any other, but God, and his onely-begotten Sonne my Spouſe.</p>
               <p>Know you therefore, that the diſorders of this <hi>inuocation,</hi> hath runne on ſo much the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in that the common people put far more confidence in the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> or in ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he or ſhe Saint (who perhaps is not in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen)
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:18039:83" rendition="simple:additions"/>then in <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, and certainely they do make more prayers and Maſſes to the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Virgin,</hi> or to ſome <hi>Saints,</hi> then vnto <hi>Chriſt:</hi> and howſoeuer in the <hi>Litanies</hi> and publique prayers vnder the Papacy, they ſay, <hi>ora pro no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis,</hi> pray for vs, yet if you examine ſilly women, and men of the vulgar ſort, you ſhall find, that they call vpon them properly as on ſo many gods, and that they vſe ordinarily to ſay, <hi>Saint Mary helpe mee, Saint Charles Borromeo ſaue mee.</hi> Goe to <hi>Millaine,</hi> and enquire among the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and you ſhall finde that this ſame <hi>Charles</hi> hath not onely driuen the renowned St. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> out of their hearts there, (who now in compariſon of this Saint <hi>Charles,</hi> is much aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in his reputation) but alſo that they put more truſt in their <hi>new</hi> Saint <hi>Charles,</hi> then in <hi>Chriſt.</hi> The reaſon is, becauſe they ſee the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnities of St. <hi>Charles</hi> ſet out with far greater pompe then thoſe of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> which doth infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly breede this errour in the mindes of the vulgar.</p>
               <p>The great ones of <hi>Rome</hi> doe willingly che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh theſe <hi>Inuocations</hi> and Idolatries, and make them Articles of Faith, that the Statues, and Images may be of more force to mooue you to
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:18039:84"/>make large contributions for the building of Churches, and Monaſteries to their names, and to endow them with faire reuenues. I know well, that ſome witty and ſubtile braines can by certaine metaphyſicall formallities frame and accommodate the conſcience to digeſt this kind of <hi>Inuocation:</hi> but by their leaue, it is farre more ſafe to hold off from it: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore yee ſhall doe well to abſteine, foraſmuch as this your abſteining tendeth not to any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Saints themſelues, but to the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping your ſelues from falling into theſe errors: neither will <hi>Chriſt</hi> take it ill, that you keepe your ſelues from ſuch <hi>Inuocations,</hi> leaſt you ſhould diſhonour him; and the Saints them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, if they were to counſaile you, would ſpeake thus: Imitate our holy actions, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme your ſelues to our liuely faith, and holy life; honour vs in your hearts, as the faithfull ſeruants of God, and in thus doing yee ſhall yeelde vs all the reſpect you owe vs. The moſt holy Mother of my Sauiour, for her part, would giue you the very ſame counſaile, and that with more vehemencie: for, ſhee would tell you, that it is irkeſome, and loathſome vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her, that you thus call vpon her, and make
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:18039:84" rendition="simple:additions"/>recourſe euer and anon to her: ſhee would tell you alſo, that thoſe glorious titles of <hi>Queene, Hope, Saluation, Aduocate,</hi> ſound abhominably in her eares, and make her ſicke againe, ſhe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging her ſelfe to bee none other then <hi>the handmaid of the Lord;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 1.38.</note> therefore take heede of this Rocke alſo. And when you repeat the <hi>Aue-mary,</hi> recite it hiſtorically in remembrance of the Incarnation of the Sonne of God in the moſt chaſt wombe of the Virgin. Prophane it not with that <hi>Inuocation, Sancta Maria, mater Dei, ora pro nobis, &amp;c.</hi> Holy <hi>Mary,</hi> the mother of God, pray for vs, &amp;c. For, certainely in ancient times thoſe words were not wont to be added in my houſe, as alſo you ſhall finde the <hi>Aue-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> without them in the later Catholique Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells of <hi>Germany,</hi> before that of <hi>Trent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And becauſe it is a laudable deuotion which hath anciently bene vſed, to make commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of <hi>Chriſts</hi> Incarnation three ſeuerall times in the day at the publique tolling of a bell, which is called <hi>the Aue-mary,</hi> namely, at Sunne-riſe, at noone, and Sunne-ſet, it were good that you would firſt purge or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it, and then beeing reformed vſe it zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly and vnto edification. You ſhall reforme
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:18039:85"/>it, if kneeling downe vpon your knees you ſhall ſay in this maner. <hi>The Angell of the Lord brought a meſſage to the virgin Mary ſaying to her, Hayle Mary full of grace, the Lord is with thee, thou art bleſſed among women; and ſhee ſaide, Behold the handmaid of the Lord, be it vnto me according to thy word. Then the word was made fleſh, and dwelt among vs: O thou that diddeſt beleeue this, thou art ſurely bleſſed, and bleſſed is the fruit of thy wombe, Ieſus. O Lord God, poure downe thy grace into our ſoules, that wee, which by the meſſage of an Angell haue knowen the Incarnation of thy Son Iefus Chriſt, may by his Croſſe, and Paſsion, bee lead to the glory of his holy reſurrection, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="rock">
               <head>¶ The fift Rocke. Images, and Reliques.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Ictures, and Statues in ancient times were vſed, as in priuate houſes, ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in publique Churches, onely for remembrance of ſacred hiſtories, and for the benefit of them, that could not, or would not read bookes. Wherein they beholding the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:18039:85" rendition="simple:additions"/>of <hi>Christ</hi> vpon the Croſſe, of the martyrdomes, and memorable actions of holy men, might for their owne particular remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the benefit of their redemption, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound vnto themſelues examples for imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the maintenance of our holy faith, and the exerciſe of chriſtian vertues. Othervſe of <hi>Images</hi> then this, which is ciuill, I was not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with for many Ages; But after that the couetouſneſſe of men did runne on, inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and forging of myracles to draw on the peoples deuotion towards ſome <hi>Image,</hi> and ſo their contributions vnder pretence of lampes, ornaments, and other materiall embelliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; thence began they to teach, that there was a certaine proper religious worſhip due to the <hi>Image</hi> it ſelfe, and then my idle Miniſters beganne to light lampes to them, to burne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe to them, to adore them, to kneele downe, and make their prayers before them. Hence aroſe that abuſe, that none vnder the Papacie knoweth how to pray, without he haue before him ſome pettie ſtatue, or picture, either pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or printed, eſpecially of the Crucifix, and of our Lady. And the Church-men doe wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully infuſe true and proper Idolatrie into the
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:18039:86" rendition="simple:additions"/>mindes of the ignorant common people, whileſt they erect ſtately Churches, curious Chappells, with ſo many encloſures, veſteries, curtaines, lampes, torches, indulgences: whileſt they carry them in Proceſſion with ſuch furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and outward pompe, beeing an externall religious worſhippe, which pertaineth vnto God: they command, and compell euery man to fall downe on his knees, and adore them, whereupon the ſilly people conceiueth a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine diuinity to be in them, and without any reflection at all <hi>ad prototypum</hi> to the principall copie, they offer their vowes, and their prayers to that ſtocke, or ſtone; to this cloth, or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blet, and expect immediately from that very <hi>Image</hi> the grace, which they requeſt, euen of eternall life. It is not to bee doubted, but that the more part of the vulgar commits moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and formall Idolatrie with ſome <hi>Images.</hi> And the doctrine, which ſome learned Papiſts doe teach, namely, that vnto <hi>Images,</hi> as <hi>Images,</hi> a proper religious worſhip is due, muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity make euen the wiſe, &amp; learned amongſt them to Idolatrize formally.</p>
               <p>A wodden Crucifixe repreſenting <hi>Christ</hi> on the Croſſe may awake the minde of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:18039:86" rendition="simple:additions"/>to adore with his ſoule him, that is repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, namely true <hi>Christ:</hi> but to teach a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per worſhip, beſides that, which is due vnto the <hi>prototype,</hi> and a proper adoration to bee due to a Crucifixe made of wood, onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it repreſents the true <hi>Christ,</hi> this is to bring-in flat Idolatrie. If they ſhall tell you, that a certaine humane, and ciuill reuerence is to bee giuen to the <hi>Images</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and alſo of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and eminent Saints, ſuch as are canonized by holy Scripture, ſuch reſpect, I ſay, as is due to the <hi>Images</hi> of great Princes, and Emperors, and famous benefactors, or of the progenitors of noble families, publiquely aduanced, or priuately reſpected; in this there were no error, nor any danger at all. But whileſt they will needs haue it to be religious, and ſpirituall worſhip, let them cloth it as cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly as they can, with the names of <hi>dulia,</hi> or <hi>hyperdulia</hi> to balke the name of <hi>latria,</hi> yet in the end it commeth to be a very <hi>latria,</hi> diuine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: inaſmuch as religious, and ſpirituall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is, nor can be any other then <hi>latria,</hi> which is the very adoration performed inwardly in the minde and ſpirit, and outwardly by the body vnto the onely true God.</p>
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:18039:87"/>
               <p>And why did God ſo ſeuerely command in the firſt table of his liuely, and eternall law, that his faithfull people ſhould beware of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any <hi>Images</hi> of what ſort ſoeuer, to be vſed in any religious worſhip, if not, becauſe hee knew, that all ſuch worſhippe of them muſt needes be <hi>Idolatry?</hi> Thinke you that the Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Gentiles did indeede worſhip thoſe Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of marble, wood, and mettall, as thinking that they were the very gods, whom they ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red? It is a folly ſo to deeme. But in that they gaue honor, and reuerence vnto thoſe Statues, as repreſenting thoſe men, whom they held for gods, nay otherwhile repreſenting ſuch beaſts, as they thought had a kinde of diuinity in them; in this reſpect our ſacred Scripture doth deride them,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 115.5.</note> ſaying, <hi>The Idolls of the heathen are ſiluer and gold, the worke of mens hands: they haue mouthes, but they ſpeake not, eyes haue they, but they ſee not, they haue eares, but they heare not, &amp;c.</hi> Whereby their Idolatry is reduced, not onely to their adoring, for gods, very men, or very beaſts, (which is indeede the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Idolatry of all) but alſo much more, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they, hauing made thoſe their Statues, &amp; Images, did render vnto theſe very ſame Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:18039:87"/>and <hi>Images</hi> a certaine proper worſhip, as being the Statues, and <hi>Images</hi> repreſenting thoſe, whom they held for true Gods. In like man<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>er alſo, whileſt Chriſtians doe yeelde vnto an <hi>Image</hi> a certaine proper religious worſhip, though onely as it repreſenteth the true <hi>Christ,</hi> the holy Scripture by the ſame reaſon will ſay of them, <hi>The Chriſtians Images are wood or cloth, the worke of mens hands: they haue mouthes, and ſpeake not, eyes, and ſee not, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither doth it excuſe the matter, to ſay, that in the <hi>Image,</hi> the <hi>prototype</hi> or firſt paterne is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dored. For, the action in it ſelfe is vnlawfull, and directly importeth Idolatry: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it ought of it ſelfe and in its owne nature to be ſhunned, as Idolatrous, as long as religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous worſhip is yeelded. For, otherwiſe it were not Idolatry to worſhip the very Idolls of the Gentiles made of any materiall ſtuffe, beeing that in that very matter whatſoeuer, there is the preſence of the true God. Nor will that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe ſerue in ſaying, <hi>I doe not adore the Statue, or Image; but God in them.</hi> The action in it ſelfe is directly terminated vpon the Statue, or <hi>Image:</hi> neither doth it ſuffice for the preuenting of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry, that the intention is directed vnto
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:18039:88" rendition="simple:additions"/>God, becauſe there doth remaine at the leaſt materiall, and externall Idolatry euen in the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious and learned, that know how to frame theſe abſtract notions: but in the vulgar ide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots there will be no leſſe then formall Idolatry. And therefore on all hands, all religious wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Statues and <hi>Images,</hi> euen of the Croſſe, and of <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, would be altogether ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed out of Chriſtendome: much more thoſe of <hi>Our Lady,</hi> and of other Saints, beeing that no religious worſhip at all is due vnto thoſe <hi>Images,</hi> or to thoſe Saints, whom they repreſent. Remember how Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſt, when hee would haue worſhipped the Angell, was by the Angell himſelfe forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with this Caueat, <hi>See thou do it not; for, I am thy fellow-ſeruant.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 22.9.</note> And ſurely Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> neuer meant to adore that Angell as God, with the worſhip called <hi>latria,</hi> proper to God onely: for, he well knew, that this was an Angell: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee bowed himſelfe to him with a religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous act, the Angell hindered him, knowing that ſuch an act was vnlawfull: how much more vnlawfull were it to bee done to an <hi>Image?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if you would cleere the matter, whether
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:18039:88" rendition="simple:additions"/>this worſhip be vſed to be giuen to the <hi>Image</hi> it ſelfe, as an <hi>Image,</hi> or to the <hi>prototype</hi> in the <hi>Image:</hi> looke into your Churches, &amp; houſes, whether the ſame adoration be yeelded to all Crucifixes, &amp; to all the <hi>Images</hi> of the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> equally, of all which the <hi>prototype</hi> or principall is the ſame: or whether there bee not rather a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in the adoring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Surely you ſhall find very great difference between one <hi>Image</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, both being of the ſame principall. Of <hi>Our Ladie's Images</hi> you ſhall haue in the ſame Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in diuers Churches, and houſes ſome, that are not ſo much as looked after, and yet one of them in ſome other Church ſhall bee frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with infinite concourſe of people. That of <hi>Loretto</hi> ſhall haue farre better doings, then that of <hi>Mont-ferrate,</hi> and ſo likewiſe of others. Therefore the vſuall worſhip is proper vnto the <hi>Image,</hi> and not to the <hi>prototype,</hi> or originall which it repreſents.</p>
               <p>Obſerue alſo the diſorders which are to bee found, not onely in the common people, and ſimple women, but alſo in thoſe, that are repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted diſcreet, and graue: when they come into a Church, if there be there any famous Statue, or <hi>Image</hi> of <hi>Our Lady,</hi> loaden with vowes, gli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtering
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:18039:89" rendition="simple:additions"/>with tapers, richly clad in gold and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, ſhut vp in ſhrines, and ſuch like, this muſt bee the firſt, that is viſited: after they haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dored the <hi>Image</hi> of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> then, for faſhion ſake, they goe to the Altar of the moſt bleſſed Sacrament, as they call it, where they ſuppoſe, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe is really and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally preſent: or if there bee no ſuch Altar there, then they firſt worſhip <hi>Our Lady</hi> dight in that man<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>er, and goe afterwards to the Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifixe; or rather for the moſt part doe not at all viſite it. How many huge tapers, and whole torches ſhall you ſee burning before the <hi>Image</hi> of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> of St. <hi>George,</hi> of St. <hi>Charles,</hi> or ſome other Saint, but before the Crucifixe ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther none at all, or a petty farthing-candle. Is this to reflect from the <hi>Image</hi> to the <hi>prototype?</hi> Is not this to commit Idolatry, and to preferre the ſeruant before the Maſter, the creature be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Creator? Is not this to put more affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in a Saint, then in <hi>Christ,</hi> and to expect more helpe from a Saint, then from <hi>Chriſt</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe? There is no one thing, whereby poore I am more defamed, and ſhamed among the Iewes, Turkes, and Pagans, then by theſe Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latries: Fly therefore from them.</p>
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:18039:89"/>
               <p>The <hi>Reliques</hi> of Saincts, if they be true, and proued ſo to bee, are to bee layed vp in honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable buriall, and kept in decent places, and are to ſerue your turne, my Children, as a memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall of the holy actions of that Sainct for your imitation. Yee are therefore to reſpect them with ciuill honour, as the members of God's principall ſeruants: but as for religious and ſpirituall worſhip, as it cannot without Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try be afforded to their ſoules now glorified in heauen, ſo is it much leſſe due vnto their aſhes, and dead bones, and leaſt of all to their Images: thoſe <hi>Reliques</hi> hauing in themſelues no diuine power at all, nor any Spirituall qualitie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they may doe you any helpe. And if God, in loue vnto his Saincts, that remaine with him in glory, vouchſafe to do you any fauour, it is he himſelfe, that doth it, and not the Sainct, much leſſe any <hi>Relique,</hi> or image of a Sainct. So alſo when God did patiently beare with the ſinnes of the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> euen to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning them their Idolatries, for the loue which he bare to <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Iacob:</hi> and when hee deferred the diſmembring of <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon's</hi> Kingdome, and pardoned many faults to his ſucceſſors Kings of Iudah for his beloued
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:18039:90"/>
                  <hi>Dauid's</hi> ſake, the thanks then were not due nor rendered to <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> nor to <hi>Dauid,</hi> but to God. So alſo may you intreate God to graunt you ſome fauours for the loue, which he beareth vnto his Saincts: but yee are not to begge thoſe fauours of the Saints them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, nor of their <hi>Reliques,</hi> nor of their <hi>Images:</hi> and hauing obteined thoſe fauours, you are to repay your thanks, and ſhew your gratitude to God onely, not vnto the Saincts, nor to any their <hi>Reliques,</hi> or <hi>Images.</hi> But, beſides all this, you may be ſure, that there are innumerable impoſtures put vpon you concerning <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques,</hi> and that, perhaps for the moſt part, the bones of knaues are ſhewed to you for the bones of Saincts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="rock">
               <head>¶ The ſixt Rocke. Merits.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Popiſh Maſters extoll <hi>Meritorious</hi> workes, eſpecially Almes; and will haue them deſerue eternall life: but their intent is, that you, being drawne on with the hope of ſo great gaine, may put out your
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:18039:90"/>money to vſe into their handes, to bring in a moſt plentifull intereſt of an hundred for one; but in the meane time they themſelues take the money, and make God your debtor both for the principall, &amp; for the vſe, in the life to come. And this their bearing you in hand with hope of ſo certaine, and infallible gaine makes the Prieſts and Friars to ruffle it out vpon your purſes: and you for your parts, if you be not the wiſer, and take not heed of this dangerous Rocke, ſhall looſe both your ſtocke and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt; and ſuffering ſhipwracke, are like to bee drowned in the gulfe of eternall puniſhment.</p>
               <p>Know ye therefore, that the principal works, which are neceſſary, next after faith, to obtaine remiſſion of ſinnes, and God's grace in this life, with eternall glory in the next, doe conſiſt in the due obſeruation of Gods Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: that ſo by God's helpe hee may keepe ſinne aloofe from him. Theſe workes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, which conſiſt in keeping the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, are neceſſary, in aſmuch as God will not iuſtifie, nor ſaue any man, that obſtinately remaineth in ſinne, and reſolutely holdeth on his way in offending his heauenly Maieſtie. Therefore a true and liuely faith, whereby a
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:18039:91"/>Chriſtian layeth hold on <hi>Christ,</hi> hath this ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that it mollifieth, and ſweetneth his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and loue towards God, and ſo it hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth him off from ſinne, and maketh him hate it. But theſe workes being neceſſary diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, without which God admitteth none into fauour, do not <hi>merit</hi> any ſupernaturall reward. For, God doeth not therefore receiue thee into fauour, becauſe thou haſt kept his Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, as though he were bound to receiue thee into his fauour for ſuch thy obſeruance: it is not ſo. In theſe performances thou haſt but done thy duety, remouing for thy owne behoofe the obſtakle &amp; impediment of ſinne, but God by his meere grace doeth accept thee as his owne: neither were it a receiuing thee into grace, if thy workes did deſerue grace: for, reward is giuen vnto deſert, nor by way of grace, but by way of Iuſtice. And yet Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it ſelfe, remiſſion of ſinnes, and adoption to become a ſonne of an enemy, theſe come from God, as a meere grace, meere bounty, and meere mercy. Thou art not therefore to boaſt of any ſuch workes, nor to flatter thy ſelfe for them, nor to acknowledge any <hi>merit</hi> at all in them: <hi>When ye haue done all thoſe things which are
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:18039:91" rendition="simple:additions"/>commanded you,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Chriſt</hi>) <hi>then ſay,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 17.10.</note> 
                  <hi>We are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable ſeruants, we haue done that, which was our duety to doe.</hi> Moreouer, ſuch performances haue in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for the moſt part, ſo much imperfection, that perhaps they haue in them more ſinne and demerit, then <hi>Merite,</hi> in regard of either vaine glory, or other humane ends, and ſuch like faulty circumſtances.</p>
               <p>Onely <hi>Chriſt's Merits</hi> are they, which being duely applied vnto a man, make God to holde himſelfe fully ſatisfied for the diſhonour, and offence taken at man, and by vertue of ſuch, and no other ſatisfaction, God receiueth a man in fauour, becauſe he ſeeth him by a liuely, and working faith inueſted in <hi>Chriſt</hi> as with the wedding-garment; and for this garments ſake he accepteth him at the mariage of glory: but whoſoeuer entreth into that heauenly ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet arayed onely with his owne garments, his owne works, and proper <hi>merits,</hi> if he come not in couered with this nuptiall garment of <hi>Chriſts</hi> righteouſnes, and <hi>Merits,</hi> he ſhall be ſure to be caſſiered; and <hi>caſt out into vtter darkenes, where ſhall be wailing and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi> And therefore, not onely iuſtification, remiſſion of ſinnes, adoption into God's Sonneſhip are to
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:18039:92" rendition="simple:additions"/>be accounted the free grace of God, which hath no other foundation, then <hi>Chriſt's</hi> onely <hi>Merits,</hi> applied vnto man by God's meere grace and bountie, but alſo eſſentiall glory it ſelfe, and eternall life is to be attributed to the ſame. For, God, when hee adopteth for his ſonne a man iuſtified by him, and that through his meere grace, for the <hi>Merits</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> onely, at the ſame time alſo, for full meaſure of the ſame grace, and for the ſame <hi>Merits</hi> alone, God doth deſtinate vnto him the euerlaſting inheritance of the eſſentiall glory of Paradiſe. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to affirme, that Chriſtians by their good workes doe purchaſe eternall life, is to auouch a groſſe and ſiniſter falſhood: as alſo to affirme that good workes, done euen in grace, are <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious</hi> of eternall life. For, eternall life is a meere fauour done vnto men, being purchaſed for them by the onely <hi>Merits</hi> of <hi>Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet for all this, good works are not to ſmall purpoſe, or vnprofitable to men. Firſt, becauſe the keeping of the Commandements is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies neceſſary, in ſuch ſort as I haue declared; and without them ſhall no man euer be ſaued, though no man be ſaued by them. Moreouer other good works, which of themſelues come
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:18039:92" rendition="simple:additions"/>not vnder commandement, are many times very profitable, and ſometimes neceſſary alſo for the keeping of the Commandements: as mortification of the fleſh, to the end that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence draw not to diſloyaltie; for which cauſe euen S. <hi>Paul kept his body vnder,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.27.</note> 
                  <hi>and brought it into ſubiection, lest by any meanes he, preaching to others, might himſelfe be a caſt-away.</hi> And for the ſame cauſe he exhorted the Coloſſians alſo to <hi>mortifie their members.</hi> Hither looke all faſtings,
<note place="margin">Col. 3.5.</note> watchings, continuall prayers, and other ſuch holy exerciſes; not to any making God a deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, nor to any obliging him to recompence them with eternall life; nor to any hoarding vp a treaſure of mens owne <hi>merits,</hi> but to reſiſt euill deſires: and therefore a man is bound e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnder paine of ſinne to vndergoe them for his owne behoofe, and for the great need, which he hath to ſtand aloofe from ſinne. To this only purpoſe long ſince in my yong yeres, Monaſteries, deſerts, ſolitary places, caues, and dennes were repleniſhed, not to procure <hi>merite</hi> by ſuch exerciſes, nor that they might thus purchaſe Paradiſe, but that the looſing of it might be thus preuented, and that the walke of the Tempter might be ſtopped, and the neere
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:18039:93"/>occaſions of ſinne taken away: Whereas now many Monaſteries are the ſchooles of vice, and of many heynous impieties, and, in a man<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>er, the proper lodges of ſinne and Satan; or, at the beſt, the Seminaries of ambition, the recepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of auarice, and the ſties to fat vp idle fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes: and generally all of them are the ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons of the Popes ſouldiers, and of his catchpoles for the maintenance of the Papacy, with all the enormities thereof, by the helpe of theſe irregular <hi>Regulars,</hi> who are bolſtred vp with many priuiledges granted by the Popes, being withdrawne from the iuriſdiction of Biſhops, to the end that they may become ſpies, champions, and very <hi>Pandars</hi> to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacie, not for venery, but to ſerue his turne for worſe vſurpations, and oppreſſions.</p>
               <p>Another benefit of good works is, that they ſerue to diſcharge the obligation, and debt, wherein euery Chriſtian is bound to bee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable in his duety to God, and to ſerue him faithfully, and to promote the glory of ſo great, and bountifull a Maſter. A bond-ſlaue, if he be good, will of himſelfe, without looking for ſtripes, ſeeke out occaſions faithfully to ſerue his good Maſter, and, doing his <hi>deuoire,</hi> doth
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:18039:93"/>not thereupon reckon his diligent ſeruice vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the title of his owne loanes, and of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter's debts.
<note place="margin">Mat 7.17.</note> A good tree of it ſelfe <hi>bringeth forth good fruit:</hi> yet doth not the planter and owner take vp that fruit on credit, or accompt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a debtor to the tree; but enioyes the fruit, as his owne, and due to him, <hi>gramercé</hi> his good planting, and huſbanding. To this purpoſe ſaid <hi>Chriſt, Let your light ſo ſhine before men,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 5.16.</note> 
                  <hi>that they may ſee your good workes, and glorifie your father, which is in heauen.</hi> Likewiſe Saint <hi>Peter</hi> maketh the ſame vſe of them,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.12.</note> 
                  <hi>That the Gentiles beholding your good works may glorifie God.</hi> And to this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying of God euery of you is bound in duty, nor can challenge any reward vpon ſo doing.</p>
               <p>Moreouer good workes done in grace, doe help on the encreaſe of your loue toward God, and towards your neighbour, and ſet forward a iuſt man to become ſtill more iuſt. In relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereunto ſome kind of <hi>merit,</hi> but very im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly ſo called, may bee attributed vnto good workes; in that God in his bounty is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to reward man's imperfect operations, with ſuch encreaſes of his heauenly gifts, and graces. So Saint <hi>Paul</hi> exhorteth the faithfull <hi>to ſerue righteouſneſſe, vnto ſanctification:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 6.16.</note> that
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:18039:94" rendition="simple:additions"/>is, that they might become ſtill more holy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Semblable</hi> thereto is that in the Reuelation, <hi>He that is iust,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 22.11.</note> 
                  <hi>let him be made iuſt ſtill.</hi> Yet is not this any true <hi>merit:</hi> becauſe the workes of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, though done in grace, yet haue no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to ſuch a reward; and, if it were not for God's gracious promiſe, they ſhould neuer receiue ſuch a reward, as by iuſtice is not due vnto them. For, euen theſe workes are to bee attributed rather to the grace of God, by whoſe helpe they are performed, then vnto man. Therefore God, in beſtowing theſe gifts, doth rather reward his owne gifts, and graces, then any worke of man. And yet for all this no man can bee ſaide to <hi>merit</hi> eternall life by his workes, as you ſee.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, good workes performed in the ſtate of grace by the faithfull, (eſpecially thoſe, which in the aforeſaid reſpects doe neither di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly, nor indirectly come vnder neceſſary obligation) haue from God, out of his meere bounty, and liberality, a promiſe of reward, which ſhall bee afforded them in the world to come: And this reward is not the eſſentials of eternall life it ſelfe, but certaine degrees, and ouer-meaſures of glory. The Pſalmiſt ſaith to
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:18039:94"/>God;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 62.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou rendereſt to euery man according to his worke.</hi> And St. <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Our light affliction worketh for vs an eternall weight of glory.</hi> And <hi>Chriſt</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe promiſeth,
<note place="margin">Marc. 9.41.</note> that <hi>whoſoeuer ſhall giue his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples a cup of cold water in his name, ſhall not loſe his reward.</hi> Of which kind of promiſes the Scripture hath plenty: Yet doth it not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon follow, that ſuch works are truely <hi>merits,</hi> or <hi>meritorious.</hi> For, that onely is true <hi>merit,</hi> to which the reward is due by iuſtice, without the entercourſe of any fauour at all. And, where grace is afforded,
<note place="margin">Rom. 11.6.</note> there all <hi>merit</hi> is exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. But in theſe good workes grace beares a great part. Firſt, in that a man doth them by the power of grace: and therefore S.
<note place="margin">Aug de gra. &amp; lib. arb. c. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaid, that <hi>God crowneth not man's merits, but his own gifts.</hi> Alſo becauſe it is out of meere grace that God promiſeth a reward; ſuch promiſes being made, not out of iuſtice, but from meere boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. As when a Prince, not being obliged to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, proclaimeth a prize for him, that ſhall runne beſt in a race, it is certaine that this running is not properly a <hi>merit;</hi> being it hath no propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the prize, which is of great valew: and if it were not for the bountie of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, that running were not of any worth at all.</p>
               <pb n="168" facs="tcp:18039:95"/>
               <p>But yet, all theſe graces being ſuppoſed, when as the Scripture willingly calleth by the name of rewards all thoſe gifts, and heauenly remunerations, which are promiſed vnto workes, ſome kinde of <hi>merit</hi> cannot be denied. For, ſurely reward doeth imply a relation, and correſpondence to ſome <hi>merit.</hi> But yee muſt take with you, that this <hi>merit</hi> hath no relation to the eſſentials of eternall life; as alſo that it ſuppoſeth all theſe graces. Whereupon you are not to rely vpon your <hi>merits,</hi> nor to build the frame of your ſaluation vpon them; being that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is your entire foundation. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore put all your hopes, both in life, and death, in him onely, and build no foundation at all, for your hope of eternall life, and of your e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting ſaluation, vpon your owne workes done, or to bee done in pious Legacies, in Maſſes, in Almes, or for Altars, or Churches. For, if you doe not take another courſe to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine eternall life by a true and liuely <hi>faith, which worketh by loue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 5.6.</note> remouing alſo betimes the obſtacles of ſinne by true, and ſincere re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, your owne <hi>merits</hi> ſhall not (much leſſe any others) any whit benefit you, but as for encreaſe of glory, and augmenting of your
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:18039:95" rendition="simple:additions"/>ioy, good workes will be very helpfull to you, ſo that they be throughly purified, and employed on lawfull things, and free from ſuperſtition, and euill circumſtances.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>THus haue I diſcouered to you, my moſt deare children, twelue principall very dangerous Rocks: which I haue but briefly ſhewed, and litle more then pointed at; inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as I haue ſure confidence in my Spouſe (by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue bin put in truſt to giue you the diſcouery of them) that he will himſelfe at length ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all your eies. I ſee, that he hath very very long had patience with the many errors of that, his, and mine, vngratefull daughter, your, not louing mother (for that am I) but cruel ſtepdame; and that now, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding her at her highest, he will no longer beare with her. He by his gentle Spirit wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in the hearts of great</hi> Princes, (<hi>yea and of great</hi> Prelats <hi>too</hi>) <hi>his, &amp; my ſonnes: he goes on taking away the manifold falſe
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:18039:96"/>preiudices, and deluſions: hee by little and little mollifieth thoſe obdurations, &amp; obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacies, whereby enormities, ſo preiudiciall to mee, and ſo pernicious to you are wilfully mainteined. They begin to acknowledge, that in</hi> Rome, <hi>not</hi> Chriſt, <hi>but the world ſwayeth the ſcepter, and that all my affaires there are reduced to temporall ends onely. He putteth theſe</hi> Princes <hi>in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance, that they are my nurſing-fathers, my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectors, my defendors; and moreouer, that it lieth on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to bring home all my daughters to me their vniuerſall Mother; and not to ſuffer one of them to tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nize ouer both her Mother, and other ſisters. Whereupon my ſelfe, with very good hope, doe expect from Chriſtian Princes, and Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealths all good iſsue of a perfect peace, vnion, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord on my behalfe. In the meane time I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe you, to take good notice of theſe Rocks, and to take ſuch heed of them, that ye may
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:18039:96" rendition="simple:additions"/>eſchew your owne lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>table wracke. So the bleſſed gale of the holy Spirit co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>duct you ſafe to the hauen of eternall happines. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>THE AVTHOR TO the godly Readers.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Et this Manuell, Chriſtian Readers, ſerue you onely for an eſſay, or rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draught of a larger worke, wherein the ſame Heads, which are here but briefly pointed at, as alſo other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters bordering thereon, are to be more particularly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted, and commodiouſly enlarged. And I hope, that I ſhall let in ſo much light vnto you, that you ſhall by God's grace be enabled to enterteine many trueths belonging to your ſoules health, which for long time haue bene, with no good meaning, kept out of your ſight. If you pleaſe to accept theſe my firſt lineaments, you may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from me the more diligent accompliſhment of the entire worke: wherein will appeare other Rockes alſo worthy the diſcouering, to the praiſe of our Sauiour</hi> IESVS CHRIST, <hi>to the ſafety of our ſoules, and to the confuſion of the Diuell. God be with you euermore.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
